<opinion>
<reporter_caption><center>REYNOLDS MET. v. ST. DEP., IND. R., <citation>792 So.2d 431</citation> (Ala.Civ.App. 2000)</center></reporter_caption>
<caption><center>Reynolds Metals Company v. State Department of Industrial Relations et al.</center></caption>
<docket><center>Nos. 2990993 to 2991001.</center></docket><court><center>Court of Civil Appeals of Alabama.</center></court>
<date><center>Decided October 20, 2000.</center>

</date>
<posture>  Appeals from Colbert Circuit Court (CV-00-19 through CV-00-27).

</posture><attorneys>  William F. Gardner and Joseph V. Musso of Cabaniss, Johnston, Gardner, Dumas  O'Neal, Birmingham; and Braxton W. Ashe of Ashe, Tanner, Wright  Kelley, Tuscumbia, for appellant.

Frank D. Marsh, general Counsel, Department of Industrial Relations, for appellee.

</attorneys>
<opinion_byline>  ROBERTSON, Presiding Judge.

</opinion_byline>
<opinion_text>  These nine consolidated appeals from judgments of the Colbert County Circuit Court arise from the same facts as those presented in <underline>Reynolds</underline><underline>Metals Co. v. State Dep't of Industrial Relations</underline>, <cross_reference>792 So.2d 419</cross_reference>
(Ala.Civ.App. 2000) ("<underline>Reynolds I</underline>"), which involved consolidated appeals from a circuit court in an adjacent county. On the authority of <underline>Reynolds I</underline>, we conclude that the Department of Industrial Relations, as a matter of law, properly awarded unemployment-compensation benefits to the workers<footnote_reference>[fn1]</footnote_reference> involved in these nine cases, and that the trial court's summary judgments are due to be affirmed.<footnote_reference>[fn2]</footnote_reference>

AFFIRMED.

Yates, Monroe, and Thompson, JJ., concur.

Crawley, J., dissents.

<footnote_body><footnote_number>[fn1]</footnote_number> Stewart Fuller; Joel Retherford; Jimmy Booker; Gene Whitlock; James E. Brown; Percy T. Glover; Sandra Cheatham; Billy Aday; and William Hester.</footnote_body>

<footnote_body><footnote_number>[fn2]</footnote_number> There is evidence that two of the workers (Billy Aday and William Hester) submitted affidavits in the trial court in which they stated that they were <underline>not</underline> offered employment by Wise although they had sought such employment.  However, as in <underline>Reynolds I</underline>, that evidence has not been argued as a separate basis for affirming the judgments in those workers' cases, and we do not address the effect of that evidence.</footnote_body>

</opinion_text><dissent_byline>  CRAWLEY, Judge, dissenting.

</dissent_byline><dissent_text>  I dissent on the same grounds as I dissented in <underline>Reynolds Metal Co. v.</underline><underline>State Dep't of Indus. Rel</underline>., <cross_reference>792 So.2d 419</cross_reference> (Ala.Civ.App. 2000) (Crawley, J., dissenting).<page_number>Page 432</page_number>

</dissent_text>
</opinion>