<opinion>
<reporter_caption><center>STATE v. STRONG, <citation>70 S.W.3d 612</citation> (Mo.App.E.D. 2002)</center></reporter_caption>
<caption><center>State of Missouri, Plaintiff/Respondent, v.</center><center>Darwyn D. Strong, Defendant/Appellant.</center></caption>
<docket><center>No. ED 79308.</center></docket><court><center>Missouri Court of Appeals, Eastern District,</center><center>Division Two.</center></court>
<date><center>March 5, 2002.</center>

</date>
<opinion_text>[EDITORS' NOTE:  THIS OPINION IS SUBJECT TO MODIFICATION OR TRANSFER TO THE SUPREME COURT.]

</opinion_text>
<posture>  Appeal from the Circuit Court of the City of St. Louis, Honorable Evelyn M. Baker.

</posture><attorneys>  Douglas R. Hoff,  Asst. Public Defender, St. Louis, MO, for Appellant.

Jeremiah W. (Jay) Nixon, Attorney General, Anne E. Edgington, Assistant Attorney General, Jefferson City, MO, for Respondent.

</attorneys><panel>  Before George W. Draper III, P.J. and Mary R. Russell, J. and Mary K. Hoff, J.

</panel>
<opinion_text><center>                                   <underline>ORDER</underline></center></opinion_text>
<opinion_byline>  PER CURIAM.

</opinion_byline>
<opinion_text>  Darwyn D. Strong (Defendant) appeals the judgment and sentence entered after a jury verdict finding him guilty of one count of first-degree murder in violation of Section <cross_reference>565.020</cross_reference> RSMo 1994<footnote_reference>[fn1]</footnote_reference> (Count I), three counts of armed criminal action in violation of Section <cross_reference>571.015</cross_reference> (Counts II, IV, VI), one count of first-degree robbery in violation of Section<cross_reference>569.020</cross_reference> (Count III), and one count of first-degree assault in violation of Section <cross_reference>565.050</cross_reference> (Count V).  The trial court sentenced Defendant to concurrent and consecutive terms of imprisonment<page_number>Page 613</page_number>
aggregating a total of life without the possibility of parole plus forty years.

We have reviewed the briefs of the parties, the legal file, and the record on appeal, and find the claim of error to be without merit.  No error of law appears.  An extended opinion reciting the detailed facts and restating the principles of law would have no jurisprudential purpose.  Judgment affirmed in accordance with Rule 30.25(b).

The parties have been furnished with a memorandum for their information only, setting forth the reasons for the order affirming the judgment pursuant to Rule 30.25(b).

<footnote_body><footnote_number>[fn1]</footnote_number> Unless otherwise noted, all subsequent statutory citations are to RSMo 1994.</footnote_body>

</opinion_text>
</opinion>