<opinion>
<reporter_caption><center>COMMONWEALTH v. JENKINS, <citation>224 Va. 456</citation> (1982)</center></reporter_caption>
<citation_line><center><citation>297 S.E.2d 692</citation></center></citation_line>
<caption><center>COMMONWEALTH OF VIRGINIA, DEPARTMENT OF MENTAL HEALTH AND MENTAL</center><center>RETARDATION v. JAMES L. JENKINS</center></caption>
<docket><center>44399</center><center>Record No. 801980.</center></docket><court><center>Supreme Court of Virginia.</center></court>
<date><center>December 3, 1982</center>

</date><panel>  Present: All the Justices.

</panel>
<syllabus>  Person civilly committed pursuant to Code <cross_reference>37.1-67.1</cross_reference> et seq., after previous confinement under Code Sec. <cross_reference>19.2-169</cross_reference>, is required under Code Sec. <cross_reference>37.1-105</cross_reference> to pay for expenses of care, treatment and maintenance, person being a patient and not an "inmate".

(1) Institutions for Mentally Ill — Admissions — Involuntary Detention (Code Sec. <cross_reference>37.1-67.1</cross_reference> <italic>et seq.</italic>) — Criminal Procedure — Raising Question of Sanity, Etc. [Code Sec.<cross_reference>19.2-169</cross_reference> (repealed 1982, material now appearing in Code Sections <cross_reference>19.2-168.1</cross_reference>, -169.1 and -169.3)] — Who is Liable for Expenses (Code Sec. <cross_reference>37.1-105</cross_reference>) — Statutory Construction — Accused Liable for Expenses While Civilly Committed Pursuant to Code Sec. <cross_reference>37.1-67.1</cross_reference> <italic>et seq.</italic> Although Previously Confined Pursuant to Code Sec. <cross_reference>19.2-169</cross_reference>.

(2) Criminal Procedure — Raising Question of Sanity, Etc. [Code Sec. <cross_reference>19.2-169</cross_reference> (repealed 1982, material now appearing in Code Sections <cross_reference>19.2-168.1</cross_reference>, -169.1 and -169.3)] — Institutions for Mentally Ill — Admissions — Involuntary Detention (Code Sec. <cross_reference>37.1-67.1</cross_reference> <italic>et seq.</italic>) — Who is Liable for Expenses (Code Sec. <cross_reference>37.1-105</cross_reference>) — Statutory Construction — Specific Language of Code Sec. <cross_reference>19.2-169</cross_reference> Subjects Accused to Provisions of Title 37.1 and Thus to "Pay Requirements" of Code Sec. <cross_reference>37.1-105</cross_reference>.

(3) Institutions for Mentally Ill — Admissions — Involuntary Detention — (Code Sec. <cross_reference>37.1-67.1</cross_reference> <italic>et seq.</italic>) — Definitions — Patient [Code Sec. <cross_reference>37.1-1</cross_reference>(16)] — Criminal Procedure — Raising Question of Sanity, Etc. [Code Sec.<cross_reference>19.2-169</cross_reference> (repealed 1982, material now appearing in Code Sections <cross_reference>19.2-168.1</cross_reference>, -169.1 and 169.3)] — Statutory Construction — Accused Civilly Committed Involuntarily is Patient under Code Sec. <cross_reference>37.1-1</cross_reference>(16) and Treated as Patient Rather Than Inmate, Only Distinction Being Notice Requirement by Director of Facility Under Code Sec. <cross_reference>19.2-168.1</cross_reference>.

(4) Institutions for Mentally Ill — Who is Liable for Expenses (Code Sec. <cross_reference>37.1-105</cross_reference>) — Application for Order to Compel Payment of Expenses (Code Sec. <cross_reference>37.1-110</cross_reference>) — Statutory Construction — When Evidence of Ability to Pay, Commonwealth Required to Proceed Under Mandate of Code Sec. <cross_reference>37.1-110</cross_reference>.<page_number>Page 457</page_number>

Defendant, charged with murder, was committed for observation and evaluation to Southwestern State Hospital pursuant to Code Sec. <cross_reference>19.2-169</cross_reference>. He was determined incompetent to stand trial and under Code Sec. <cross_reference>19.2-169</cross_reference> was committed civilly for treatment pursuant to Code Sec. <cross_reference>37.1-67</cross_reference> <italic>et seq.</italic> This period of hospitalization for treatment ran from 12 May 1977 through 13 July 1978. He was then released into the custody of the Sheriff and remained in jail until the Spring of 1979 when he was again referred for observational evaluation pursuant to Code Sec.<cross_reference>19.2-169</cross_reference>, found incompetent to stand trial and was again civilly committed pursuant to Code Sec. <cross_reference>37.1-67.1</cross_reference> <italic>et seq.</italic>
remaining in the hospital from 23 May 1979 through 31 March 1980. Pursuant to Code Sections <cross_reference>37.1-105</cross_reference> and -110 the Commonwealth sought reimbursement of the charges for care, treatment and maintenance of defendant during the periods of commitment for treatment from 12 May 1977 through 13 July 1978 and from 23 May 1979 through 31 March 1980. The Trial Judge, on the theory that defendant was an inmate during the entire period beginning with his arrest through March, 1980, denied recovery. The Commonwealth appeals.

1. A person is liable under Code Sec. <cross_reference>37.1-105</cross_reference> for the expenses of his care, treatment and maintenance while civilly committed to a state hospital pursuant to Code Sec. <cross_reference>37.1-67.1</cross_reference><italic>et seq.</italic> even though previously confined to the facility for observation and evaluation under Code Sec. <cross_reference>19.2-169</cross_reference> (now repealed and superseded by Code Sections <cross_reference>19.2-168.1</cross_reference>, -169.1 and -169.3).

2. The specific language of Code Sec. <cross_reference>19.2-169</cross_reference> subjects the accused to the provisions of Title 37.1 if the accused requires hospitalization for the treatment of his mental disease; and the accused, having been twice so committed, is subject to the provisions of Code Sec. <cross_reference>37.1-105</cross_reference> which renders him liable for the two periods of hospitalization.

3. When an accused is civilly committed under Title 37.1, he is not under the direct control of the criminal authorities during his incompetency, being defined in Code Sec. <cross_reference>37.1-1</cross_reference>(16) as a patient. He is, as a practical matter, being handled as a "patient" and not as an "inmate" except for the notice to authorities required by the facility director pursuant to Code Sec. <cross_reference>19.2-169</cross_reference> at least ten days prior to the unconditional release or discharge of the accused.

4. The Commonwealth was required to proceed under the mandate of Code Sec. <cross_reference>37.1-110</cross_reference> which requires payment by the patient when there is evidence of ability to pay.

</syllabus>
<posture>  Appeal from a judgment of the Circuit Court of Smyth County. Hon. J. Aubrey Matthews, judge presiding.

<italic>Reversed and remanded.</italic>

</posture><attorneys>  Dennis G. Merrill, Assistant Attorney General (Marshall Coleman, Attorney General; Walter H. Ryland, Chief Deputy Attorney General, on briefs), for appellant.<page_number>Page 458</page_number>

Richard A. Money (Lowe and Money, P.C., on brief), for appellee.

</attorneys>
<opinion_byline>  COMPTON, J., delivered the opinion of the Court.

</opinion_byline>
<opinion_text>  The question presented is whether a person charged with a crime and civilly committed to a State mental hospital is liable to the Commonwealth for expenses incurred for care, treatment, and maintenance at such facility.

The appellant, Commonwealth of Virginia Department of Mental Health and Mental Retardation, filed suit in 1980 in the court below against appellee James L. Jenkins, a patient in Southwestern State Hospital in Marion. Alleging Jenkins had incurred certain charges while a patient there, the Commonwealth sought a judgment against Jenkins for $19,921 due as of March 31, 1980. Following an <italic>ore tenus</italic> hearing at which the facts were stipulated, the trial court denied the claim and dismissed the suit with prejudice in a September 1980 order, from which we awarded the Commonwealth an appeal.

Jenkins was taken into custody and charged in Radford with murder. On February 15, 1977, he was committed by court order to Southwestern State Hospital for observation, pursuant to Code Sec. <cross_reference>19.2-169</cross_reference>.<footnote_reference>[fn1]</footnote_reference>

The hospital staff determined Jenkins was not mentally competent to stand trial. Thus, according to other provisions of Sec. <cross_reference>19.2-169</cross_reference> <italic>infra,</italic> Jenkins was committed to the care of the hospital<page_number>Page 459</page_number>
under the civil procedures provided in Chapter 2 of Title 37.1. He remained so committed from May 12, 1977 through July 13, 1978, the first period for which the Commonwealth seeks reimbursement of charges.

Jenkins then was found competent to stand trial. He was released from the hospital into the custody of the Sheriff of the City of Radford. He remained in jail from July of 1978 until the Spring of 1979, when his mental condition deteriorated and a question again was raised about his competence to stand trial. Accordingly, he was referred a second time to Southwestern State Hospital pursuant to a new order entered under Sec. <cross_reference>19.2-169</cross_reference>.

When the 45-day observation period expired, the hospital staff again determined he was not competent to stand trial. Consequently, a second civil commitment order was entered placing Jenkins under the care of the hospital. He remained civilly committed at that facility from May 23, 1979 through March 31, 1980, the second period for which the State seeks reimbursement of charges.

Denying the Commonwealth's claim, the trial judge reasoned that Jenkins had been an "inmate" of the State correctional facilities during the entire period beginning with his arrest in February of 1977 through March of 1980. The court noted that Jenkins was charged with a crime, was committed to a State hospital for observation under Sec. <cross_reference>19.2-169</cross_reference> with a warrant pending against him, was found incompetent to stand trial, and was committed to the same hospital for care, treatment, and maintenance. He ruled that under such circumstances Jenkins was an "inmate" of either the jail or the hospital and, "as such," there was "no difference" in the period of observation under Sec. <cross_reference>19.2-169</cross_reference>, for which the State did not charge, and in the period of hospitalization under Title 37.1, a mere "technical change in commitment," for which a charge was made. We disagree.<footnote_reference>[fn2]</footnote_reference>

[1] We are of opinion that the applicable statutes provide in plain terms that a person is liable for the expenses of his care, treatment, and maintenance when confined to a State hospital<page_number>Page 460</page_number>
pursuant to Title 37.1, even though he previously had been confined to the facility pursuant to Code Sec. <cross_reference>19.2-169</cross_reference> as a person charged with crime.

In addition to the provisions already noted, <italic>supra,</italic> Sec.<cross_reference>19.2-169</cross_reference> also provided that if a defendant, upon observation, is found mentally incompetent to stand trial

"or requires hospitalization for the treatment of his mental disease or defect, an appropriate <italic>court shall commit the</italic><italic>accused pursuant to the provisions of Sec. <cross_reference>37.1-67</cross_reference> of the Code</italic>
of Virginia and, thereafter, <italic>the accused shall be subject to</italic><italic>the provisions of Title 37.1</italic> with respect to treatment, care, transfer, discharge, <italic>and all other applicable sections.</italic>" (Emphasis added.)

Jenkins was committed twice under that provision pursuant to civil commitment orders entered under Code Sec. <cross_reference>37.1-67.1</cross_reference><italic>et seq.,</italic> the successors to Sec. <cross_reference>37.1-67</cross_reference>. Consequently, having been so committed, Jenkins was "subject to the provisions of Title 37.1" by virtue of the specific language of Sec.<cross_reference>19.2-169</cross_reference>.

Included within Title 37.1 is Code Sec. <cross_reference>37.1-105</cross_reference> which provided, in part:

"<italic>Any person</italic> who has been or who may be admitted to any State hospital . . . <italic>shall be liable</italic> for the expenses of his care, treatment and maintenance in such hospital . . . ." (Emphasis added.)<footnote_reference>[fn3]</footnote_reference>

The foregoing language, considered with the specific provisions of Sec. <cross_reference>19.2-169</cross_reference>, clearly fixes liability upon Jenkins for the two periods of hospitalization in question.

[3] The trial court based its decision on the conclusion that Jenkins was an "inmate" at all times during his stay in the State mental hospital. But the Attorney General points out "that there is no significant difference between the handling [by the hospital authorities] of patients incapable of standing trial and other involuntarily committed patients." He says the only apparent difference was set forth in Sec. <cross_reference>19.2-169</cross_reference>:<page_number>Page 461</page_number>

"[A]t least ten days prior to the unconditional release or discharge of such individual charged with a crime, the facility director shall notify the appropriate court or judge thereof, the appropriate attorney for the Commonwealth and the attorney for the accused of such intended release or discharge."

Thus, as the Attorney General notes, the hospital director could have authorized the patient's unconditional release, provided he notified the appropriate criminal justice authorities. Upon such notice, the clerk of court was required to issue a <italic>praecipe</italic> to an officer of the court directing him forthwith to bring the person from the hospital facility and commit him to jail or the custody from which he was removed. Code Sec. 19.2-171.<footnote_reference>[fn4]</footnote_reference>

Thus, when an accused is civilly committed under Title 37.1, he is not under the direct control of the criminal authorities during his incompetency. Moreover, Code Sec. <cross_reference>37.1-1</cross_reference>(16) defines one involuntarily admitted to a State hospital according to the provisions of Title 37.1 as a "patient." In short, as a practical matter as well as by statutory definition, Jenkins was a patient, not an inmate, during the periods in question.

Consequently, the Commonwealth was obligated to proceed against Jenkins according to the mandate of Code Sec. <cross_reference>37.1-110</cross_reference>, which provided, in part:

"Upon the failure of any patient . . . to make payment of [his expenses], and whenever it appears from investigation that such patient, . . . has sufficient estate, or there is evidence of ability to pay such expenses, the Department shall petition [the appropriate court] for an order to compel payment of such expenses by persons liable therefor. . . ."<footnote_reference>[fn5]</footnote_reference>

For these reasons, the judgment below will be reversed and the case will be remanded for a new trial limited solely to the issue of the amount due by Jenkins to the Commonwealth for reimbursement of expenses.

<italic>Reversed and remanded.</italic>

<footnote_body><footnote_number>[fn1]</footnote_number> That statute provided, in part:

If, prior to arraignment of any person charged with crime, either the court or attorney for the Commonwealth or counsel for the accused has reason to believe that such person, because of mental disease or defect, is in such mental condition that he lacks substantial capacity to understand the proceedings against him or to assist in his own defense, and it is necessary for evaluation and observation in order for the court to determine whether such person is mentally competent to plead and stand trial or understand the proceedings against him and assist in his own defense, the court or the judge thereof may, after hearing evidence or the representations of counsel on the subject, commit the accused to a State facility designated by the Commissioner of Mental Health and Mental Retardation for examination, evaluation, observation, and report if it is felt by the court that temporary hospitalization, not to exceed forty-five days, is required for such determination and such commitment shall be under such limitations as the court may order, pending the determination of his mental condition.

Section <cross_reference>19.2-169</cross_reference> was repealed by the 1982 General Assembly. Acts 1982, ch. 653. <italic>See</italic> Sections <cross_reference>19.2-168.1</cross_reference>, -169.1 and -169.3, for present provisions covering the same subject matter.</footnote_body>

<footnote_body><footnote_number>[fn2]</footnote_number> On appeal, Jenkins contends the Commonwealth failed to prove certain facts essential to sustain a recovery against him. Such an argument was not made in the trial court and will not be noted for the first time on appeal. Rule 5:21. Also, Jenkins mounts a broadside constitutional attack on the entire statutory scheme under which he was hospitalized. We are unable properly to consider these constitutional arguments because they are based, in part, on assumptions of fact which are not supported by the meager oral stipulation in the trial court.</footnote_body>

<footnote_body><footnote_number>[fn3]</footnote_number> In 1982, Sec. <cross_reference>37.1-105</cross_reference> was rewritten. Acts 1982. ch. 50.</footnote_body>

<footnote_body><footnote_number>[fn4]</footnote_number> Code Sec. 19.2-171 was also repealed in 1982. Acts 1982, ch. 653.</footnote_body>

<footnote_body><footnote_number>[fn5]</footnote_number> In 1982, 9 <cross_reference>37.1-110</cross_reference> was rewritten. Acts 1982, ch. 50.</footnote_body><page_number>Page 462</page_number>

</opinion_text>
</opinion>