<opinion>
<reporter_caption><center>WILMINGTON TRUST CO. v. CALPINE CORP., <citation>906 A.2d 807</citation> (Del. 2005)</center></reporter_caption>
<caption><center>WILMINGTON TRUST COMPANY, Solely in its capacity as Second Indenture Lien</center><center>Trustee, Defendant Below, Appellant, v. CALPINE CORPORATION, Plaintiff</center><center>Below, Appellee. CALPINE CORPORATION, Plaintiff Below,</center><center>Appellant/Cross-Appellee, v. BANK OF NEW YORK and WILMINGTON TRUST</center><center>COMPANY, Defendants Below, Appellees, and WILMINGTON TRUST COMPANY,</center><center>Solely in its Capacity as First Lien Indenture Trustee, Defendant Below,</center><center>Cross-Appellant.</center></caption>
<docket><center>Nos. 602 and 603, 2005 Consolidated.</center></docket><court><center>Supreme Court of Delaware.</center></court><hearing_date><center>Submitted: December 15, 2005.</center></hearing_date>
<date><center>Decided: December 16, 2005.</center>

</date>
<posture>  Court of Chancery of the State of Delaware, in and for New Castle County, C.A. No. 1669-N.

</posture><panel>  Before <bold>HOLLAND, BERGER</bold> and <bold>JACOBS,</bold> Justices.

</panel>
<opinion_text><center>                                  <bold><underline>ORDER</underline></bold></center></opinion_text>
<opinion_byline>  Jack B. Jacobs, Justice.

</opinion_byline>
<opinion_text>  This 16<superscript>th</superscript> day of December 2005, upon consideration of the briefs of the parties and the record in this case and oral argument, it appears to the Court that:

(1) This case involves multiple expedited appeals from an Order and Final Judgment ("Order") entered by the Court of Chancery on December 2, 2005, implementing its post-trial Opinion handed down on November 22, 2005 ("Opinion"),<footnote_reference>[fn*]</footnote_reference> and the rulings made at a hearing held on December 2, 2005. The exigencies of time do not permit us to elaborate, or even summarize, the bases for the parties' disputes or the trial court's reasoning and conclusions reached in deciding the multitudinous and complex factual and legal issues before it. We therefore have attached a copy of the Opinion and the Order for reference, and unless noted otherwise, adopt in this Order the terms used by the trial court in its Opinion.

(2) Three issues are presented in these appeals: (1) whether the Court of Chancery erred in determining that Calpine's use of approximately $312 million of the Rosetta Proceeds to purchase natural gas was not a permitted purchase of Designated Assets, and, therefore, must be restored to the Designated Asset Sales Proceeds Account ("DASPA"); (2) whether the trial court erroneously held that the First Lien Trustee lacked contractual standing to request a remedy for Calpine's adjudicated improper use of the approximately $312 million of Rosetta Proceeds and to assert its counterclaims against Calpine; and (3) whether the Court of Chancery abused its discretion in requiring the Restoration Proceeds to be re-deposited in the DASPA on January 22, 2006 rather than on an earlier date. We address those issues in that sequence.

<center>                       <bold><italic>The Designated Assets Issue</italic></bold></center>
(3) Calpine contests the trial court's determination that Calpine's use of approximately $312 million of the Rosetta Proceeds to purchase natural gas was not a permitted purchase of Designated Assets. Calpine argues, among other things, that the Court of Chancery misconstrued the distinction between natural gas assets and natural gas contracts, and mistakenly assumed that Designated Assets must be long-term natural gas reserves. After carefully considering Calpine's arguments, we conclude that the Court of Chancery correctly construed the exclusion contained in the definition of "Designated Assets," properly held that Calpine's purchases of natural gas using approximately $312 million of the Rosetta Proceeds were not purchases of Designated Assets, and validly determined that Calpine must restore the approximately $312 million of Rosetta Proceeds to the DASPA. Accordingly, we affirm those determinations on the basis of, and for the reasons set forth in, the Court of Chancery's well-reasoned and well-written Opinion.

<center>                     <bold><italic>The Contractual Standing Issue</italic></bold></center>
(4) The First Lien Trustee challenges that portion of the Opinion (and implementing provisions of the Order) adjudicating that the First Lien Trustee lacked contractual standing to seek (i) the restoration to the DASPA of approximately $312 million of the Rosetta Proceeds that Calpine had improperly withdrawn, or (2) any relief with respect to the approximately $400 million remaining in the DASPA. The Opinion also determined that First Lien Trustee lacked contractual standing to advance any of the counterclaims the First Lien Trustee had asserted against Calpine in this action, other than the counterclaim for indemnification of its litigation expenses. First Lien Trustee claims that those determinations were erroneous as a matter of law for two reasons.

(5) First, it argues, the trial court's "no contractual standing" rulings are predicated upon the Court of Chancery's determination (embodied in Paragraph 3 of the Order) that Calpine's use of the Rosetta Proceeds to make the June 2005 tender offer to the First Lien Noteholders extinguished any right of the First Lien Indenture Trustee to demand (i) the restoration of those Rosetta Proceeds that were withdrawn from the DASPA, or (ii) other relief with respect to the $400 million of Proceeds remaining in the DASPA Account. First Lien Trustee claims that that predicate determination was erroneous, because the tender offer made by Calpine was not a conforming Asset Sale Offer under the First Lien Indenture, which allowed Calpine to make a tender offer only after Calpine had received Net Proceeds from a sale of Designated Assets. The First Lien Trustee claims that because Calpine did not receive the Net Proceeds before commencing its tender offer, that offer was not a conforming Asset Sale Offer, and that the Court of Chancery erred in holding otherwise.

(6) Second, the First Lien Trustee claims that even if Calpine's tender offer for the First Lien Notes was a conforming Asset Sale Offer, the First Lien Trustee had significant contractual rights with respect to the collateral that were conferred by the Collateral and the Control Agreements, independent of whatever effect that tender offer may have had. The First Lien Trustee claims that in reaching its contrary conclusion, the Court of Chancery misconstrued those Agreements.

(7) After carefully considering the contentions of the parties and the record, we conclude the First Lien Trustee's first claim of error is without merit, and that the Court of Chancery correctly determined, for the reasons stated in its Opinion, that the June 2005 tender offer to the First Lien Holders was a Qualifying Offer. We further conclude, however, that the First Lien Trustee's second claim of error is meritorious. Even though that tender offer extinguished the First Lien Trustee's right to object to uses of the Rosetta Proceeds not prohibited by the First Lien Indenture, the First Lien Trustee retained an interest in those proceeds that conferred upon the First Lien Trustee contractual standing to enforce the Instruments in any this or any future transactions involving the collateral which secures the First Lien Notes.

(8) The Rosetta Proceeds and any assets purchased with them are still collateral for the First Lien Notes, subject to the First Lien Trustee's senior lien and to the First Lien Noteholders' rights under the Control Agreement. Contrary to the Court of Chancery's determination, neither the First Lien Indenture nor any provision of the Control Agreement exempts Calpine from strict compliance with the requirements the Control Agreement imposes for withdrawing the proceeds of a sale of Designated Assets from the DASPA after a conforming tender offer under the First Lien Indenture is made. The First Lien Trustee is a Secured Party. As such, it is an express, intended beneficiary of the Control Agreement and is entitled to enforce that Agreement's provisions. The Control Agreement provides that disbursements to Calpine from the DASPA may only be made upon proper certification by Calpine that (among other things) "no Secured Debt Default has occurred." The term "Secured Debt Default" is defined in the Collateral Agreement (of which the First Lien Trustee is an express beneficiary and a party by virtue of having executed the Collateral Trust Joinder) as an event that constitutes (or that upon the giving of notice or the passage of time would constitute) a default that could cause the acceleration of the First Lien or the Second Lien Debt.

(9) Calpine's withdrawal of the Rosetta Proceeds in connection with the Disputed Contracts was prohibited under the Collateral Agreement and the Second Lien Indenture, because, as the Court of Chancery found, the Disputed Contracts were not Designated Assets. Calpine's withdrawal of $312 million from the DASPA also constituted a Secured Debt Default under the Collateral Agreement, the terms of which were made applicable to the Control Agreement. Under Section 5.02 of the Control Agreement, the First Lien Trustee, as an intended beneficiary of the Control Agreement, has the right to enforce that Agreement if withdrawals are made in violation of it. The Court of Chancery's contrary determination was, therefore, erroneous as a matter of law.

<center>                   <bold><italic>The Re-Deposit Date Extension Issue</italic></bold></center>
(10) The Second Lien Trustee appeals from that portion of the Order establishing January 22, 2006 as the date by which Calpine must restore the approximately $312 million of the improperly withdrawn Rosetta Proceeds — the Restoration Amount — to the DASPA. The Second Lien Trustee argues that under the terms of the Indenture, Calpine is required to use the entire Rosetta Proceeds (including the Restoration Amount) to: (1) purchase replacement Designated Assets, (2) repurchase the First Lien Notes, or (3) make a tender offer to repurchase the Second Lien Notes, by no later than January 3, 2006. Had the Restoration Amount not been improperly withdrawn from the DASPA, that amount would have been included in the collateral on deposit in the DASPA, with the result that the DASPA would contain the full amount of the collateral to which Second Lien Noteholders were found to be contractually entitled. By extending the date for re-depositing the Restoration Amount from the January 3, 2006 deadline to January 22, 2006, the Court of Chancery increased by 19 days the time during which the Noteholders will be deprived of the full collateral secured by the Instruments. In doing that, the Second Lien Trustee argues, the Court of Chancery abused its discretion.

(11) Although extending by 19 days the January 3, 2006 deadline for re-depositing the Restoration Amount was within the Court of Chancery's discretion, we conclude that any such extension must be made subject to conditions that would adequately safeguard the Second Lien Noteholders' contractual rights. We affirm that portion of the trial court's Order establishing January 22, 2006 as the deadline by which Calpine must physically deposit the Restoration Amount into the DASPA: That extended deadline is subject, however, to the following conditions that, we conclude, will effectuate the 180 day deadline contractually imposed by Section 4.10 (c) of the Second Lien Indenture and will protect those Noteholders' property rights in the collateral to which they have been found contractually entitled:

<block_quote>  a) Until January 3, 2006, Calpine may use the proceeds in the DASPA to purchase replacement Designated Assets or for any other proper purpose that is authorized by the applicable Instruments.</block_quote>

<block_quote>  b) Although Calpine is not required to deposit the Restoration Amount in the DASPA until January 22, 2006, for purposes of calculating Excess Proceeds, any unpaid Restoration Amount shall be added to the amount actually on deposit in the DASPA as of January 3, 2006, with the result that the entire Restoration Amount shall be regarded for all legal purposes as if it had been physically re-deposited in the DASPA on January 3, 2006.</block_quote>

<block_quote>  c) If after making the calculation in (b) above, there are more than $50 million of Excess Proceeds, then Calpine must (i) make an irrevocable (<italic>i.e.</italic>
non-withdrawable) tender offer to purchase the Second Lien Notes; and (ii) the amount of that tender offer must include the entire unpaid Restoration Amount in addition to the amount that is actually on deposit in the DASPA on the date of the offer. During the period January 3, 2006 until the date on which payment to the Noteholders under the offer is made, no DASPA funds may be disbursed for any purpose other than to pay for Second Lien Notes that are tendered into the offer.</block_quote>

(12) This case shall be remanded to the Court of Chancery with directions to modify its Order to conform to the rulings made herein. The conditions set forth in paragraph (11) above will afford the parties a remedy that is consistent with, and that effectuates, the trial court's equitable rulings by affording Calpine additional time to fund its adjudicated obligation to restore the Restoration Amount to the DASPA, while preserving and securing to their fullest extent the contract rights of the Second Lien Noteholders. Requiring Calpine to make the tender offer in the full amount (including the unpaid Restoration Amount) of the Excess Proceeds on January 3, 2006 is appropriate, because the tender offer to the Second Lien Noteholders must remain open for 20 days, and if Calpine redeposits the Restoration Amount into the DASPA by January 19, 2006, the full amount of Excess Proceeds will be on deposit to pay the Second Lien Noteholders who tender into the offer.

NOW, THEREFORE, IT IS ORDERED that the Order and Final Judgment of the Court of Chancery is affirmed in part, reversed in part, and modified in part. This matter is remanded to the Court of Chancery for proceedings consistent with this Order, and the Clerk of this Court is directed to issue the mandate immediately.

<footnote_body><footnote_number>[fn*]</footnote_number> <italic>Calpine Corporation v. The Bank of New York, et. al.,</italic><cross_reference>2005 WL 3111956</cross_reference> (Del.Ch.).</footnote_body><page_number>Page 808</page_number>

</opinion_text>
</opinion>