<opinion>
<reporter_caption><center>IN RE MOORE, <citation>691 A.2d 1151</citation> (D.C. 1997)</center></reporter_caption>
<caption><center>In re Lloyd N. MOORE, Respondent.</center><center>A Member of the Bar of the District of Columbia Court of Appeals.</center></caption>
<docket><center>No. 93-BG-964.</center></docket><court><center>District of Columbia Court of Appeals.</center></court><hearing_date><center>Submitted February 25, 1997.</center></hearing_date>
<date><center>Decided March 27, 1997.</center>

</date><panel>  Before KING, RUIZ, and REID, Associate Judges.

</panel>
<opinion_byline>  PER CURIAM.

</opinion_byline>
<opinion_text>  Respondent Lloyd N. Moore, a tax attorney and managing partner of his law firm, pleaded guilty in June 1993, pursuant to a plea agreement, to one count of willful failure to file federal income tax returns in violation of<cross_reference>26 U.S.C. § 7203</cross_reference> (1994), a misdemeanor. Upon consideration of his guilty plea, on August 11, 1993, this court suspended Moore from the practice of law in the District of Columbia. Moore filed a timely affidavit of compliance pursuant to D.C. Bar R. XI, § 14.

The Board on Professional Responsibility ("Board") found that respondent was guilty of a "serious crime" under the Rules of the D.C. Court of Appeals,<footnote_reference>[fn1]</footnote_reference> and that Moore had committed multiple violations of DR <cross_reference>1-102</cross_reference>(A)(4) by engaging in dishonest conduct and misrepresentation, and had violated DR<cross_reference>1-102</cross_reference>(A)(5) by engaging in conduct prejudicial to the administration of justice. The Board also found that Moore's conduct did<page_number>Page 1152</page_number>
not constitute moral turpitude <italic>per se, see In re McBride</italic>,<cross_reference>602 A.2d 626</cross_reference> (D.C. 1992) (en banc), and therefore Moore is not subject to automatic disbarment under D.C. Code § 2503(a) (1996 Repl.). The Board recommends that Moore be suspended from the practice of law in the District of Columbia for a period of three years <italic>nunc pro tunc</italic> to August 11, 1993, with a showing of fitness required for reinstatement, and recommends that a determination be made at the time Moore applies for reinstatement whether a probationary condition should be imposed.

Neither respondent Moore nor Bar Counsel take exception to the report and recommendation of the Board in this matter. Pursuant to D.C. Bar R. XI, § 9(g)(2), we impose the sanctions recommended by the Board; therefore it is

ORDERED that respondent is hereby suspended from the practice of law in this jurisdiction for three years,<italic>nunc pro tunc</italic> to August 11, 1993, with a showing of fitness required for reinstatement. It is further ORDERED that when Moore applies for reinstatement, the Board shall make a determination whether probation and monitoring should be imposed as a condition of reinstatement.

<italic>So ordered.</italic>

<footnote_body><footnote_number>[fn1]</footnote_number> D.C. Bar R. XI, § 10(b) defines "serious crime" to include "willful failure to file income tax returns. . . ."</footnote_body>

</opinion_text>
</opinion>