<opinion unpublished=true>
<reporter_caption><center>STATE v. GALPIN, 27515-5-II (Wash.App. 4-1-2003)</center></reporter_caption>
<caption><center>STATE OF WASHINGTON, v. DARREN GENE GALPIN, Appellant.</center></caption>
<docket><center>No. 27515-5-II, 27525-2-II</center></docket><court><center>The Court of Appeals of Washington, Division Two.</center></court>
<date><center>Filed: April 1, 2003</center><center>DO NOT CITE. SEE RAP 10.4(h).</center><center>UNPUBLISHED OPINION</center>

</date>
<posture><unpublished><footnote_body>[EDITOR'S NOTE: This case is unpublished as indicated by the issuing court.]</footnote_body>
Appeal from Superior Court of Lewis County Docket No: 00-1-00483-9 Judgment or order under review Date filed: 06/20/2001

</unpublished></posture><attorneys><unpublished>  Counsel for Appellant(s), Jodi R. Backlund, Backlund  Mistry, 331 N.W. Park St, Chehalis, WA 98532-2024.

Manek R. Mistry, Backlund  Mistry, 331 N.W. Park St, Chehalis, WA 98532-2024.

Counsel for Respondent(s), J. Andrew Toynbee, Attorney at Law, M/S Pr001, 360 N.W. North St, Chehalis, WA 98532-1925.

</unpublished></attorneys>
<opinion_byline><unpublished>  QUINN-BRINTNALL, A.C.J.

</unpublished></opinion_byline>
<opinion_text><unpublished>  Darren Galpin pleaded guilty to three drug-related charges: manufacture, possession with intent to deliver, and possession of a controlled substance, and one count of driving while license suspended in December 2000. He appeals the trial court's denial of his motion to withdraw his guilty pleas.

Galpin failed to comply with terms of his plea agreement, which were conditions precedent to the State's obligation to fulfill its obligations under the contract. Thus, we affirm Galpin's convictions. But because the parties and the trial court miscalculated Galpin's offender score on the simple possession count and because the trial court erred by not considering a drug offender sentencing alternative (DOSA) sentence on one of the two cause numbers, we remand for resentencing.

<center>                                   FACTS</center>
On December 22, 2000, Galpin pleaded guilty to manufacture of a controlled substance, possession of a controlled substance, possession of a controlled substance with intent to deliver, and third degree driving while license suspended.<footnote_reference>[fn1]</footnote_reference> On that same date he entered into a contract with the Lewis County Prosecutor's Office. Under the contract the prosecutor agreed to allow Galpin to substitute pleas to lesser charges and agreed to recommend a lenient sentence after Galpin provided information to the Unified Narcotics Enforcement Team (UNET) and satisfied other conditions set out in the contract.<footnote_reference>[fn2]</footnote_reference>

Galpin agreed to (2) . . . make at least three (3) purchases of [methamphetamine] and/or [methamphetamine precursors] in a quantity as indicated by UNET from each of the THREE (3) separate individuals and/or groups in a manner as indicated by UNET such that the information developed from each individual investigation will result in the seizure of controlled substances and in the prosecution against each individual(s) and/or group(s). . .

. . . . .

(4) Contact the supervising detective, or his designee, in person or telephonically on a daily basis until the conclusion of the criminal and civil proceedings against all subjects who are arrested as a result of information provided by GALPIN;

. . . .

(6) GALPIN shall appear in person at any location chosen by the supervising detective, or his designee, within two hours of the request;

. . . .

(8) GALPIN shall perform such tasks pertaining to the investigations as directed by the supervising detective, or his designee, to include but not limited to wearing of a wire device, introducing an undercover law enforcement officer to persons who are possessing, purchasing, manufacturing and/or delivering controlled substances, permitting of phone conversations being recorded;

(9) Should the supervising detective not be available, GALPIN will report to another member of UNET, designated by the supervising detective.

. . . .

(12) GALPIN agrees to waive all rights in regard to speedy sentencing. GALPIN agrees to work with UNET for a time period not to exceed 90 days from the signing of this contract to complete the active investigations (i.e., arrest(s) or charging(s) of the individuals and/or groups mentioned in subsection 2). The 90 day time period does not include the time period it takes to complete the prosecution of these same individuals and/or groups. However, GALPIN must testify truthfully in any hearing, proceeding, or trial which occurs after the 90 day period;

(13) Failure to meet any of the above conditions may result in the State seeking immediate authorization of a warrant for GALPIN's arrest, and that everything (s)he has performed up to the violation will not count towards the successful completion of the contract. The State will then recommend the maximum sentence allowed . . . .

Suppl. Clerk's Papers (CP) at 33-34.

Galpin testified that he read the contract before signing it and had no questions about his contractual obligations at the time he entered into it. Galpin did not maintain daily contact with UNET officers, refused to perform some of the jobs requested, and completed only three of the nine required purchases within the 90-day term set out in the contract. The detectives assigned to Galpin's case testified that Galpin successfully arranged a sale of pseudoephedrine that led to what appears to be a significant bust, referred to in testimony as the Market Street Market transaction. But after this transaction, Galpin failed to check in daily as the contract required.

Detective Tim Tingle testified that during the second month of the contract (February 2001), he heard from Galpin fewer than six times. Tingle explored alternatives with Galpin, including suggesting various people Galpin could target, but Galpin declined. Tingle spoke with Galpin `a few times' in March, and not at all in April. Report of Proceedings (RP) at 14. In essence, Galpin assisted UNET in one major sting operation involving the purchase of precursor materials from a convenience store and then ceased contact. After the 90-day contract period, Galpin arranged to make another purchase, but the officers refused to deal with him. At his sentencing hearing, Galpin sought specific performance of the plea agreement,<footnote_reference>[fn3]</footnote_reference> claiming fulfillment of the agreement or, in the alternative, lack of good faith on the part of the State. The State in turn alleged breach. The trial court took testimony for two days on the question of each party's breach. The court found that the State had met its burden to prove that Galpin breached the agreement and it made findings in an oral ruling.

Confusion about Galpin's offender score necessitated a continuance. When the hearing resumed, defense counsel explained that the parties were `agreed as to what constitutes the prior criminal history . . . [s]o there's three prior felony points. On each of these then he would have an offender score of 7.' RP at 86-87.

On cause No. 00-1-00483-9, the court sentenced Galpin to 120 months on count I (manufacture of a controlled substance) and 14 months on count II (possession of a controlled substance). On cause No. 00-1-00727-7, the court sentenced Galpin to 77 months on count I (possession of a controlled substance with intent to deliver).<footnote_reference>[fn4]</footnote_reference> Galpin challenges (1) the trial court's finding that he breached the plea agreement, (2) the court's refusal to sentence him under DOSA, and (3) the court's calculation of his offender score.

<center>                                  ANALYSIS</center>
Breach of Contract

A plea agreement is a contract between the State and the defendant.<italic>State v. Sledge</italic>, <cross_reference>133 Wn.2d 828</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>838-39</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>947 P.2d 1199</cross_reference> (1997). Basic contract principles of good faith and fair dealing impose on the State an implied promise to act in good faith in plea agreements. <italic>Sledge</italic>,<cross_reference>133 Wn.2d at 838-39</cross_reference>. Due process establishes the State's duty to comply with plea agreements. Sledge, <cross_reference>133 Wn.2d at 839-40</cross_reference>.

Compliance is a question of fact. <italic>In re Personal Restraint of James</italic>,<cross_reference>96 Wn.2d 847</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>850</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>640 P.2d 18</cross_reference> (1982) (defendant charged but not convicted of additional misdemeanors between plea and sentencing). And to decide the compliance issue, the trial court must hold an evidentiary hearing at which the State bears the burden of proving by a preponderance of the evidence that the defendant has failed to perform his part of the agreement. James, <cross_reference>96 Wn.2d at 850</cross_reference>.

(1) Daily Contact With the UNET Officers Team The trial court found that Galpin breached the agreement's daily reporting requirement. Galpin admits that he did not report every day, but he asserts that the State waived his non-compliance by failing to rescind the contract in the second month when he began breaching this provision.

The primary objective of the plea agreement was for Galpin to purchase drugs, thus enabling UNET to target, arrest, and prosecute drug dealers. Daily check-ins would keep Galpin available for that purpose. If Galpin had participated in the required drug purchases, his failure to check in every day alone would not be sufficient grounds to support a finding that he breached the contract. But the State was within its rights to give Galpin an opportunity to cooperate and make the required number of purchases. And the State did not waive the daily reporting requirement when it decided not to move to rescind the contract in the second month when Galpin failed to report. Substantial evidence supports the trial court's finding that Galpin breached his daily reporting requirement.

(2) 90-Day Term

Galpin phoned Tingle within days of the contract expiring with a prospective deal; Tingle refused to talk because the 90-day term had passed. Galpin argues that, because the contract did not expressly provide that "time is of the essence," the 90-day term was optional and he had not yet breached the contract. Br. of Appellant at 13-15. Galpin argues that the State's need to fight drug crime was no different on the 91st day of the contract than on the 89th day. He states that he was willing to continue working for UNET and even made suggestions for potential transactions after the contract period had expired. But the record does not support Galpin's claim that the State made it impossible for him to satisfy his obligations under the contract; rather it establishes that he was not cooperative. In February, the second month of the contract, Galpin contacted UNET six times within 30 days. As a result of Galpin's lack of productivity, UNET detectives offered other possible contacts that would allow Galpin to complete the contract. But Galpin expressly refused to participate in these activities targeting his friends, or to perform reverse buys in which he would be arrested to protect his cover. Galpin's lack of timely cooperation breached the contract long before its expiration.

DOSA

Galpin claims that the trial court should have held an evidentiary hearing before denying his request for a DOSA sentence.

This court reviews DOSA eligibility determinations for an abuse of discretion.<footnote_reference>[fn5]</footnote_reference> <italic>State v. Williams</italic>, <cross_reference>112 Wn. App. 171</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>178</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>48 P.3d 354</cross_reference>
(2002) (citing RCW <cross_reference>9.94A.660</cross_reference>(2)). An abuse of discretion occurs if the sentencing court's decision is manifestly unreasonable or based on untenable grounds or untenable reasons. <italic>State v. Stenson</italic>, <cross_reference>132 Wn.2d 668</cross_reference>,<cross_reference>701</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>940 P.2d 1239</cross_reference> (1997), <italic>cert. denied</italic>, <cross_reference>523 U.S. 1008</cross_reference> (1998).

The Sentencing Reform Act (SRA) provides that if a defendant disputes material facts used in sentencing, "the court must either not consider the fact or grant an evidentiary hearing on the point." <italic>State v. Mail</italic>,<cross_reference>121 Wn.2d 707</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>712</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>854 P.2d 1042</cross_reference> (1993) (quoting RCW 9.94A.370(2)<footnote_reference>[fn6]</footnote_reference>. In order to dispute any of the information presented for consideration at a sentencing hearing, a defendant must make a timely and specific challenge. <italic>State v. Garza</italic>, <cross_reference>123 Wn.2d 885</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>890</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>872 P.2d 1087</cross_reference> (1994). Galpin points out that he expressly refused to stipulate to the amount of methamphetamine he possessed and asked the court "to make a finding that there was not a large amount and admit Mr. Galpin to a DOSA sentence." RP at 94-95. But Galpin had already admitted in open court at the plea hearing to possessing three-quarters of an ounce of methamphetamine with the intent to sell and/or deliver. That amount equals approximately 21 grams. And, more importantly, he did not request an evidentiary hearing, even in his motion for reconsideration. The trial court did not err in considering Galpin's possession of 21 grams of methamphetamine during the sentencing hearing and denying his DOSA request on the possession of a controlled substance with intent to deliver charge in cause No. 00-1-00727-7.

(1) Effect of One Cause Number On Another In DOSA Determination

Immediately after the court denied his DOSA request, Galpin moved for reconsideration, arguing that his sentence on one cause number did not preclude the court's consideration of a DOSA sentence on the other. The court ruled that because Galpin was not eligible for a DOSA sentence on the possession of a controlled substance with intent to deliver charge (cause No. 00-1-00727-7), it was precluded from imposing a DOSA on the manufacture and possession of a controlled substance charges (cause No. 00-1-00483-9). Galpin argues that the statute, RCW <cross_reference>9.94A.660</cross_reference>(1),<footnote_reference>[fn7]</footnote_reference>
does not expressly bar defendants who are ineligible to receive a DOSA sentence on one case from participating in the DOSA program on another.

RCW <cross_reference>9.94A.660</cross_reference> reads in pertinent part as follows (emphasis added):

(1) An offender is eligible for the special drug offender sentencing alternative if:

(a) The offender is convicted of a felony that is not a violent offense or sex offense and the violation does not involve a sentence enhancement under RCW <cross_reference>9.94A.510</cross_reference>(3) or (4);

(b) The offender has no current or prior convictions for a sex offense or violent offense in this state, another state, or the United States;

(c) For a violation of the Uniform Controlled Substances Act under chapter <cross_reference>69.50</cross_reference> RCW or a criminal solicitation to commit such a violation under chapter <cross_reference>9A.28</cross_reference> RCW, the offense involved only a small quantity of the particular controlled substance as determined by the judge upon consideration of such factors as the weight, purity, packaging, sale price, and street value of the controlled substance; and

(d) The offender has not been found by the United States attorney general to be subject to a deportation detainer or order and does not become subject to a deportation order during the period of the sentence.

Galpin is correct: RCW <cross_reference>9.94A.660</cross_reference>(1) does not mention other current cases, except when those cases are sex or violent offenses. See RCW<cross_reference>9.94A.660</cross_reference>(1)(b). The trial court's decision to deny Galpin a DOSA on cause No. 00-1-00727-7 does not control its determination of whether to grant his request for a DOSA on cause No. 00-1-00483-9.

Galpin's Offender Score

Galpin argues that the parties and the trial court erroneously believed that Galpin's offender score was seven on count II of cause No. 00-1-00483-9, the simple possession charge. As is clear from the face of the judgment and sentence, Galpin had three prior felony points and two other current offenses. His correct score on the simple possession charge is therefore a five, with a standard range of 4 to 12 months, as correctly reflected in the Statement of Defendant on Plea of Guilty.<footnote_reference>[fn8]</footnote_reference>
Accordingly, Galpin's standard range was miscalculated; thus the 14-month sentence imposed is outside the standard range. We remand for resentencing under the correct offender score.

Because the record supports the trial court's oral ruling that Galpin breached the plea agreement by failing to report and refusing to perform tasks as directed by the supervising detective, we affirm the trial court's enforcement of the plea agreement. We likewise affirm the trial court's decision to deny Galpin's DOSA request on cause No. 00-1-00727-7, but because Galpin's offender score was miscalculated and the court mistakenly believed that it was precluded from considering a DOSA sentence on cause No. 00-1-00483-9, we remand for resentencing. On remand, the trial court shall compute Galpin's standard range on the possession charge using an offender score of five and consider whether a DOSA sentence on cause No. 00-1-00483-9 (the manufacture and possession charges) is warranted.

A majority of the panel having determined that this opinion will not be printed in the Washington Appellate Reports, but will be filed for public record pursuant to RCW <cross_reference>2.06.040</cross_reference>, it is so ordered.

ARMSTRONG and HOUGHTON, JJ., concur.

<footnote_body><footnote_number>[fn1]</footnote_number> Galpin was charged under two different cause numbers. Under No. 00-1-00483-9 he was charged with manufacture of a controlled substance (count I) and possession of a controlled substance (count II). Under No. 00-1-00727-7, Galpin was charged with possession of a controlled substance with intent to deliver (count I) and driving while license suspended or revoked (count II).</footnote_body>

<footnote_body><footnote_number>[fn2]</footnote_number> In exchange for Galpin's cooperation, the State would allow him to withdraw his guilty plea on certain of the charges and plead to lesser charges, and the State would recommend a lower sentence:

(15) If GALPIN performs all promises enumerated above, the Lewis County Prosecutor's Office agrees . . . that:

(a) GALPIN be allowed to withdraw his/her plea of guilty to Manufacture of a Controlled Substance — Methamphetamine and Possession of a Controlled Substance Methamphetamine . . . and Possession of a Controlled Substance with Intent to Deliver — Methamphetamine and Driving While License Suspended 3rd Degree . . . in order that (s)he plead guilty to one count of Attempted Manufacture of a Controlled Substance — Methamphetamine . . . and one count of Attempted Possession of a Controlled Substance with Intent to Deliver — Methamphetamine . . . AND THAT

(b) GALPIN be sentenced to: a sentence of 8 months at the Department of Corrections on each of the above stated cause numbers, with the sentences to run consecutively to each other; 9-12 months of community custody on each of the above stated cause numbers whereby GALPIN must follow all standard Department of Corrections rules and regulations . . . . Suppl. Clerk's Papers (CP) at 35.</footnote_body>

<footnote_body><footnote_number>[fn3]</footnote_number> See note 2.</footnote_body>

<footnote_body><footnote_number>[fn4]</footnote_number> The disposition of the driving while license suspended charge is not clear from the record.</footnote_body>

<footnote_body><footnote_number>[fn5]</footnote_number> The State is technically correct when it argues that a standard range sentence may not be appealed. See former RCW 9.94A.210(1) (1989) (recodified as RCW <cross_reference>9.94A.585</cross_reference>); <italic>State v. Mail</italic>, <cross_reference>121 Wn.2d 707</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>710</cross_reference>,<cross_reference>854 P.2d 1042</cross_reference> (1993). But numerous exceptions to this rule have eviscerated the statute's appeal limitation. If, as here, a defendant claims that the trial court miscalculated his offender score or failed to follow the specific procedure required by the Sentencing Reform Act (SRA), he may appeal and perhaps challenge the validity of his sentence for the first time on appeal or collateral attack. <italic>See In re Personal</italic><italic>Restraint of Goodwin</italic>, <cross_reference>146 Wn.2d 861</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>876-77</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>50 P.3d 618</cross_reference> (2002) (holding that a sentence based upon an incorrect offender score even when the result of a negotiated plea agreement is a fundamental defect resulting in a miscarriage of justice that may be raised for the first time on appeal when the error is clear on the face of the judgment and sentence); Mail, <cross_reference>121 Wn.2d at 712</cross_reference>.</footnote_body>

<footnote_body><footnote_number>[fn6]</footnote_number> This statute was recodified in 2001 as RCW <cross_reference>9.94A.530</cross_reference>. <italic>See</italic> Laws of 2001, ch. <cross_reference>10</cross_reference>, § 6.</footnote_body>

<footnote_body><footnote_number>[fn7]</footnote_number> At the time of Galpin's offenses, this statute was codified as RCW 9.94A.120(6).</footnote_body>

<footnote_body><footnote_number>[fn8]</footnote_number> The score on the simple possession was five but seven on the other two charges because on a simple possession there is no "tripling" of the offender points. Compare former RCW 9.94A.360(7) (1999) (recodified as<cross_reference>9.94A.525</cross_reference>(7), Laws of 2001, ch. <cross_reference>10</cross_reference>, § 6) and former RCW 9.94A.360(12) (1999) (recodified as <cross_reference>9.94A.525</cross_reference>(12), Laws of 2001, ch. <cross_reference>10</cross_reference>, § 6).</footnote_body>

</unpublished></opinion_text>
</opinion>