<opinion unpublished=true>
<reporter_caption><center>IN RE MARRIAGE OF SMITH, 24428-8-III (Wash.App. 10-3-2006)</center></reporter_caption>
<caption><center>In re the Marriage of: JANE ELIZABETH SMITH, Respondent, and RANDY DALE</center><center>SMITH, Appellant.</center></caption>
<docket><center>No. 24428-8-III.</center></docket><court><center>The Court of Appeals of Washington, Division Three.</center></court>
<date><center>Filed: October 3, 2006</center><center>UNPUBLISHED OPINION</center>

</date>
<posture><unpublished><footnote_body>[EDITOR'S NOTE: This case is unpublished as indicated by the issuing court.]</footnote_body>
Appeal from Spokane Superior Court. Docket No: Judgment or order under review. Date filed: 07/29/2005. Judge signing: Honorable Michael P Price.

</unpublished></posture><attorneys><unpublished>  Counsel for Appellant(s), Dale Leonard Raugust, Attorney at Law, 606 S Pines Rd, Spokane Valley, WA, 99206-5450.

Counsel for Respondent(s), Gordon R Stoa, Attorney at Law, 422 W Riverside Ave Ste 518, Spokane, WA, 99201-0302,

</unpublished></attorneys>
<opinion_byline><unpublished>  SWEENEY, C.J.

</unpublished></opinion_byline>
<opinion_text><unpublished>  Randy D. Smith appeals the trial court's refusal to modify his obligation for spousal maintenance. He argues that the maintenance provisions in the court's decree of dissolution are void under state law since they were not set out in a separation agreement. We conclude, as the trial court did, that the terms of the maintenance agreement are adequately spelled out in the court's findings of fact, conclusions of law, and decree. And we conclude that the court had discretionary authority to hold Mr. Smith in contempt for failing to pay that support. We therefore affirm the trial court's order.

<center>                                  FACTS</center>
Randy D. Smith and Jane E. Smith were married. They separated in January 1998 and signed a separation agreement. Mr. Smith agreed to pay Ms. Smith spousal maintenance. The maintenance award was non-modifiable. The agreement provided that the maintenance would terminate "upon the death or remarriage of the wife or upon the wife's entry into a cohabitational meretricious relationship with another person." Clerk's Papers (CP) at 11.

The court entered a decree of dissolution on May 2, 2000. The court's findings note this earlier separation agreement, but approve a later agreement: "The parties have reached an alternative written agreement embodied in these documents." CP at 18 (emphasis added). "The husband has the ability to provide maintenance and the wife is in need of maintenance and the parties have entered an agreement embodied in these documents which will supplant the written Separation Agreement, which also provides for maintenance." CP at 19 (emphasis added). And the new maintenance provisions were attached to the decree of dissolution as exhibit 3 and provided for nonmodifiable spousal maintenance until December 31, 2008, "irrespective of the remarriage of either party." CP at 38.

Mr. Smith later learned that Ms. Smith became pregnant by another man before they signed the decree of dissolution. Ms. Smith married the man after the court entered the decree of dissolution. Mr. Smith then moved to set aside the judgment and vacate that portion of the decree of dissolution obligating him to pay spousal support. He said that he would have "sought to enforce the original separation agreement" had he known about Ms. Smith's "meretricious relationship and pregnancy." CP at 43.

A superior court commissioner concluded that Ms. Smith's misrepresentations were "irrelevant to the settlement . . . reached by the parties." CP at 55. He found:

<block_quote>  "[t]he parties used the maintenance to equalize the property distribution. They made this maintenance non-modifiable irrespective of remarriage. By reasonable inference, it really wasn't maintenance." CP at 55.</block_quote>

From this the commissioner concluded that "[Ms.] Smith's lie to the Court was not material to the property division." CP at 55. He denied Mr. Smith's motion to change the decree.

Mr. Smith moved to revise the commissioner's ruling. The court affirmed the commissioner's order "denying partial vacation of the spousal maintenance and property division in the Decree." CP at 65. The court also denied his motion for reconsideration.

Two years later Mr. Smith again petitioned to modify the spousal maintenance. And he moved for an order declaring the maintenance provisions in the decree void as a matter of law because they were "non-modifiable" and yet were not part of a separation agreement as required by RCW <cross_reference>26.09.170</cross_reference>. Ms. Smith moved to dismiss his motions and for an order of contempt based on Mr. Smith's failure to pay maintenance.

A superior court commissioner dismissed Mr. Smith's motion for modification and his motion to vacate. And he held Mr. Smith in contempt for "willfully not paying his maintenance payments as ordered." CP at 135. The superior court affirmed the ruling.

<center>                               DISCUSSION</center><center>                 "Non-modifiable" Maintenance Provision</center>
The question here is one of law. Does RCW <cross_reference>26.09.170</cross_reference>(2) require that a provision for "non-modifiable" spousal support be set out in a separate agreement?one independent of the dissolution decree — We conclude it does not because the parties here memorialized their agreement by a decree of dissolution. The question is one of law and so our review is de novo. In re Marriage of Kinnan,<cross_reference>131 Wn. App. 738</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>751</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>129 P.3d 807</cross_reference> (2006).

The general rule is that a party may move to modify an award for spousal maintenance. RCW <cross_reference>26.09.170</cross_reference>(1); RCW <cross_reference>26.09.070</cross_reference>(7). But that is not so if they have agreed to make the spousal maintenance non-modifiable. RCW 29.09.170(1); RCW <cross_reference>26.09.070</cross_reference>(7). And spousal maintenance generally terminates when a spouse receiving maintenance remarries. RCW <cross_reference>26.09.170</cross_reference>(2). But that is also subject to exception. RCW <cross_reference>26.09.170</cross_reference>(2). By statute the parties to the dissolution may agree that the spousal support obligation will not end when the wife (here) remarries. The termination of maintenance is separate and distinct from the modification of maintenance. RCW <cross_reference>26.09.170</cross_reference>(1), (2); In re Marriage of Rufener, <cross_reference>52 Wn. App. 788</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>792</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>764 P.2d 655</cross_reference> (1988).

Mr. Smith argues that the provisions of this decree that extend his spousal support obligation beyond Ms. Smith's remarriage are void because they are not also set out in a separation agreement. Ms. Smith responds that they have a new agreement; and it is set out in the court's decree of dissolution.

Here, the judge found that the parties' "separation contract should not be approved" since the "parties have reached an alternative written agreement embodied in these documents." CP at 18 (emphasis added). The court then attached the maintenance provisions to the decree. And the findings of fact, conclusions of law, and decree were signed by the lawyers for both Mr. and Ms. Smith. That decree reflects their agreement that Mr. Smith would pay Ms. Smith spousal maintenance until December 31, 2008, whether or not she remarried and an agreement that the provision could not be modified.

The court concluded that the parties' new agreement supplanted their earlier separation agreement. CP at 19.

Both parties stipulated to the findings, conclusions, and decree here. Those findings, conclusions, and decree memorialize an agreement that spousal maintenance will be nonmodifiable and will not terminate on Ms. Smith's remarriage.

Mr. Smith also argues that the first separation agreement is still binding because it could be modified only if the modifications were in writing and executed with the same degree of formality as the original agreement. And the dissolution decree here does not reflect "the same degree of finality" since he did not sign it, his lawyer did. And the document was not notarized.

First, agreements and stipulations made as part of a court proceeding are binding. RCW <cross_reference>2.44.010</cross_reference>; CR 2A; Nguyen v. Sacred Heart Med. Ctr., <cross_reference>97 Wn. App. 728</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>734-35</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>987 P.2d 634</cross_reference> (1999). Second, a lawyer has authority to commit his client to stipulations and agreements in writing or on the record. RCW <cross_reference>2.44.010</cross_reference>; CR 2A; Nguyen, <cross_reference>97 Wn. App. at 734-35</cross_reference>.

So an agreement reflected in a superior court decree is an agreement executed with, at least, the same degree of finality as a contract signed by a notary. Contempt? Nonpayment of Spousal Maintenance

Finally, Mr. Smith argues that the court could not hold him in contempt for failing to pay spousal maintenance because the court's order for spousal maintenance was invalid.

We review a trial court's contempt order for an abuse of discretion. Moreman v. Butcher, <cross_reference>126 Wn.2d 36</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>40</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>891 P.2d 725</cross_reference>
(1995).

Contempt is an "intentional disobedience of a lawful court order." In re Marriage of Humphreys, <cross_reference>79 Wn. App. 596</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>599</cross_reference>,<cross_reference>903 P.2d 1012</cross_reference> (1995). A contempt order is invalid only if the court lacked jurisdiction or authority to make the original order. We have rejected the predicate for Mr. Smith's essential argument?that the order for spousal maintenance is void. Seattle Nw. Sec. Corp. v. SDG Holding Co., <cross_reference>61 Wn. App. 725</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>733</cross_reference>,<cross_reference>812 P.2d 488</cross_reference> (1991). And so his argument, that the court could not hold him in contempt, also fails. In fact, this judge could have held Mr. Smith in contempt even if its order was wrong, just so long as it had authority to enter the order. Id.

We affirm the trial court's order.

A majority of the panel has determined that this opinion will not be printed in the Washington Appellate Reports but it will be filed for public record pursuant to RCW <cross_reference>2.06.040</cross_reference>.

SCHULTHEIS, J. and KULIK, J. Concur.

</unpublished></opinion_text>
</opinion>