<opinion unpublished=true>
<reporter_caption><center>IN RE PARENTAGE OF D. K., 45734-9-I (Wash.App. 2-5-2001)</center></reporter_caption>
<caption><center>In Re the Parentage of DANIEL KEMPER, MARK S. NEGRIE, Respondent v. KATHI</center><center>J. KEMPER Appellant.</center></caption>
<docket><center>No. 45734-9-I.</center></docket><court><center>The Court of Appeals of Washington, Division One.</center></court>
<date><center>Filed: February 5, 2001.</center><center>DO NOT CITE. SEE RAP 10.4(h).</center><center>UNPUBLISHED OPINION.</center>

</date>
<posture><unpublished><footnote_body>[EDITOR'S NOTE: This case is unpublished as indicated by the issuing court.]</footnote_body>
Appeal from Superior Court of King County, No. 97-5-01466-3, Hon. Richard A. Jones, November 18, 1999, Judgment or order under review.

</unpublished></posture><attorneys><unpublished>  Counsel for Appellant(s), Mark S. Negrie (Appearing Pro Se), 119 Ward Street, Seattle, WA 98109.

Counsel for Respondent(s), Catherine A. Chaney, Law Office of Catherine Chaney, 810 3rd Ave. Ste. 757, Seattle, WA 98104.

</unpublished></attorneys>
<opinion_byline><unpublished>  WALTER E. WEBSTER, J.

</unpublished></opinion_byline>
<opinion_text><unpublished>  Mark Negrie and Kathi Kemper are unmarried parents of a three-year old child. Negrie lives in Seattle, while Kemper and their son reside in Boston, Massachusetts. Under their Parenting Plan, Negrie may visit their son every six weeks for up to seven consecutive days each visit. Despite the Parenting Plan, the parents have had difficulty agreeing on visitation dates. They sought mediation, but did not discuss their problems with the mediator because they could not agree on how much each should pay for mediation costs. When Kemper limited visitation to weekends, Negrie filed a motion for contempt alleging that she violated the Parenting Plan. Kemper also filed a motion for contempt against Negrie because he refused to pay half of the mediation costs. The trial court found both parties in contempt and ordered mediation.

Negrie appeals, arguing the trial court erred by:

<block_quote>  1) failing to rule on his motion to strike and motion for sanctions;</block_quote>

<block_quote>  2) not ordering the correct amount of additional visitation time;</block_quote>

3) not awarding costs and civil penalties for contempt;

<block_quote>  4) finding him in contempt; and party to pay 50 percent of mediation costs.</block_quote>

This Court reverses and remands because the trial court failed to rule on the post-trial motions to strike and for sanctions as well as on costs, attorney fees and civil penalties. Also, the trial court failed to award twice the additional visitation time because it found Kemper in contempt for the second time in three years.

<center>                                   FACTS</center>
Kathi Kemper and Mark Negrie dated for three months in 1996. Kemper gave birth to their child on March 7, 1997, in Seattle. According to the Parenting Plan, the child resides with Kemper and Negrie has certain visitation rights. As anticipated in the Plan, Kemper moved to Boston with their child in June 1998. During their child's preschool years, Negrie may travel to Boston every six weeks to visit their child for up to seven consecutive days:

<block_quote>  All visitations shall take place in Boston, Massachusetts every six (6) weeks on specific dates mutually agreed to by both parents. Visitation shall be arranged at least three (3) weeks in advance unless reasonable notice is given for any changes. Visits are to occur up to daily for up to seven (7) consecutive days. The visitations are to be supervised by the mother or the child's au pair until the child is at least 18 months old.</block_quote>

Unless there is a substantial change of circumstances for either parent, the visitation schedule shall be reviewed in June 1999 and again in June 2002. If there is a substantial change of circumstances, the visitation schedule may be reviewed within one (1) month of that change.

Clerk's Papers (CP) at 26. If the parents have a dispute about visitation, they must submit to mediation upon the written request by either parent:

<block_quote>  Disputes between the parties, other than child support disputes, shall be submitted to mediation to a mutually agreed mediation center[,] individual, or agency. The cost of this process shall be allocated between the parties and paid as determined in the dispute resolution process. The counseling, mediation or arbitration process shall be commenced by notifying the other party by written request.</block_quote>

CP at 28. Either parent has the right to seek review of the dispute resolution process in superior court.

On June 3, 1998, the King County Superior Court found Kemper in contempt for violating the Parenting Plan by not providing the father with visitation on certain dates. The court did not accept Kemper's excuse that she was out of state on business on those dates. It ordered Kemper to mail to Negrie a two-week period in which he may schedule his seven days of visitation. If there were any problems in scheduling visitation, the court mandated dispute resolution.

By November 1998, Negrie and Kemper called a mediator to settle disputes about visitation but could not proceed because they disagreed on the allocation of mediation costs. Negrie wanted Kemper to pay 82 percent of the costs, based on her higher income as listed on child support worksheets. Kemper, on the other hand, suggested that he pay 80 percent since he initiated the dispute resolution process. When he refused, she offered to split the costs evenly at 50 percent each, as they had in a previous mediation. He refused. Because they could not agree on allocation of costs, the mediation ended before any discussion on visitation could take place. Nonetheless, Negrie and Kemper were able to schedule visitation without major problems until the summer of 1999. Kemper had sent a schedule to Negrie for June visits and noted that, in bad weather, visits would take place at the museum, or if that was closed, then at the aquarium. One June day, Negrie arrived at a park for a visit, but Kemper had the au pair take their child to the children's museum because of the weather. Apparently, they disagreed about the weather that day, causing Negrie to miss a visit.

They also disagreed about visitation during childcare. For speech development purposes, Kemper enrolled their son in childcare and wrote a letter to Negrie explaining that it would be difficult to schedule weekday visits. Negrie wrote back asserting that Kemper had violated the contempt order by limiting visitation to weekends. Kemper responded that she was not in contempt and suggested mediation in Boston. Negrie filed a motion for contempt against Kemper in the King County Superior Court for violating the visitation schedule in the Parenting Plan. About three weeks later, Kemper filed her own motion for contempt against Negrie for violating the dispute resolution provision. A commissioner found neither parent in contempt and ordered them to submit to mediation, the cost of which they would split evenly. Upon revision, a superior court judge found both parents in contempt and ordered mediation. Negrie appeals.<footnote_reference>[fn1]</footnote_reference>

<center>                                 DISCUSSION</center><center>                   I. Motions to Strike and for Sanctions</center>
Negrie contends that the trial court did not rule on his post-trial motions to strike and for sanctions. Kemper had filed a contempt motion against Negrie for not using the dispute resolution process set out in the Parenting Plan. After Negrie responded to the motion, Kemper filed documents in strict reply and mailed them to Negrie on the day before the hearing. Negrie argues that the trial court failed to rule on his motion to strike Kemper's documents for late service. Kemper contends that the late service created no prejudice against Negrie. The trial court has broad discretion in permitting the filing of pleadings, even if they do not conform to the rules. Bargreen v. Little, <cross_reference>27 Wn.2d 128</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>133</cross_reference>,<cross_reference>177 P.2d 85</cross_reference> (1947). An appellate court will overturn a discretionary ruling only if there is a manifest abuse of discretion. Coggle v. Snow,<cross_reference>56 Wn. App. 499</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>504</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>784 P.2d 554</cross_reference> (1990). There is no record of the trial court's ruling on Negrie's motion to strike. Since there is no record of the trial court's ruling, it appears that the trial court did not exercise its discretion at all. Because this Court is unable to determine whether the trial court abused its discretion, we remand for a ruling on the motion to strike.

We note that in King County family law proceedings a party must serve all documents in strict reply by 12:00 noon two court days prior to the hearing on the relevant motion. LR 94.04(b)(3). If a party elects to serve the documents by mail, the party must deposit such documents in the post office at least three business days before the deadline. CR 5(b)(2)(A). Here, Kemper mailed the documents in strict reply to Negrie on September 28, 1999. The hearing on Kemper's contempt motion, however, took place the next day on September 29, 1999. We find that Kemper did not serve the documents on time.

Nonetheless, failure to comply with the notice requirement is not fatal if the nonmoving party had actual notice of the pending motion and time to prepare, thereby suffering no prejudice. Cf. Loveless v. Yantis,<cross_reference>82 Wn.2d 754</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>759</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>513 P.2d 1023</cross_reference> (1973) (construing CR 6(d)) cited in 1 Washington State Bar Ass'n, Civil Procedure Deskbook ยง 6.6(4)(a) (1992). Here, Kemper filed her contempt motion on September 15, 1999. As evidenced by his response filed September 23, 1999, Negrie had actual notice of Kemper's contempt motion as well as time to prepare for the hearing. Negrie has not made a showing of prejudice to this Court.<footnote_reference>[fn2]</footnote_reference>
Upon remand, the trial court may use its discretion in ruling on the motion to strike.

Negrie argues that the trial court should have imposed sanctions on Kemper for the late service of documents in strict reply. LR 94.04(j) states that the King County Superior Court may impose sanctions or terms as deemed appropriate. There is no record of the trial court's ruling, if any, on Negrie's motion for sanctions. It appears that the trial court failed to rule on this motion. Because this Court is unable to review for abuse of discretion without a discretionary decision, we remand to the trial court for such a ruling.

<center>                            II. Visitation Time</center>
Negrie contends that the trial court did not order enough makeup visitation time. We review visitation issues for manifest abuse of discretion. Kirshenbaum v. Kirshenbaum, <cross_reference>84 Wn. App. 798</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>804</cross_reference>,<cross_reference>929 P.2d 1204</cross_reference> (1997). In the revision hearing, the trial court awarded 44 hours of visitation, based on information presented to the commissioner below.

Negrie requests an additional 14 hours of visitation missed as of the trial court's revision hearing. The trial court, however, based its decision on the record before the commissioner and would not entertain new information about missed visitation. Upon a motion for revision, a superior court judge may only review facts and issues presented to the commissioner. In re Marriage of Moody, <cross_reference>137 Wn.2d 979</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>992</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>976 P.2d 1240</cross_reference>
(1999) (construing RCW <cross_reference>2.24.050</cross_reference>).

Because the trial court correctly limited review to information before the commissioner, we find no abuse of discretion. Nonetheless, to expedite resolution of continuing violations, we direct the trial court to conduct a hearing on visitation time missed during court proceedings. Negrie requests twice the makeup visitation time awarded by the trial court because it found Kemper in contempt of the Parenting Plan, the second time in 16 months. Under RCW <cross_reference>26.09.160</cross_reference>(3)(a), the court must award twice the amount of the time missed with the child if the court makes a second finding of contempt within a three-year period. On June 3, 1998, the King County Superior Court found Kemper in contempt for violating visitation provisions in the Parenting Plan. Within three years, on September 29, 1999, the superior court again found Kemper in contempt for changing visitation opportunities in violation of the Parenting Plan. Because the superior court found Kemper in contempt twice in three years, we find that the trial court erred in not ordering twice the visitation time. As a result, we order the trial court to consider RCW<cross_reference>26.09.160</cross_reference>(3)(a) on remand.

<center>            III. Court Costs, Attorney Fees and Civil Penalties</center>
Next, Negrie requests $750 in costs for the superior court's finding of contempt against Kemper. RCW <cross_reference>26.09.160</cross_reference>(2)(b)(ii) and (3)(b) mandate that the parent in contempt must pay to the other parent all court costs and attorney fees incurred as a result of noncompliance. Here, the trial court found both parties in contempt, but did not make a ruling on costs. Negrie proceeded pro se while Kemper acted through her attorney. We award costs to both parties and attorney fees to Kemper, except fees attributable to the late service.

Negrie also requests the Court to order Kemper to pay a $750 civil penalty for the second finding of contempt in three years. RCW<cross_reference>26.09.160</cross_reference>(3)(c) requires a civil penalty of at least $250 for the second finding of contempt. Elsewhere in the statute, the court must order a civil penalty of at least $100 for the first finding of contempt. RCW<cross_reference>26.09.160</cross_reference>(2)(b)(iii); In re Marriage of Wolk, <cross_reference>65 Wn. App. 356</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>359</cross_reference>,<cross_reference>828 P.2d 634</cross_reference> (1992). Here, the trial court found both parties in contempt but did not make a ruling on civil penalties. We order civil penalties against both parties. Accordingly, we award $250 to Negrie and $100 to Kemper.

<center>                      IV. Contempt and Mediation Costs</center>
Negrie argues that the trial court abused its discretion by finding him in contempt for demanding that Kemper pay 82 percent of mediation costs before they proceeded with mediation. RCW <cross_reference>26.09.160</cross_reference>(2)(b) states that the court shall find a parent in contempt if, based on all the facts and circumstances, the parent has acted in bad faith in not complying with the parenting plan. According to the Parenting Plan, the parents must submit visitation disputes to mediation in which allocation of costs will be determined:

<block_quote>  `Disputes between the parties, other than child support disputes, shall be submitted to mediation to a mutually agreed mediation center[,] individual, or agency. The cost of this process shall be allocated between the parties and paid as determined in the dispute resolution process.'</block_quote>

CP at 28.

On November 17, 1998, Negrie and Kemper set up a telephone conference with a mediator to settle visitation disputes. The mediator required them to agree on allocation of costs for mediation before proceeding. Negrie refused to proceed with mediation unless Kemper paid 82 percent of the costs, similar to the child support percentages. Kemper suggested that he pay 80 percent since he started the dispute resolution process. After he refused, she recommended that they split the costs 50 percent each as they had on a previous occasion. He refused again. Eventually, the mediation broke down when neither parent would change their position on costs.

It is true that the child support worksheet uses 82 percent to calculate Kemper's basic child support obligation because she makes more income than he does. Despite Negrie's lower income, however, the child support order also recognizes his substantial wealth from investments. Hewitt, <cross_reference>98 Wn. App. at 87</cross_reference> (Negrie had an IRA account worth $31,645 and non-IRA accounts worth over $175,000, while Kemper had at least $200,000 in investments, at least $186,436 in retirement accounts, and $140,000 equity in her home). Despite his investment wealth, Negrie demanded that Kemper pay 82 percent. Although she made an offer to compromise at 50 percent, he made no counteroffer. We cannot say that the trial court abused its discretion by finding him in contempt.

Negrie contends that he simply followed RCW <cross_reference>26.09.160</cross_reference> in filing a motion for contempt against Kemper for her noncompliance with the Parenting Plan. For that, he says he cannot be faulted. The motion for contempt against Kemper, however, is a separate issue. Contrary to Negrie's belief, the trial court did not find him in contempt for filing the motion. Rather, the trial court found him in contempt for insisting that Kemper pay 82 percent of mediation costs. We find no error.

Negrie argues that the trial court abused its discretion by ordering each party to pay 50 percent of the mediation costs. A court may not order a dispute resolution process, other than court action, if either parent is unable to afford the cost of such process. RCW <cross_reference>26.09.187</cross_reference>(1). To determine whether such a process is feasible, the court considers all relevant factors, including any agreements made between the parents as well as differences in financial ability. RCW <cross_reference>26.09.187</cross_reference>(1). Because Negrie has investment wealth and had previously agreed to pay 50 percent of mediation costs, we cannot say the trial court abused its discretion.

Kemper asserts for the first time on appeal that the trial court lacked jurisdiction to enforce provisions of the Parenting Plan because it allegedly expired after June 1999. Although RAP 2.5(a) allows a party to raise a jurisdictional issue for the first time on appeal, the party must actually file an appeal for the Court to reach the issue. RAP 2.4(a) (affirmative relief requires notice of appeal from respondent); In re Marriage of Payne, <cross_reference>82 Wn. App. 147</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>153</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>916 P.2d 968</cross_reference> (1996); see also Amalgamated Transit Union Local 587 v. State, ___ Wn.2d ___, <cross_reference>11 P.3d 762</cross_reference>,<cross_reference>778</cross_reference> (2000) (affirmative relief requires cross appeal). Because Kemper failed to file a cross appeal, the issue is not before us.

Finally, Kemper contends that the trial court erred in finding her in contempt for changing the dates of visitation opportunities. Since she has not filed a cross appeal, we do not reach this issue either. Payne,<cross_reference>82 Wn. App. at 153</cross_reference>.

<center>                                 CONCLUSION</center>
To summarize, the trial court failed to order twice the visitation time missed for Kemper's second finding of contempt in three years. We direct the trial court to determine the total visitation time missed and to award twice that amount to Negrie minus any time already made up. But, we conclude that the trial court did not abuse its discretion by finding Negrie in contempt and by ordering each parent to pay 50 percent of mediation costs. Nevertheless, the trial court failed to rule on Negrie's motion to strike and motion for sanctions. We remand for a ruling on the motions and accelerate the proceedings under RAP 18.12. See also Wolk,<cross_reference>65 Wn. App. at 359</cross_reference>. Finally, we award costs, attorney fees and civil penalties under RCW <cross_reference>26.09.160</cross_reference> as set forth herein.

We reverse and remand.

WE CONCUR: APPELWICK, J., COX, J.

<footnote_body><footnote_number>[fn1]</footnote_number> Negrie and Kemper have appeared before this Court previously. In re Paternity of Hewitt, <cross_reference>98 Wn. App. 85</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>988 P.2d 496</cross_reference> (1999), review denied,<cross_reference>141 Wn.2d 1007</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>10 P.3d 1073</cross_reference> (2000) (trial court abused its discretion in requiring Negrie to pay more than his proportionate share of travel expenses to visit child).</footnote_body>

<footnote_body><footnote_number>[fn2]</footnote_number> Although Negrie raises constitutional arguments implicating due process and equal protection, we do not reach them because he has failed to cite any relevant authority. Cowiche Canyon Conservancy v. Bosley,<cross_reference>118 Wn.2d 801</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>809</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>828 P.2d 549</cross_reference> (1992); City of Spokane v. Taxpayers of Spokane, <cross_reference>111 Wn.2d 91</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>96</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>758 P.2d 480</cross_reference> (1988).</footnote_body>

</unpublished></opinion_text>
</opinion>