<opinion>
<reporter_caption><center>REESE v. BARBEE, <citation>134 N.C. App. 728</citation> (1999)</center></reporter_caption>
<citation_line><center><citation>518 S.E.2d 571</citation></center></citation_line>
<caption><center>PORTIA REESE, Individually and as Administratrix of the Estate of CARLO</center><center>REESE, Plaintiff, v. LEE TODD BARBEE, Defendant</center></caption>
<docket><center>No. COA98-1487</center></docket><court><center>North Carolina Court of Appeals</center></court>
<date><center>Filed 7 September 1999</center>

</date>
<syllabus><bold>1. Appeal and Error — law of the case — same issue — earlier</bold><bold>appellate ruling binding</bold>

Although this appeal involves a different defendant-unnamed uninsured motorist insurer, the doctrine of law of the case provides that the earlier appellate ruling on the same issue of the applicable limitations period for service upon an insurance company providing coverage for an uninsured motorist is binding on this case because both appeals arose out of a single action, involve the same facts, and raise the identical issue of law.

<bold>2. Collateral Estoppel and Res Judicata — claims precluded —</bold><bold>issues precluded</bold>

Although this appeal involves a different defendant-unnamed uninsured motorist insurer, plaintiff is precluded by res judicata from re-litigating the identical issue of the applicable limitations period for service upon an insurance company providing coverage for an uninsured motorist.

</syllabus>
<posture>    Appeal by plaintiff from order entered 14 September 1998 by Judge B. Craig Ellis in Wake County Superior Court.  Heard in the Court of Appeals 16 August 1999.

</posture><attorneys>    <italic>Currie, Becton  Stewart, by Elwood Becton and Pipkin, Knott,</italic><italic>Clark  Berger, L.L.P., by Michael W. Clark and Ashmead P. Pipkin,</italic><italic>for plaintiff-appellant</italic>.

<italic>Cranfill, Sumner  Hartzog, L.L.P., by Stephanie Hutchins</italic><italic>Autry, for unnamed defendant-appellee North Carolina Farm Bureau</italic><italic>Mutual Insurance Company, Inc</italic>.

<italic>Yates, McLamb  Weyher, L.L.P., by Rodney E. Pettey, for</italic><italic>defendant-appellee Lee Todd Barbee</italic>.

</attorneys>
<opinion_byline>    JOHN, Judge.

</opinion_byline>
<opinion_text>    Plaintiff appeals the trial court's order allowing unnamed defendant North Carolina Farm Bureau Mutual Insurance Company's (Farm Bureau) motion to dismiss.  We affirm the trial court.<page_number>Page 729</page_number>

Pertinent factual and procedural information includes the following:  On 15 July 1994, defendant Lee Todd Barbee (defendant) was involved in an automobile collision with a vehicle in which Carlo Reese (decedent), the son of plaintiff Portia Reese, was a passenger.  Decedent subsequently died from injuries allegedly sustained in the collision.

On 26 July 1996, plaintiff commenced the instant wrongful death action, seeking recovery from unnamed defendants Nationwide Mutual Insurance Company (Nationwide) and North Carolina Farm Bureau Mutual Insurance Company (Farm Bureau) under the uninsured motorist provisions of respective insurance policies which plaintiff claimed provided coverage for decedent.  Only Farm Bureau is involved in the present appeal.

An original summons and subsequent alias and pluries summonses were obtained until successful service upon defendant occurred on 10 October 1996.  Summons was not issued to Farm Bureau until 25 April 1997 and was served 28 April 1997.  In its answer, Farm Bureau raised, <italic>inter alia</italic>, the defense that plaintiff's claims were barred by the statute of limitations.

Summons upon Nationwide was not issued until 24 April 1997, and its subsequent motion to dismiss on grounds plaintiff's claims were barred by the applicable limitations period was allowed by the trial court.  On plaintiff's appeal, this Court affirmed the ruling, holding the action against Nationwide had not been commenced within two years of decedent's death on 28 July 1994 as required by N.C.G.S. § <cross_reference>1-53</cross_reference>(4) (1996).  <italic>Reese v. Barbee</italic>,<cross_reference>129 N.C. App. 823</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>501 S.E.2d 698</cross_reference> (1998), <italic>aff'd</italic>, <cross_reference>350 N.C. 60</cross_reference>,<cross_reference>510 S.E.2d 374</cross_reference> (1999).

Farm Bureau filed a similar motion to dismiss plaintiff's claim on 17 June 1998.  The motion was allowed and plaintiff appeals.

Plaintiff maintains this Court is not bound by the previous opinion in <italic>Reese</italic>, noting that our Supreme Court, being evenly divided, stated the decision was without precedential value.<italic>Reese v. Barbee</italic>, <cross_reference>350 N.C. 60</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>510 S.E.2d 374</cross_reference> (1999)<italic>.</italic>  Farm Bureau responds that the earlier decision nonetheless constituted the law of the instant case and, further, that the doctrine of res judicata compels affirmance of the trial court's order.  We conclude Farm Bureau has the better of the argument.

<block_quote>    Where an appellate court decides questions and remands a case for further proceedings, its decisions on those questions become<page_number>Page 730</page_number>
law of the case, both in the subsequent proceedings in the trial court and upon a later appeal, where the same facts and the same questions of law are involved.</block_quote>

<italic>Sloan v. Miller Building, Corp</italic>., <cross_reference>128 N.C. App. 37</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>41</cross_reference>,<cross_reference>493 S.E.2d 460</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>463</cross_reference> (1997).

Although the present appeal involves a different unnamed defendant, both the current and previous appeals arose out of a single action, involve the same facts, and have raised the identical issue of law.  Moreover, both Nationwide and Farm Bureau became parties pursuant to N.C.G.S. § <cross_reference>20-279.21</cross_reference>(b)(3)(a) (1993). Accordingly, the earlier appellate ruling on the issue raised herein is binding  under the doctrine of law of the case.  <italic>See</italic><italic>also In the Matter of Appeal from Civil Penalty</italic>, <cross_reference>324 N.C. 373</cross_reference>,<cross_reference>384</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>379 S.E.2d 30</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>36</cross_reference> (1989) (subsequent panel of Court of Appeals bound by decision of earlier panel on same issue, even if in a different case, unless precedent has been overturned by a higher court).

In addition, the doctrine of res judicata prevents a plaintiff, who has once litigated an issue and had it finally determined adversely, from re-litigating the identical issue against a second defendant.  <italic>Crosland-Cullen Co. v. Crosland</italic>,<cross_reference>249 N.C. 167</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>170</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>105 S.E.2d 655</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>657</cross_reference> (1958).  In the case <italic>sub</italic><italic>judice</italic>, the issue of the applicable limitations period for service upon an insurance company providing coverage for an uninsured motorist has earlier been litigated by plaintiff and determined adversely to her.  The circumstance that the present appeal involves a different uninsured motorist insurer is of no consequence.  <italic>See id</italic>.

Affirmed.

Judges HUNTER and SMITH concur.<page_number>Page 731</page_number>

<center>                CASES REPORTED WITHOUT PUBLISHED OPINIONS</center><center>                          FILED 17 AUGUST 1999</center>
AKINS v. CITY OF THOMASVILLE        Davidson         Affirmed in part, No. 98-1142-2                       (96CVS1423)      Reversed in part, (95CVS1977)      and remanded

BETHUNE v. BETHUNE                  Harnett          Affirmed No. 98-762                          (96CVD1209)

BRENNER v. MAJER                    Watauga          Affirmed No. 98-886                          (94CVS220)

BUCHANAN v. CITY OF                 Davidson         Affirmed THOMASVILLE                       (97CVS2409) No. 98-1621-2

CITY OF CHARLOTTE v.                Mecklenburg      I.  No error as to BLYTHE CONSTR., INC.              (95CVS5154)          defendant's appeal. No. 98-870                                           II. Affirmed as to plaintiff's appeal.

CLAYTON v. McCLINTOCK               Guilford         Affirmed No. 98-900                          (96CVS7980)

CRAIG v. CLEARY                     Durham           No Error No. 98-809                          (95CVS0029)

DONALDSON v. N.C. DEP'T             Craven           Affirmed OF HUMAN RESOURCES                (96CVS1654) No. 98-1277

HARTWELL v. MAHAN                   Davidson         Affirmed No. 98-890                          (95CVD950)

HILL v. MORTON                      Forsyth          Vacated in part and No. 98-983                          (91CVS5839)      dismissed in part

JORDAN v. JORDAN                    Davie            Affirmed No. 98-1244                         (97CVD407)

LINEBERGER v. NATIONWIDE            Gaston           Affirmed MUT. INS. CO.                     (98CVS1750) No. 98-1063

LYNN v. BURNETTE                    Durham           Dismissed No. 98-1303                         (96CVS02815)

ROSS v. ROSS                        Onslow           Affirmed No. 98-967                          (96CVD2454)

STATE v. GRAHAM                     New Hanover      No Error No. 98-955                          (97CRS8961)

STATE v. HOWIE                      Mecklenburg      No Error No. 98-1030                         (95CRS56350)<page_number>Page 732</page_number>

STATE v. SOUSA                      Rowan            No Error No. 98-1123                         (96CRS00459) (96CRS00460) (96CRS00461) (96CRS00462) (96CRS00463) (96CES00464) (96CRS00465)

STATE v. STANLEY                    Johnston         New Trial No. 98-1139                         (95CRS2550)

WILLIAMS v. CITY OF                 Ind. Comm.       Affirmed WILMINGTON                        (545262) No. 98-788

<center>                         FILED 7 SEPTEMBER 1999</center>
ADAMS v. RJRA-I TRUST               Forsyth          No Error No. 98-1311                         (96CVS5021)

BEAVERS v. UNLIMITED                Ind. Comm.       Affirmed TREE SERV.                        (453229) No. 98-1627

CANEEL COVE HOMEOWNERS              New Hanover      Reversed ASS'N v. COURTLAND DEV., INC.     (91CVS2808) No. 98-598

COLLIER v. STAMPER                  Guilford         Affirmed No. 98-1344                         (93CVS7876)

GOGGINS v. BALATSIAS                Mecklenburg      Affirmed No. 98-1195                         (97CVS16564)

GORE v. KINSTON SERV., INC.         Ind. Comm.       Affirmed No. 98-1158                         (633744)

GUILFORD COUNTY v. TURLINGTON       Guilford         Affirmed No. 98-1256                         (87CVD2868)

HANSEN v. HANSEN                    Wake             Remanded for No. 98-1043                         (96CVD08358)     purposes of clerical modification and affirmed.

HELMS v. BAUCOM                     Union            New Trial No. 98-1279                         (97CVS00241)

IN RE APPEAL OF TWENTIETH           Prop. Tax Comm.  Affirmed CENTURY HEATING, CO.              (96PTC169) No. 98-1178

IN RE GILLESPIE                     Buncombe         Affirmed No. 99-294                          (98J106)<page_number>Page 733</page_number>

IN RE McMILLIAN                     Cumberland       Reversed and No. 98-1138                         (98J6)           Remanded (98J7)

IN RE SHANNON                       Mecklenburg      Affirmed No. 99-150                          (97J1152)

PATRICK v. ALLSTATE INS. CO.        Pitt             Reversed and No. 98-669-2                        (97CVS434)       Remanded

SAUNDERS v. EDENTON                 Ind. Comm.       Affirmed OB/GYN CTR.                       (308081) No. 98-1252

SHUGART v. VESTAL                   Surry            Affirmed No. 98-1177                         (97CVS448)

STATE v. ALLEN                      Forsyth          No Error No. 98-679                          (94CRS2883)

STATE v. BAILEY                     Forsyth          No Error No. 98-921                          (97CRS46057)

STATE v. BREEDEN                    Guilford         No Error No. 98-1041                         (97CRS23303) (97CRS23304) (97CRS23305) (97CRS23306) (97CRS23307) (97CRS23308) (97CRS23309) (97CRS23310) (97CRS30884) (97CRS30885) (97CRS31516) (97CRS31517) (97CRS31518) (97CRS32623)

STATE v. BROOKS                     Guilford         No Error No. 99-62                           (98CRS25787) (97CRS25788)

STATE v. CARDOZA                    Mecklenburg      No Error No. 98-799                          (97CRS38164) (97CRS38165) (97CRS38166) (97CRS38167) (97CRS38169) (97CRS38172)

STATE v. CASE                       Guilford         Affirmed No. 99-236                          (97CR571676)<page_number>Page 734</page_number>

STATE v. DIXON                      Rockingham       No Error No. 99-126                          (97CRS589)

STATE v. HARRIS                     Union            No Error No. 99-82                           (97CRS7448) (97CRS7449) (97CRS7451) (97CRS7452) (97CRS10637)

STATE v. HELMS                      Durham           No Error No. 98-1625                         (97CRS37855) (97CRS37856)

STATE v. HOLLARS                    Alamance         No Error No. 99412                           (95CRS1956)

STATE v. HUNT                       Orange           No Error No. 99-224                          (97CRS9452)

STATE v. JOHNSON                    Gaston           No Error No. 99-165                          (98CRS16246) (98CRS16247) (98CRS16248) (98CRS16249)

STATE v. LAMB                       Onslow           No Error No. 98-1141                         (97CRS16373)

STATE v. LOFTIN                     Forsyth          Affirmed No. 99-198                          (97CRS42311) (97CRS42312) (97CRS42351)

STATE v. MAULTSBY                   Columbus         Affirmed No. 99-42                           (96CRS6083) (96CRS6084) (97CRS5871)

STATE v. MIMS                       Alamance         No Error No. 99-297                          (98CRS9606) (98CRS9607) (98CRS9608) (98CRS20037)

STATE v. OKIJI                      Guilford         No Error No. 99-253                          (97CRS61447) (97CRS61448) (97CRS61449) (97CRS61450)

STATE v. REYNOLDS                   Randolph         No Error No. 98-1548                         (96CRS155) (96CRS12776)<page_number>Page 735</page_number>

STATE v. SARTORI                    Haywood          No Error No. 99-445                          (96CRS2678) (96CRS2679)

STATE v. TAYLOR                     Wayne            No Error No. 99-269                          (96CRS2012) (96CRS2013)

STATE v. VELASQUEZ                  Davidson         No Error No. 99-256                          (97CRS22833) (97CRS22834)

STATE v. WALLACE                    Durham           No Error No. 99-227                          (97CRS30977)

STATE v. WARD                       Hyde             No Error No. 99-325                          (97CRS845) (97CRS846)

STATE v. WHITE                      Lee              No Error No. 98-1596                         (97CRS5960) (97CRS5961)

STATE v. WHITE                      Mecklenburg      No Error No. 99-299                          (97CRS5596) (95CRS30760)

STATE v. WILLIAMS                   Mecklenburg      Affirmed No. 99-173                          (97CRS10980)

WHITAKER v. N.C. DIV. OF            Halifax          Affirmed MOTOR VEHICLES                    (97CVS609) No. 99-210

<page_number>Page 1</page_number>

</opinion_text>
</opinion>