<opinion unpublished=true>
<reporter_caption><center>STATE v. FRAZIER, COA09-1503 (N.C.App. 5-18-2010)</center></reporter_caption>
<caption><center>STATE OF NORTH CAROLINA v. TIMOTHY FRANKLIN FRAZIER.</center></caption>
<docket><center>No. COA09-1503</center></docket><court><center>North Carolina Court of Appeals</center></court>
<date><center>Filed 18 May 2010</center><center>This case not for publication</center>

</date>
<opinion_text><unpublished><footnote_body>[EDITOR'S NOTE: This case is unpublished as indicated by the issuing court.]</footnote_body>
Nash County Nos. 07 CRS 57373, 57398.

</unpublished></opinion_text>
<posture><unpublished>  Appeal by Defendant from judgments entered 10 June 2009 by Judge Walter H. Godwin, Jr. in Nash County Superior Court. Heard in the Court of Appeals 17 May 2010.

</unpublished></posture><attorneys><unpublished>  <italic>Attorney General Roy Cooper, by Assistant Attorney</italic><italic>General LaToya B. Powell, for the State.</italic>
 <italic>Paul F. Herzog for Defendant.</italic>

</unpublished></attorneys>
<opinion_byline><unpublished>  BEASLEY, Judge.

</unpublished></opinion_byline>
<opinion_text><unpublished>  Defendant Timothy Franklin Frazier appeals from convictions of three counts of indecent liberties with a child. Defendant was sentenced to a minimum of 16 and a maximum of 20 months and a minimum of 13 and a maximum of 16 months imprisonment.

On appeal, Defendant's counsel asserts that he was unable to identify any issue in the case that would potentially support a finding by this Court of prejudicial error and asks this Court to review the record for possible prejudicial error. Counsel has shown to the satisfaction of this Court that he has complied with the requirements of <italic>Anders v. California</italic>,<cross_reference>386 U.S. 738</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>18 L. Ed. 2d 493</cross_reference> (1967),<page_number>Page 2</page_number>
and <italic>State v. Kinch</italic>, <cross_reference>314 N.C. 99</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>331 S.E.2d 665</cross_reference> (1985). By letter dated 12 December 2009, Defendant's counsel advised Defendant of his right to file written arguments with this Court and provided him with the necessary documents to do so. Defendant has not filed any written arguments on his own behalf with this Court, and a reasonable time within which he could have done so has passed.

Pursuant to <italic>Anders</italic> and <italic>Kinch</italic>, we must fully examine the record to determine whether any issues of arguable merit appear therefrom or whether the appeal is wholly frivolous. Upon review of the entire record, we find the appeal to be wholly frivolous.

No Error.

Judges STEPHENS and ERVIN concur.

Report per Rule 30(e).<page_number>Page 1</page_number>

</unpublished></opinion_text>
</opinion>