<opinion>
<reporter_caption><center>WEEKLY CASES DISPOSED OF WITHOUT OPINION, <citation>11 Neb. App. xiv</citation> (2003)</center></reporter_caption><court><center>Nebraska Court of Appeals.</center></court>
<date><center>2003</center>

</date>     No. A-02-485: Beers v. Tallon. Appeal dismissed. See, rule 7A(2); Neb. Rev. Stat. § <cross_reference>25-1301</cross_reference> (Cum. Supp. 2000).

No. A-02-501: Martin v. Cameron. Appeal dismissed. See, rule 7A(2); Neb. Rev. Stat. § <cross_reference>25-1912</cross_reference> (Cum. Supp. 2000). See, also, Pofahl v. Pofahl, <cross_reference>196 Neb. 347</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>243 N.W.2d 55</cross_reference> (1976).

No. A-02-505: Martin v. Nesbitt. Appeal dismissed. See, rule 7A(2); Neb. Rev. Stat. § <cross_reference>25-1912</cross_reference> (Cum. Supp. 2000).

No. A-02-506: Martin v. Bagley. Appeal dismissed. See, rule 7A(2); Neb. Rev. Stat. § <cross_reference>25-1912</cross_reference> (Cum. Supp. 2000). See, also, Pofahl v. Pofahl, <cross_reference>196 Neb. 347</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>243 N.W.2d 55</cross_reference> (1976).

No. A-02-546: In re Interest of Andre R. Appeal dismissed. See, rule 7A(2); In re Interest of Andrew H. et al., <cross_reference>5 Neb. App. 716</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>564 N.W.2d 611</cross_reference>
(1997).

No. A-02-555: Schuelke v. Walker. Appeal dismissed. See, rule 7A(2); Neb. Rev. Stat. § <cross_reference>25-1912</cross_reference> (Cum. Supp. 2000).

No. A-02-640: State on behalf of Schincke v. Schincke. Appeal dismissed. See, rule 7A(2); Kinsey v. Colfer, Lyons, <cross_reference>258 Neb. 832</cross_reference>,<cross_reference>606 N.W.2d 78</cross_reference> (2000); Carroll v. Moore, <cross_reference>228 Neb. 561</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>423 N.W.2d 757</cross_reference>
(1988).

No. A-02-661: Thornton v. Thornton. Appeal dismissed. See, rule 7A(2); Hammond v. Hammond, <cross_reference>3 Neb. App. 536</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>529 N.W.2d 542</cross_reference> (1995).

No. A-02-694: State v. Smith. Stipulation allowed; appeal dismissed.

No. A-02-768: State v. Al-Sayagh. Appeal dismissed. See, rule 7A(2); State v. Pruett, <cross_reference>258 Neb. 797</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>606 N.W.2d 781</cross_reference> (2000).

No. A-02-770: State v. Al-Sayagh. Appeal dismissed. See, rule 7A(2); State v. Pruett, <cross_reference>258 Neb. 797</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>606 N.W.2d 781</cross_reference> (2000).

No. A-33-20021: State v. Mollner. Appellant's exception to district court's order of dismissal entered May 30, 2002, dismissed. See, rule 7A(2); Neb. Rev. Stat. § <cross_reference>29-2315.01</cross_reference> (Reissue 1995). See, also, Neb. Rev. Stat. § <cross_reference>25-2221</cross_reference> (Reissue 1995); State v. Johnson, <cross_reference>259 Neb. 942</cross_reference>,<cross_reference>613 N.W.2d 459</cross_reference> (2000).

No. A-02-159: Wolzen v. Neth. Motion of appellant to  dismiss appeal sustained; appeal dismissed.

Nos. A-02-301, A-02-302: State v. Heidelberg. Motion of appellee for summary affirmance sustained; judgment affirmed. See rule 7B(2).

No. A-02-421: State v. Lillard. Motion of appellee for  summary affirmance sustained; judgment affirmed. See rule 7B(2).

No. A-02-442: State v. Gardiner. Motion of appellant to  dismiss appeal sustained; appeal dismissed.

No. A-02-461: Adams v. Lint. By order of the court, appeal dismissed for failure to file briefs.

No. A-02-492: Mayer v. Nebraska Dept. of Motor Vehicles. Motion of appellant to dismiss appeal sustained; appeal dismissed.

No. A-02-602: State v. Ferguson. Appeal dismissed. See, rule 7A(2); Neb. Rev. Stat. § <cross_reference>25-1301</cross_reference> (Cum. Supp. 2000).

No. A-02-682: Russell v. Johanns. Appeal dismissed. See, rule 7A(2); Gordon v. Community First State Bank, <cross_reference>255 Neb. 637</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>587 N.W.2d 343</cross_reference>
(1998).

No. A-02-755: In re Estate of Rossenbach. Stipulation allowed; appeal dismissed with prejudice.

Nos. A-00-720, A-00-721: State v. Beers. Petition of appellant for further review overruled on August 29, 2002.

No. A-01-902: State v. SapaNajin, <cross_reference>11 Neb. App. 190</cross_reference> (2002). Petition of appellant for further review overruled on August 29, 2002.

No. A-01-1077: Ignacio v. ConAgra Beef Co. Petition of appellee for further review overruled on August 29, 2002.

No. A-01-1086: State v. Garcia. Petition of appellant for further review overruled on August 29, 2002.

No. A-01-1093: State v. Wilger. Petition of appellant for further review overruled on August 29, 2002.

No. A-01-1121: Trouba v. Cather  Sons Constr. Co. Petition of appellant for further review overruled on August 29, 2002.

No. A-01-1151: State v. Henry. Petition of appellee for further review overruled on August 29, 2002.

No. A-01-1208: State v. Parks. Petition of appellant for further review overruled on August 29, 2002.

No. A-01-1230: State v. Janis. Petition of appellant for further review overruled on August 29, 2002.

No. A-01-1390: State v. Steele. Petition of appellant for further review overruled on August 29, 2002.

No. A-02-030: State v. Cheshek. Petition of appellant for further review overruled on August 29, 2002.

No. A-02-040: State v. Metzger. Petition of appellant for further review overruled on August 29, 2002.

No. A-02-137: State v. Durst. Petition of appellant for further review overruled on August 29, 2002.

No. A-02-240: State v. Hovendick. Petition of appellant for further review overruled on August 29, 2002.

No. A-02-501: Martin v. Cameron. Petition of appellant for further review overruled on August 29, 2002.

No. A-01-072: Hartman v. Hartman. Petition of appellant for further review overruled on September 11, 2002.

No. A-01-693: Crouse v. Crouse. Petition of appellant for further review overruled on September 11, 2002.

No. A-01-900: State v. Robles. Petition of appellant for further review dismissed on September 11, 2002, for lack of jurisdiction.

Nos. A-01-1021, A-01-1022: In re Interest of Michael C. Petition of appellant for further review overruled on September 11, 2002.

Nos. A-01-1024, A-01-1050: State v. Miller. Petition of appellant for further review dismissed on September 11, 2002, for lack of jurisdiction.

No. A-01-1120: Coffey v. Waldinger Corp., <cross_reference>11 Neb. App. 293</cross_reference> (2002). Petition of appellant for further review overruled on September 11, 2002.

No. A-01-1124: Jones v. IBP, inc. Petition of appellant for further review overruled on September 11, 2002.

No. A-01-1212: State v. Mata. Petition of appellant for further review overruled on September 16, 2002.

Nos. A-01-1333, A-01-1334: In re Interest of Emilio L. Petition of appellant for further review overruled on September 11, 2002.

No. A-02-944: State v. Witmer. Appeal dismissed. See rule 7A(2). Multiple appeals from the same case are prohibited. See rule 1C.

No. A-02-953: River City Life Center v. Douglas Cty. Bd. of Equal. Appeal dismissed. See Neb. Rev. Stat. § <cross_reference>25-1905</cross_reference> (Reissue 1995). See, also, Neb. Rev. Stat. § <cross_reference>77-202.04</cross_reference> (Cum. Supp. 2000).

No. A-02-980: In re Estate of McKamy. Motion of appellant to dismiss appeal sustained; appeal dismissed.

No. A-02-1021: Brown v. Republican Valley Windworks. Appeal dismissed. See, rule 7A(2); Neb. Rev. Stat. § <cross_reference>25-1315</cross_reference>(1) (Cum. Supp. 2000); Scottsdale Ins. Co. v. City of Lincoln, <cross_reference>260 Neb. 372</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>617 N.W.2d 806</cross_reference>
(2000).

No. A-02-1041: Ash v. Hehner. Appeal dismissed. See, rule 7A(2); Neb. Rev. Stat. § <cross_reference>25-1912</cross_reference> (Cum. Supp. 2000). No. A-02-1113: State v. Vasser. Stipulation allowed; appeal dismissed.

No. A-02-1114: State v. Vasser. Stipulation allowed; appeal dismissed.

No. A-02-868: Tobin v. Lasauskas. Appeal dismissed. See, rule 7A(2); Bass v. Dalton, <cross_reference>218 Neb. 379</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>355 N.W.2d 225</cross_reference> (1984).

No. A-02-884: Prokop v. Santin. Motion of appellee for summary dismissal sustained. See, rule 7B(1); Neb. Rev. Stat. § <cross_reference>25-1912</cross_reference>
(Cum. Supp. 2002); Federal Land Bank v. McElhose, <cross_reference>222 Neb. 448</cross_reference>,<cross_reference>384 N.W.2d 295</cross_reference> (1986).

No. A-02-887: Van Natter v. Van Natter. Motion of appellant to dismiss appeal sustained; appeal dismissed.

No. A-02-904: Mumin v. Hart. Appeal dismissed. See, rule 7A(2); Neb. Rev. Stat. § <cross_reference>25-1301</cross_reference> (Cum. Supp. 2002). See, also, Mumin v. Hart, <cross_reference>9 Neb. App. 404</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>612 N.W.2d 261</cross_reference> (2000).

No. A-02-908: Johnson v. Department of Corr. Servs. Motion of appellant to dismiss appeal sustained; appeal dismissed.

No. A-02-912: In re Interest of Jasmine P.  Jordin L. Motion of appellant to dismiss appeal sustained; appeal dismissed.

No. A-02-956: State v. Zakrzewski. Motion of appellant to dismiss appeal sustained; appeal dismissed.

No. A-02-964: Minflow, Inc. v. First District Assn. Stipulation allowed; matter remanded to district court with directions to vacate judgment and dismiss this action with prejudice; each party to pay own costs.

No. A-02-967: Mumin v. Dees. Appeal dismissed. See rule 7A(2).

No. A-02-977: State v. Fouts. Motion of appellant to dismiss appeal sustained; appeal dismissed.

No. A-02-993: State v. Covey. Appeal summarily dismissed. See, rule 7A(2); State v. Ruiz-Medina, <cross_reference>8 Neb. App. 529</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>597 N.W.2d 403</cross_reference> (1999).

No. A-02-1006: State v. Smith. Appeal dismissed. See, Neb. Rev. Stat. § <cross_reference>29-825</cross_reference> (Cum. Supp. 2000); State v. Ruiz-Medina,<cross_reference>8 Neb. App. 529</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>597 N.W.2d 403</cross_reference> (1999).

No. A-02-1015: State v. Lombardo. Motion of appellant to dismiss appeal sustained; appeal dismissed.

No. A-02-1016: State v. Lombardo. Motion of appellant to dismiss appeal sustained; appeal dismissed.

No. A-01-802: <bold>In re Trust Created by Charles E. Fleecs.</bold> Petition of appellee for further review overruled on February 12, 2003.

No. S-01-1055: <bold>Big Crow v. City of Rushville</bold>, <cross_reference>11 Neb. App. 498</cross_reference>
(2002). Petition of appellee for further review sustained on February 12, 2003.

No. A-02-677: <bold>State v. Vargas-Godinez.</bold> Petition of appellant for further review overruled on February 12, 2003.

No. A-02-734: <bold>State v. Wessling.</bold> Petition of appellant for further review overruled on February 12, 2003.

No. A-02-745: <bold>State v. Core.</bold> Petition of appellant for further review overruled on February 12, 2003.

No. A-02-1288: <bold>Anzalone v. Department of Corr. Servs.</bold> Petition of appellant for further review overruled on February 12, 2003.

No. A-03-176: Lynch v. State Farm Mut. Auto. Ins. Co. Appeal dismissed. See, rule 7A(2); Gordon v. Community First State Bank,<cross_reference>255 Neb. 637</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>587 N.W.2d 343</cross_reference> (1998).

No. A-03-196: State ex rel. Tyler v. Britten. Motion of appellant to dismiss appeal sustained; appeal dismissed.

No. A-02-235: State v. Castillo, <cross_reference>11 Neb. App. 622</cross_reference> (2003). Petition of appellant for further review overruled on April 30, 2003.

No. A-02-788: In re Interest of Chico B.  Cheri B. Petition of appellant for further review overruled on April 30, 2003.

No. A-03-273: State v. Chen. Appeal dismissed. See, rule 7A(2); Neb. Rev. Stat. § <cross_reference>29-2101</cross_reference> (Cum. Supp. 2002); State v. McCracken,<cross_reference>248 Neb. 576</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>537 N.W.2d 502</cross_reference> (1995); State v. Engleman, <cross_reference>5 Neb. App. 485</cross_reference>,<cross_reference>560 N.W.2d 851</cross_reference> (1997). See, also, State v. McCormick and Hall,<cross_reference>246 Neb. 271</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>518 N.W.2d 133</cross_reference> (1994).

No. A-03-317: Barnard v. Belding. Appeal dismissed. See, rule 7A(2); O'Connor v. Kaufman, <cross_reference>255 Neb. 120</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>582 N.W.2d 350</cross_reference> (1998).

No. A-03-332: Hernandez v. Hernandez. Stipulation allowed; appeal dismissed at cost of appellant.

No. A-03-362: State v. Nelson. Motion of appellant to dismiss appeal sustained; appeal dismissed.

No. A-03-407: Sindelar v. Creston Fertilizer Co. Appeal dismissed. See, rule 7A(2); State v. Plymate, <cross_reference>8 Neb. App. 513</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>598 N.W.2d 65</cross_reference>
(1999); Forrest v. Eilenstine, <cross_reference>5 Neb. App. 77</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>554 N.W.2d 802</cross_reference> (1996) (time for filing appeal is not tolled unless proceedings leading up to motion for new trial constitute trial).

No. A-03-450: Cullum v. Department of Corr. Servs. Appeal dismissed. See, rule 7A(1); Neb. Rev. Stat. § <cross_reference>25-1912</cross_reference>(1) (Cum. Supp. 2002).

No. A-03-490: Lyle v. City of Hastings. Appeal dismissed. See, rule 7A(2); Burke v. Blue Cross Blue Shield, <cross_reference>251 Neb. 607</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>558 N.W.2d 577</cross_reference>
(1997).

No. A-33-30017: State v. Martinez. Application to docket appeal under Neb. Rev. Stat. § <cross_reference>29-2315.01</cross_reference> (Reissue 1995) denied for lack of final order. See State v. Wieczorek, <cross_reference>252 Neb. 705</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>565 N.W.2d 481</cross_reference>
(1997).

Nos. A-01-995, A-01-996: Bochart v. Glinsmann. Petitions of appellee for further review overruled on May 23, 2003.

No. A-01-596: State v. Turner. Motion of appellee for summary affirmance sustained; judgment affirmed. See rule 7B(2).

Nos. A-01-625, A-01-936: State v. Mackey. Motion of appellee for summary dismissal sustained. See rule 7B(1).

No. A-01-670: Bert Murphy, L.L.C. v. Carhart. Stipulation allowed; appeal dismissed with prejudice; each party to pay own costs.

No. A-01-675: Caton v. Nebraska Dept. of Corr. Servs. Appeal dismissed as moot. See Hron v. Donlan, <cross_reference>259 Neb. 259</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>609 N.W.2d 379</cross_reference>
(2000).

No. A-01-692: In re Interest of Shaylyn B.  Shanice G. By order of the court, appeal dismissed for failure to file briefs.

No. A-01-792: Antillon v. Wertz. Stipulation allowed; appeal dismissed; each party to pay own costs.

No. A-01-809: Todd v. Barta. Stipulation allowed; appeal dismissed.

No. A-01-819: State v. Dawson. Motion of appellee for summary affirmance sustained; judgment affirmed. See rule 7B(2).

No. A-01-837: State v. Thompson. Motion of appellee for summary affirmance sustained. See, Sindelar v. Hanel Oil, Inc., <cross_reference>254 Neb. 975</cross_reference>,<cross_reference>581 N.W.2d 405</cross_reference> (1998); State v. Bush, <cross_reference>254 Neb. 260</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>576 N.W.2d 177</cross_reference>
(1998). See, also, State v. Feiling, <cross_reference>255 Neb. 427</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>585 N.W.2d 456</cross_reference>
(1998); State v. Gangahar, 9  Neb. App. 205, <cross_reference>609 N.W.2d 690</cross_reference> (2000); State v. Linn, <cross_reference>3 Neb. App. 332</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>526 N.W.2d 683</cross_reference> (1995); State v. Stuthman,<cross_reference>2 Neb. App. 317</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>509 N.W.2d 410</cross_reference> (1993).

No. A-01-921: In re Interest of Emilio L. Affirmed. See rule 7A(1).

No. A-01-937: State v. Burrell. Motion of appellee for summary affirmance sustained; judgment affirmed. See, rule 7B(2); State v. Andersen, <cross_reference>232 Neb. 187</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>440 N.W.2d 203</cross_reference> (1989); State v. Alcaraz,<cross_reference>8 Neb. App. 215</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>590 N.W.2d 414</cross_reference> (1999).

Nos. A-01-945, A-01-946: State v. Tyler. By order of the court, appeal dismissed for failure to file briefs.

No. A-01-950: Stahla v. Stahla. Motion of appellant to dismiss appeal sustained; appeal dismissed.

No. A-01-980: Quick v. Quick. Stipulation allowed; appeal dismissed.<page_number>Page xv</page_number>


</opinion>