<opinion unpublished=true>
<reporter_caption><center>STATE v. CLARK, 11-280 (La.App. 3 Cir. 10/5/11)</center></reporter_caption>
<caption><center>STATE OF LOUISIANA v. WILBERT CLARK.</center></caption>
<docket><center>No. 11-280.</center></docket><court><center>Court of Appeal of Louisiana, Third Circuit.</center></court>
<date><center>October 5, 2011.</center><center>NOT DESIGNATED FOR PUBLICATION</center><page_number>Page 1</page_number>

</date>
<posture><unpublished><footnote_body>[EDITOR'S NOTE: This case is unpublished as indicated by the issuing court.]</footnote_body>
APPEAL FROM THE FIFTEENTH JUDICIAL DISTRICT COURT PARISH OF LAFAYETTE, NO. CR 117650 HONORABLE EDWARD D. RUBIN, DISTRICT JUDGE.

</unpublished></posture><attorneys><unpublished>  Michael Harson, District Attorney — Fifteenth Judicial District, Keith A. Stutes — Assistant District Attorney, Lafayette, Louisiana, COUNSEL FOR APPELLEE: State of Louisiana.<page_number>Page 2</page_number>

Edward K. Bauman, Louisiana Appellate Project, Lake Charles, Louisiana, COUNSEL FOR DEFENDANT/APPELLANT: Wilbert Clark.

</unpublished></attorneys><panel><unpublished>  Court composed of JOHN D. SAUNDERS, J. DAVID PAINTER, and JAMES T. GENOVESE, Judges.<page_number>Page 3</page_number>

</unpublished></panel>
<opinion_byline><unpublished>  GENOVESE, Judge.

</unpublished></opinion_byline>
<opinion_text><unpublished>  On October 17, 2007, the grand jury indicted Defendant, Wilbert Clark, on the charge of first degree murder. On February 2, 2010, Defendant entered a guilty plea to the amended charge of manslaughter. He was sentenced to serve forty years without the benefit of probation, parole, or suspension of sentence.<footnote_reference>[fn1]</footnote_reference>

Defendant's appellate counsel has filed a brief in this matter pursuant to <italic>Anders v. California</italic>,<cross_reference>386 U.S. 738</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>87 S.Ct. 1396</cross_reference> (1967). For the following reasons, we affirm Defendant's conviction and sentence, as amended, remand the matter with instructions, and grant Defendant's appellate counsel's motion to withdraw.

<center>                                  <bold><underline>FACTS</underline></bold></center>
At the guilty plea proceeding, the State set forth the following factual basis in support of Defendant's plea. On April 19, 2007, while the victim, Sandra Anderson, was sleeping, Defendant poured gasoline on her and set her on fire. The victim woke up screaming, and Defendant ran from the house. The victim died as a result.

<center>                              <bold><underline>ERRORS PATENT</underline></bold></center>
In accordance with La. Code Crim.P. art. <cross_reference>920</cross_reference>, all appeals are reviewed for errors patent on the face of the record. We find one actionable error patent concerning Defendant's sentence. The trial court erred in ordering Defendant's sentence to be served without benefit of parole. Defendant was sentenced to serve forty years without the benefit of probation, parole, or suspension of sentence. Louisiana Revised Statutes <cross_reference>14:31</cross_reference>(B) provides that a person convicted of<page_number>Page 4</page_number>
manslaughter "shall be imprisoned at hard labor for not more than forty years[,]" and it does not set forth any prohibition against probation, parole, or suspension of sentence. Louisiana Code of Criminal Procedure Article <cross_reference>893</cross_reference> prohibits the trial court from suspending a sentence and placing on probation persons convicted of certain crimes of violence, including manslaughter, but it does not prohibit parole. <italic>See</italic> La.R.S. <cross_reference>14:2</cross_reference>(B). Thus, the trial court erred in ordering Defendant's sentence to be served without the benefit of parole. Accordingly, we amend Defendant's sentence to delete the denial of parole eligibility and instruct the trial court to make an entry in the minutes reflecting this change. <italic>State v.</italic><italic>Batiste</italic>, 09-521 (La.App. 3 Cir. 12/9/09), <cross_reference>25 So.3d 981</cross_reference>; <italic>State v. Levy</italic>, 08-1467 (La.App. 3 Cir. 6/10/09), <cross_reference>12 So.3d 1135</cross_reference>; and <italic>State v.</italic><italic>Dupree</italic>, 07-98 (La.App. 3 Cir. 5/30/07), <cross_reference>957 So.2d 966</cross_reference>.

<center>                             <bold><underline>ANDERS ANALYSIS</underline></bold></center>
Pursuant to <italic>Anders</italic>, <cross_reference>386 U.S. 738</cross_reference>, Defendant's appellate counsel has filed a brief stating that he could find no errors on appeal that would support a reversal of the Defendant's conviction or sentence. Thus, counsel seeks to withdraw.

In <italic>State v. Benjamin</italic>,<cross_reference>573 So.2d 528</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>531</cross_reference> (La.App. 4 Cir. 1990), the fourth circuit explained the <italic>Anders</italic> analysis:

<block_quote>    When appointed counsel has filed a brief indicating that no non-frivolous issues and no ruling arguably supporting an appeal were found after a conscientious review of the record,  <italic>Anders</italic> requires that counsel move to withdraw. This motion will not be acted on until this court performs a thorough independent review of the record after providing the appellant an opportunity to file a brief in his or her own behalf. This court's review of the record will consist of (1) a review of the bill of information or indictment to insure the defendant was properly charged; (2) a review of all minute entries to insure the defendant was present at all crucial stages of the proceedings, the jury composition and verdict were correct and the sentence is legal; (3) a review of all pleadings in the record; (4) a review of the jury sheets;<page_number>Page 5</page_number>
and (5) a review of all transcripts to determine if any ruling provides an arguable basis for appeal. Under C.Cr.P. art. <cross_reference>914.1</cross_reference>(D) this Court will order that the appeal record be supplemented with pleadings, minute entries and transcripts when the record filed in this Court is not sufficient to perform this review. 6</block_quote>

Pursuant to <italic>Anders</italic> and <italic>Benjamin</italic>, we have performed a thorough review of the record, including pleadings, minute entries, the charging instrument, and the transcripts. Defendant was properly charged by bill of indictment, which was amended, and was present and represented by counsel at all crucial stages of the proceedings. Defendant entered a free and voluntary guilty plea after properly being advised of his rights in accordance with <italic>Boykin v. Alabama</italic>,<cross_reference>395 U.S. 238</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>89 S.Ct. 1709</cross_reference> (1969). Additionally, Defendant received a legal sentence, as amended. We have found no issues which would support an assignment of error on appeal. Therefore, Defendant's appellate counsel's motion to withdraw is granted.

<bold>CONVICTION AND SENTENCE AFFIRMED AS AMENDED. REMANDED</bold><bold>WITH INSTRUCTIONS. MOTION TO WITHDRAW GRANTED.</bold>

This opinion is NOT DESIGNATED FOR PUBLICATION. Uniform Rules — Courts of Appeal, Rule 2-16.3.<page_number>Page 6</page_number>

<center>                                  <bold><underline>ORDER</underline></bold></center>
After consideration of appellate defense counsel's motion to withdraw as attorney of record and the appeal presently pending in the above-captioned matter;

<bold>IT IS HEREBY ORDERED</bold> that appellate defense counsel's motion to withdraw as attorney of record is granted.

<bold>THUS DONE AND SIGNED</bold> this ______ day of September, 2011.

<footnote_body><footnote_number>[fn1]</footnote_number> The minutes of sentencing indicate that the trial court sentenced Defendant in accordance with the plea agreement, whereas, the sentencing transcript does not clearly set forth that the sentence imposed was part of the plea agreement. Nevertheless, Defendant is not challenging his sentence on appeal; thus, the issue need not be addressed.</footnote_body>

</unpublished></opinion_text>
</opinion>