<opinion>
<reporter_caption><center>IN THE INTEREST OF A.F., 02-0783 (Iowa App. 8-14-2002)</center></reporter_caption>
<caption><center>IN THE INTEREST OF A.F., Minor Child, B.F., Mother, Appellant.</center></caption>
<docket><center>No. 2-648 / 02-0783.</center></docket><court><center>Court of Appeals of Iowa.</center></court>
<date><center>Filed August 14, 2002.</center>

</date>
<posture>  Appeal from the Iowa District Court for Polk County, LINDA READE, Judge.

The mother appeals from the juvenile court's termination of her parental rights to her daughter. <bold>AFFIRMED</bold>.

</posture><attorneys>  Joseph Renzo, Des Moines, for appellant.

Bryan Tingle, Des Moines, for father.

Thomas J. Miller, Attorney General, Mary Pippin, Assistant Attorney General, and Celene Coffman, Assistant County Attorney, for appellee-State.

Samuel Marks, Urbandale, guardian ad litem for minor child.

</attorneys><panel>  Considered by SACKETT, C.J., and MAHAN and ZIMMER, JJ.

</panel>
<opinion_byline>  <bold>MAHAN, J</bold>.

</opinion_byline>
<opinion_text>  The mother appeals from the juvenile court's termination of her parental rights to her daughter. She contends (1) the Iowa Department of Human Services (DHS) failed to provide reasonable efforts to reunify her and her daughter; and (2) the termination was not in the best interests of the child. We affirm.

We review termination proceedings de novo. <italic>In re C.B</italic>.,<cross_reference>611 N.W.2d 489</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>492</cross_reference> (Iowa 2000). Our primary concern in termination proceedings is the best interests of the child. <italic>Id</italic>. To support the termination of parental rights, the State must establish the grounds for termination by clear and convincing evidence. <italic>Id</italic>.

We find the mother did not preserve error with regard to her argument that DHS failed to make reasonable reunification efforts. The sufficiency of services should be raised at the removal or review hearing or when services are offered. <italic>In re L.M.W.,</italic><cross_reference>518 N.W.2d 804</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>807</cross_reference> (Iowa Ct.App. 1994). In addition, it is too late to challenge the service plan at the termination hearing. <italic>Id</italic>. In any event, these issues must be raised before appeal. <italic>In re C.M.,</italic><cross_reference>526 N.W.2d 562</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>566</cross_reference> (Iowa Ct.App. 1994). No evidence appears in the record that the mother challenged the services provided at the appropriate times. We accordingly decline to address this issue on appeal.

Upon a careful review of the record, we also find the termination of the mother's parental rights is in the best interests of the child.<footnote_reference>[fn1]</footnote_reference> We find there is no chance of immediate reunification because she is still incarcerated. There is also little chance of imminent reunification once she is released from prison. She has no suitable employment or permanent residence for her child. She also has parenting issues that are unresolved. DHS offered the mother a myriad of services to facilitate reunification. However, the mother did not take advantage of these services, and failed to progress. In fact, she admitted that in the six months prior to the termination hearing she made no effort to regain custody of her daughter. The mother has had no contact with DHS, her attorney, or her child since November 2001. The amount of patience for the mother's actions must be reasonably limited because "patience with parents can soon translate into intolerable hardship for their children." <italic>In re</italic><italic>A.Y.H.,</italic> <cross_reference>508 N.W.2d 92</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>96</cross_reference> (Iowa Ct.App. 1993). Therefore, the best interests of the child warrant the termination of the mother's parental rights. Accordingly, we affirm the juvenile court.

<bold>AFFIRMED</bold>.

<footnote_body><footnote_number>[fn1]</footnote_number> It appears from the mother's petition that she is also claiming the court should not have terminated her rights because her daughter was in the custody of a relative. <italic>See</italic> Iowa Code ยง <cross_reference>232.116</cross_reference>(3)(a) (2001). We question whether the mother has preserved this issue for our review. As a general rule, an issue not presented in the juvenile court may not be raised for the first time on appeal. <italic>In re C.M.,</italic> <cross_reference>526 N.W.2d 562</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>566</cross_reference> (Iowa Ct.App. 1994). Because the juvenile court did not address this issue, error was not preserved. Even if the mother had preserved error on this issue, her claim is without merit. The court has discretion, based on the unique circumstances of each case and the best interests of the child, whether to apply the factors in section<cross_reference>232.116</cross_reference>(3) to save the parent-child relationship. <italic>In re C.L.H.,</italic><cross_reference>500 N.W.2d 449</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>454</cross_reference> (Iowa Ct.App. 1993). Because we find the termination was in the best interests of the child, we decline to apply the exception.</footnote_body>

</opinion_text>
</opinion>