<opinion>
<reporter_caption><center>PARKER v. COM., <citation>47 Va. App. 666</citation> (2006)</center></reporter_caption>
<citation_line><center><citation>626 S.E.2d 459</citation></center></citation_line>
<caption><center>Malcolm PARKER, Appellant, v. COMMONWEALTH of Virginia, Appellee.</center></caption>
<docket><center>Record No. 1592-04-4.</center></docket><court><center>Court of Appeals of Virginia.</center></court>
<date><center>February 21, 2006.</center>

</date><panel>  Present FITZPATRICK, C.J., BENTON, ELDER, FRANK, HUMPHREYS, CLEMENTS, FELTON, KELSEY, McCLANAHAN and HALEY, JJ.

<center>                  Upon a Petition for Rehearing En Banc</center></panel>
<opinion_text>  On January 24, 2006 came the appellee, by the Attorney General of Virginia, and filed a petition requesting that the Court set aside the judgment rendered herein on, and grant a rehearing <italic>en</italic><italic>banc</italic> thereof.

On consideration whereof, the petition for rehearing <italic>en banc</italic>
is granted, the mandate entered herein on is stayed pending the decision of the Court <italic>en banc,</italic> and the appeal is reinstated on the docket of this Court.

Notwithstanding the provisions of Rule 5A:35, the following briefing schedule hereby is established: Appellant shall file an opening brief upon rehearing <italic>en banc</italic> within 21 days of the date of entry of this order; appellee shall file an appellee's brief upon rehearing <italic>en banc</italic> within 14 days of the date on which the opening brief is filed; and appellant may file a reply brief upon rehearing <italic>en banc</italic> within 14 days of the date on which the appellee's brief is filed. The appellant shall attach as an addendum to the opening brief upon rehearing <italic>en banc</italic> a copy of the opinion previously rendered by the Court in this matter. It is further ordered that the appellee shall file<page_number>Page 667</page_number>
twelve additional copies of the appendix previously filed in this case.

</opinion_text>
</opinion>