<opinion>
<reporter_caption><center>CUMULATIVE LIST OF CASES DISPOSED OF WITHOUT OPINION, <citation>1 Neb. App. xvi</citation> (1993)</center></reporter_caption><court><center>Nebraska Court of Appeals.</center>

</court>
CUMULATIVE LIST OF CASES DISPOSED OF WITHOUT OPINION

No. A-90-611: <bold>Brokaw v. Moon.</bold> Stipulation allowed; appeal dismissed.

No. A-90-618: <bold>Stevens v. Shreeves.</bold> Stipulation allowed; appeal dismissed.

No. A-90-950: <bold>State v. Matthews.</bold> Appeal dismissed. See Rule 7A(2).

No. A-90-1011: <bold>State v. Pierce.</bold> Cause having not been shown, appeal dismissed as moot.

No. A-90-1029: <bold>In re Appeal of Fremont Plaza.</bold> Stipulation allowed; appeal dismissed.

No. A-90-1068: <bold>Eure v. Eure.</bold> Appeal dismissed. See Rule 7A(2).

No. A-90-1102: <bold>M  M Grain Co. v. Stutzman.</bold> Motion of appellee for summary dismissal sustained. See Rule 7B(1).

No. A-90-1168: <bold>Newman v. Newman.</bold> Stipulation allowed; appeal dismissed with prejudice.

No. A-90-1263: <bold>State v. Wokoma.</bold> Stipulation allowed; appeal dismissed.

No. A-91-003: <bold>Jeppesen v. Arp.</bold> Stipulation allowed; appeal dismissed.

No. A-91-006: <bold>Krafka v. Krafka.</bold> Stipulation allowed; appeal and cross-appeal dismissed.

No. A-91-100: <bold>Abdullah v. Gunter.</bold> Stipulation allowed; appeal dismissed.

No. A-91-113: <bold>Howell v. Howell.</bold> Motion of appellant to dismiss appeal sustained; appeal dismissed.

No. A-91-154: <bold>Peterson v. Peterson.</bold> Stipulation allowed; appeal dismissed.

No. A-91-212: <bold>Frics v. Chase.</bold> Appeal dismissed. See Rule 7A(2).

No. A-91-291: <bold>Anson v. Anson.</bold> Stipulation allowed; appeal dismissed with prejudice; each party to pay own costs.

No. A-91-492: <bold>State v. Grant.</bold> Affirmed. See Rule 7A(1).

No. A-91-595: <bold>State v. De Los Santos.</bold> Stipulation allowed; appeal dismissed.

No. A-91-609: <bold>Friedlan v. Miller Farm Home Oil Serv.</bold>
Motion of appellant to dismiss appeal sustained; appeal dismissed.

No. A-91-630: <bold>State v. Bandur.</bold> Affirmed. See Rule 7A(1).<page_number>Page xvii</page_number>


</opinion>
