<opinion unpublished=true>
<reporter_caption><center>RIVERTON CITY v. CHRISTENSEN, <citation>2005 UT App 354</citation></center></reporter_caption>
<caption><center>Riverton City, Plaintiff and Appellee v. Shane R. Christensen, Defendant</center><center>and Appellant.</center></caption>
<docket><center>Case No. 20030983-CA.</center></docket><court><center>Utah Court of Appeals.</center></court>
<date><center>Filed August 18, 2005.</center><center>(Not For Official Publication).</center>

</date>
<posture><unpublished><footnote_body>[EDITOR'S NOTE: This case is unpublished as indicated by the issuing court.]</footnote_body>
Appeal from the Third District, Sandy Department, 031400353 The Honorable Michael K. Burton.

</unpublished></posture><attorneys><unpublished>  Shane R. Christensen, St. George, Appellant Pro Se.

</unpublished></attorneys><panel><unpublished>  Before Judges Bench, Davis, and McHugh.

</unpublished></panel>
<opinion_text><unpublished><center>                           MEMORANDUM DECISION</center></unpublished></opinion_text>
<opinion_byline><unpublished>  PER CURIAM:

</unpublished></opinion_byline>
<opinion_text><unpublished>  This case originated in the Riverton Justice Court. Shane R. Christensen appealed the decision of that court to the district court. Following a trial de novo, Christensen was convicted of two infractions. Christensen appeals this decision. Based upon a review of the entire record, we dismiss for lack of jurisdiction.

Utah Code section 78-5-120 governs appeals from justice courts.<underline>See</underline> Utah Code Ann. ยง 78-5-120 (2002). Section 78-51-20(7) states that "[t]he decision of the district court is final and may not be appealed unless the district court rules on the constitutionality of a statute or ordinance." <underline>Id.</underline>
ยง 78-5-120(7). "By enacting [section 78-5-120] the Utah Legislature . . . specifically and intentionally limited the issues that may be appealed from a district court's judgment." <underline>State v. Hinson</underline>,<cross_reference>966 P.2d 273</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>276</cross_reference> (Utah Ct.App. 1998). Accordingly, "absent an issue regarding the constitutionality of a statute or ordinance, the decision of the district court is final and this court has no jurisdiction to hear an appeal thereof." <underline>Id.</underline> at 277.

Although Christensen now alleges violations of various constitutional provisions, these allegations were not pursued below and were not decided by the district court. Therefore, this appeal is not taken from a district court ruling on the constitutionality of a statute or ordinance.

As a result, this appeal is not within our appellate jurisdiction. Once this court has determined that it lacks jurisdiction, "it retains only the authority to dismiss the action." <underline>Varian-Eimac, Inc. v. Lamoreaux</underline>, <cross_reference>767 P.2d 569</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>570</cross_reference>
(Utah Ct.App. 1989).

Accordingly, this appeal is dismissed.

Russell W. Bench, Associate Presiding Judge, James Z. Davis, Judge, and Carolyn B. McHugh, Judge.

</unpublished></opinion_text>
</opinion>