<opinion>
<reporter_caption><center>IN RE ABRAMOWITZ, <citation>197 N.J. 504</citation> (2009)</center></reporter_caption>
<citation_line><center><citation>964 A.2d 301</citation></center></citation_line>
<caption><center>IN THE MATTER OF ARNOLD M. ABRAMOWITZ, AN ATTORNEY AT LAW (ATTORNEY NO.</center><center>027231976).</center></caption><court><center>Supreme Court of New Jersey.</center></court>
<date><center>February 13, 2009.</center>

</date>
<opinion_text><center>                                  <bold>ORDER</bold></center>
The Disciplinary Review Board having filed with the Court its decision in DRB 08-254, concluding on the record certified to the Board pursuant to <italic>Rule</italic> 1:20-4(f) (default by respondent), that <bold>ARNOLD M. ABRAMOWITZ of IRVINGTON</bold>, who was admitted to the bar of this State in 1976, should be suspended from the practice of law for a period of three months for violating <italic>RPC</italic> 1.1(a) (gross neglect), <italic>RPC</italic>
8.4(c) (conduct involving dishonesty, fraud, deceit or misrepresentation), and good cause appearing;

It is ORDERED that <bold>ARNOLD M. ABRAMOWITZ</bold> is suspended from the practice of law for a period of three months and until the further Order of the Court, effective March 13, 2009; and it is further

ORDERED that respondent comply with <italic>Rule</italic> 1:20-20 dealing with suspended attorneys; and it is further

ORDERED that pursuant to <italic>Rule</italic> 1:20-20(c), respondent's failure to comply with the Affidavit of Compliance requirement of<page_number>Page 505</page_number><italic>Rule</italic> 1:20-20(b)(15) may (1) preclude the Disciplinary Review Board from considering respondent's petition for reinstatement for a period of up to six months from the date respondent files proof of compliance; (2) be found to constitute a violation of <italic>RPC</italic> 8.1(b) and<italic>RPC</italic> 8.4(c); and (3) provide a basis for an action for contempt pursuant to <italic>Rule</italic> 1:10-2; and it is further

ORDERED that the entire record of this matter be made a permanent part of respondent's file as an attorney at law of this State; and it is further

ORDERED that respondent reimburse the Disciplinary Oversight Committee for appropriate administrative costs and actual expenses incurred in the prosecution of this matter, as provided in <italic>Rule</italic> 1:20-17.

</opinion_text>
</opinion>