<opinion>
<reporter_caption><center>MILK CONTROL COM. v. LYKENS DAIRY, INC., <citation>181 Pa. Super. 142</citation> (1956)</center></reporter_caption>
<citation_line><center><citation>124 A.2d 441</citation></center></citation_line>
<caption><center>Milk Control Commission <italic>v.</italic> Lykens Dairy, Inc., Appellant.</center></caption><court><center>Superior Court of Pennsylvania.</center></court><hearing_date><center>April 9, 1956.</center></hearing_date>
<date><center>July 17, 1956.</center>

</date>
<syllabus>  <italic>Milk control — Dealers — Weighing or measuring permits —</italic><italic>Separate permit for each farm having bulk milk holding tank —</italic><italic>Revocation of license — Police power — Milk Control Law</italic>.

On appeal from an order of the court below affirming an order of the Milk Control Commission which revoked appellant's milk dealer's license for the current license year and also revoked its right to apply for a milk dealer's license for the next year, in which it appeared that appellant had refused to pay the specified fee to cover a weighing and measuring permit for each and every farm equipped with a bulk milk holding tank from which appellant received milk into its tank delivery truck at the farm; and that the court below held that (1) under § 601 of the Milk Control Law of April 28, 1937, P. L. 417, as amended, a permit was required of appellant for each farm equipped with a bulk milk holding tank from which appellant received milk into its tank delivery truck at the farm, (2) § 601 and related sections of the Milk Control Law constituted a reasonable exercise of the police power, and that (3) the action of the commission was in accord with the law; it was <italic>Held</italic> that the order of the court below should be affirmed.

</syllabus>
<opinion_text>  Argued April 9, 1956.

</opinion_text><panel>  Before RHODES, P.J., HIRT, GUNTHER, WRIGHT, WOODSIDE, ERVIN, and CARR, JJ.

</panel>
<posture>  Appeal, No. 3, March T., 1956, from order of Court of Common Pleas of Dauphin County, Commonwealth Docket, 1954, No. 107, in case of Milk Control Commission of the Commonwealth of Pennsylvania v. Lykens Dairy, Inc. Order affirmed.

Appeal by milk dealer to court of common pleas from decision of Milk Control Commission revoking its<page_number>Page 143</page_number>
dealer's license for current year and revoking right to apply for license next year.

The facts are stated in the opinion, by SOHN, J., of the court below, as follows:

The appellant in this case, Lykens Dairy, Inc., Lykens, Pa., appeals from the order of the Milk Control Commission of the Commonwealth of Pennsylvania, dated April 6, 1954, which revoked its milk dealer's license for the license year, covered from May 1, 1953 to April 30, 1954, and which also revoked its right to apply for a milk dealer's license for the year beginning May 1, 1954 to April 30, 1955.

The Pennsylvania Milk Control Commission required and demanded that the appellant pay a fee of five dollars to cover a weighing or measuring permit for each and every farm equipped with a bulk milk holding tank from which the appellant received milk into its tank delivery truck at the farm. The refusal of the appellant to pay such fee was deemed by the Commission to be in violation of Article VI, Section 601 of the Milk Control Law, approved April 28, 1937, and its amendments (<cross_reference>31 P.S. 700j-601</cross_reference>), which provides in its first paragraph as follows: "It shall be <italic>unlawful</italic> for any milk dealer to <italic>buy or receive</italic>
milk from <italic>producers</italic> at any plant, station, creamery, factory <italic>or</italic><italic>other place</italic> within the Commonwealth where such milk is <italic>weighed</italic>
or <italic>measured,</italic> or to sell or deliver milk to stores or consumers, unless the milk dealer holds a <italic>permit</italic> for <italic>each place of</italic><italic>weighing or measuring</italic> such milk, issued by the commission as herein provided." (Emphasis supplied.) This section of the act was implemented by the Milk Control Commission by its Bulletin 443, issued August 20, 1953, which provides: "2. Each place where a Farm Bulk Milk Tank is located shall hold a Weighing or Measuring Permit as required by Section 601 of<page_number>Page 144</page_number>
the Pennsylvania Milk Control Law approved April 28, 1937, and its amendments." The citation which resulted in the order of April 6, 1954, alleged that the appellant failed to apply for and receive a milk dealer's weighing and/or measuring permit for the calendar year 1954, and for such places within the Commonwealth where milk is received from producers. It also charged the appellant with failure to hold a permit for each place of weighing and measuring milk received from producers.

The appellant, inter alia, asks this court to declare the aforesaid order of April 6, 1954, to be "unjust, arbitrary, capricious, illegal, and not in conformity with law, without authority and an abuse of discretion and utterly in disregard of the provisions of the Milk Control Law, the Constitution of the United States and the Constitution of the Commonwealth of Pennsylvania."

We have considered here not only Section 601 of the Milk Control Law and Bulletin 443, but also Sections 602, 603 and 404(10).

Section 602 provides as follows: "It shall be unlawful for any milk dealer to buy or receive milk from producers, or to sell or deliver milk to stores or consumers, on the basis of, or with reference to, the amount of butterfat contained in such milk, unless the butterfat test thereof is conducted by a tester certified by the commission." There is an annual fee for a tester's certificate amounting to three dollars.

Section 603 provides: "It shall be unlawful for any milk dealer to buy or receive milk from producers, or to sell or deliver milk to stores or consumers on the basis of, or with reference to, the amount of butterfat contained in such milk, unless the samples taken for testing purposes shall be made by a certified tester or certified weigher and sampler, and according to the method<page_number>Page 145</page_number>
prescribed in this act." This fee for a weigher's and sampler's certificate is set at three dollars a year.

Section 404(10) provides: ". . . the commission may decline to grant a license to an applicant, or may suspend or revoke the right of a licensee for a new license period . . . after determination by the commission that the dealer or handler: . . . (10) Has violated any of the provisions of this act, or any of the rules, regulations or orders of the commission, . . ." This latter provision pertains to the general license to operate which all dealers must have and is not to be confused with the permit in question here.

The appellant's chief contention in this case is that it presents a problem in statutory construction. It says that a new fact situation exists which was not contemplated by the legislature at the time the Milk Control Law was first passed. Instead of milk being delivered at a dealer's plant, station, creamery or factory, as formerly, it now says that it collects milk in its own tank truck operated by its own tester or weigher and sampler at nineteen different farms where the producers each own a bulk milk holding tank. It avers that it is not obliged to have and exhibit at each farm a weighing or measuring permit.

With regard to the statutory construction argument, our attention has been directed by the appellant to the Statutory Construction Act of May 28, 1937, P. L. 1019, Article IV, Section 51 (46 P.S. 551), which provides as follows: "When the words of a law <italic>are not explicit,</italic> the intention of the Legislature may be ascertained by considering, among other matters — (1) the occasion and necessity for the law; (2) the circumstances under which it was enacted; (3) the mischief to be remedied; (4) the object to be attained; (5) the former law, if any, including other laws upon the same or similar subjects; (6) the consequences of a particular<page_number>Page 146</page_number>
interpretation; (7) the contemporaneous legislative history; and (8) legislative and administrative interpretations of such law." (Emphasis supplied.)

In view of the opening phrase "When the words of a law <italic>are</italic><italic>not explicit,"</italic> we need not fall back upon this Statutory Construction Act to enable us to understand just what the legislature originally had in mind when it passed the Milk Control Law. The wording of Section 601 thereof is most definite, positive and explicit. It provides that it shall be unlawful for any milk dealer to either buy or receive milk from a producer "at any plant, station, creamery, factory <italic>or other</italic><italic>place</italic> where such milk is <italic>weighed or measured,</italic> . . . unless the milk dealer holds a permit <italic>for each place of weighing or</italic><italic>measuring</italic>. . . ." This language clearly indicates that the legislature had in mind the fact that conditions in the industry with regard to the collection and weighing and measuring of milk might change from time to time when it included the words "or other place" and for "each place of weighing or measuring," and that, wherever the place might be, a separate permit would have to be obtained therefor. It was a provision to protect not only the producer but the dealer as well, and to prevent disputes between them. However, changing or changed conditions would not authorize us in effect to hold Section 601 of no effect. Appellant's own citation in its brief from 50 Am. Jur., Statutes, section 237 disputes its contention. There it is stated: "A new meaning may not be given the words of an old statute in consequence of changed conditions. The fact that events probably not foreseen by the legislature have occurred, does not permit the court to undertake to enact new law."

The appellant also argues that now because the place of measurement is the farmer's milkhouse, the dealer has no authority to enter it except upon the invitation<page_number>Page 147</page_number>
of the farmer himself, and that he must first secure permission of the farmer to exhibit the permit. It is hardly likely that the producer of any commodity, with a ready market in view, would so unreasonably hedge in with restrictions the attempts of his purchaser to buy and take away his product, that it would result in the destruction of the very market itself.

Again the appellant makes much of the fact that the bulk milk tank, the measuring stick and the calibration chart are owned by the farmer and under his exclusive control. They may be owned by the farmer, but they are not under his exclusive control. Each farm tank is permanently affixed in concrete at each location and is equipped with a measuring rod graduated to 1/32nd of an inch, by which the quantity of milk in the tank can be ascertained by applying the reading on the measuring rod to a calibration chart. The calibration chart is made up in the first instance by the seller of the farm bulk milk tank, and is thereafter approved by the Department of Internal Affairs, in accordance with the laws of the Commonwealth of Pennsylvania. Any recalibration which may be required thereafter as a result of settlement of the ground under the concrete base, or otherwise, must also be performed by that department. A certified weigher or tester, licensed by the Milk Control Commission, weighs and measures and tests the milk before it is pumped from the farm tank into the dealer's tank truck, and about all that can be said with respect to the farmer is that he buys and owns his equipment, but its control is under the supervision of the Department of Internal Affairs and the Milk Control Commission, acting through its weighers and samplers and testers, all of whom have to be licensed by the Milk Control Commission and all of whom are required to pay to it an annual license fee of three dollars.<page_number>Page 148</page_number>

The tanks of the farmers are subject to regular inspections by the Milk Control Commission. This appears in the testimony of Glenn R. Spangler, Director of the Bureau of Enforcement and Acting Secretary of the Milk Control Commission. He testified, inter alia, that he sends out inspectors to see whether the farmers' tanks are in proper working condition, and that the expense involved for each inspection at each farm is approximately six dollars for one inspection. These are made at intervals on an average of twice a year, He said: "The basis of the payment to producers is entirely on the measurement and the butterfat content of the milk supplied to him and if the tank is not in proper level or if the weigher and sampler does not agitate the milk properly or take sample properly the producer will not receive the proper test. It may be high or low. The producer may be injured financially or the dealer may be injured financially depending on the way the sample is taken, the way the milk is agitated in the tank and conditions surrounding its maintenance. Under my supervision agents of the Commission inspect milk plants where milk is received from producers at various intervals throughout the year and this is done to insure the producer that he gets the proper test, the proper weight and that the dealer pays for the proper amount of milk at the proper butterfat content." In the light of the expert testimony of this experienced witness, there can be no doubt that, wherever the milk is delivered, the provisions for licensing each place, irrespective of who owns or controls the equipment, are for the benefit of both producer and dealer. It is not for the benefit of the producer alone. Mr. Spangler made this doubly clear when he was asked the question: "Q. So the inspection system became necessary in order to protect the interests of the producer?" And he answered: "A. And the dealer."<page_number>Page 149</page_number>

In interpreting the provisions of the act in question here we must assume that the Department of Internal Affairs and the Pennsylvania Milk Control Commission will both perform their full legal duties with respect to the farmer's milk tank and the equipment supplied with it. Each must complement the other. The appellant argues that the five dollars required for a permit for each place where a tank is located could not be used for the purpose for which it is collected and that it could not be used for policing the equipment. The appellant cites <italic>Flynn</italic><italic>et al. v. Horst,</italic> <cross_reference>356 Pa. 20</cross_reference> where the license fee was stricken down because the amount collected was substantially more than the amount necessary to police the sale of oleomargarine. The end-result of that case cannot properly be cited here where the testimony shows that each inspection costs six dollars and that on the average there are two a year at each tank. Five dollars does not adequately compensate for inspections costing twelve dollars annually. However, in <italic>Flynn v. Horst,</italic> supra, it was pointed out by President Judge HARGEST of this court that: "`A fee for the license . . . must be such a fee only as will legitimately assist in the regulation; and it should not exceed the necessary or probable expense of issuing the license and of inspecting and regulating the business which it covers.'" And again (page 25): "`The license fees exacted by the Act in question must be sustained, if at all, under a proper exercise of the police power. . . . But while it is for the legislature to determine in the first instance what laws and regulations are needed to carry out these ends, the courts may determine whether the regulations have some reasonable relation to those ends. Powell v. Commonwealth, <cross_reference>114 Pa. 265</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>7 A. 913</cross_reference>.'" The testimony in the case at bar clearly demonstrates that the sections of the Milk Control Law and the regulations followed have a clear and<page_number>Page 150</page_number>
reasonable relation to a proper exercise of the police power and to the purpose for which the Milk Control Law was passed. Nor can we agree that <italic>Fox Film Corporation's Application,</italic><cross_reference>295 Pa. 461</cross_reference> in anywise supports appellant's contentions. To the contrary, it points out that the Act of 1915 establishing the Board of Censors for moving picture films applies to talking films as well and says (page 470): "The act is expressed in general language, is prospective in its application and purpose, and, containing no express restrictions, applies to all cases that come within its terms and its general aim."

One other matter which must be considered is the appellant's claim that the Milk Control Law does not give the Milk Control Commission the authority or power to inspect or police the weighing and measuring equipment. The duty of the inspector is not only to see that the dealer does not cheat or deceive the farmer in reading the measuring stick and chart. The Commission has many other responsibilities.

Section 602 covers the responsibility of the "Certified Testers." To determine that these testers do their work properly and conscientiously is the duty of the inspector.

Section 604 covers "Refusal, Suspension and Revocation of Permits and Certificates." The farmer can scarcely be deemed to have sufficient scientific knowledge to testify concerning the conduct of the dealer's employee to disqualify the latter.

Section 606 deals with "Samples; Check Tests." In the fourth paragraph of the preamble of the Milk Control Law is contained the following: "This knowledge of weights, tests and uses is in the exclusive possession of the dealer. . . . Hence, milk producers are subject to fraud and imposition, and do not possess the freedom of contract necessary for the procuring of cost of production."<page_number>Page 151</page_number>
Section 606 provides also: "The commission may require that the composite samples be <italic>tested on the premises</italic> where they are taken." (Emphasis supplied.) The supervision of this section requires that the Commission's inspector call at the farmer's milk house where the composite sample is taken. This section also provides: "Any person taking a sample or samples of milk, either from the aliquot part of each lot of milk sampled or from the composite lot of milk sampled, shall thoroughly stir or mix the contents of each and every container immediately before such sample or samples are taken, in such manner that the milk is thoroughly mixed in each container before the sample is taken." Some farmers may know this and some may not, or their duties may require their presence elsewhere when the dealer's agent comes for the milk. Inspection from time to time, and without notice, is necessary to supervise the dealer's agent.

Sections 606 and 607 have to do with the "Babcock Test." The law requires payment to producers based on the butterfat content of the milk. It can only be determined by persons who are sufficiently acquainted with and learned in the operation of this test. The sample taken from the producer's tank <italic>at his</italic><italic>farm</italic> is the first step in determining the amount of money he shall receive for the milk which the dealers purchase. Only an inspector having sufficient scientific knowledge can check on this test.

Section 607 deals with "Violations." The preamble of the Milk Control Law clearly shows that the legislature had knowledge that some dealers were unscrupuluos. Without inspectors and inspections the Milk Control Commission would be helpless in policing the industry.

Section 608 covers "Payment for Milk; Statement." The best way for the Commission to determine if the<page_number>Page 152</page_number>
dealer has paid the farmer is for the inspector to ask the farmer. The best way to determine if the dealer has issued the farmer a proper statement is for the inspector to read the statement the farmer receives. Merely examining the dealer's books is not sufficient. They might be in error or they might not be truthful. A check <italic>at the farm itself</italic> is necessary on the part of the inspector.

Although it does not seem to be raised in appellant's briefs, quite a point was made by the appellant during the hearing as to when and where title to the milk passed, and as to who owned the equipment. This we find has no place in the determination of the issues raised under the Milk Control Law. Section 601 requires a permit for "any plant, station, creamery, factory <italic>or</italic><italic>other place . . . where such milk is weighed or measured."</italic> It is the <italic>place</italic> of weighing or measuring that is contemplated, not who owns the equipment or where title to the milk passes.

We find that the act of the Pennsylvania Milk Control Commission here is fully in accordance with the law as we have heretofore pointed out, that the law is clear, explicit, positive and reasonable, that it is a reasonable exercise of the police power and the powers granted by the Milk Control Law, and further the prospective ends and aims of the legislature when it adopted the Milk Control Law. Accordingly, we make the following order.

And now, November 29, 1954, the Findings of Fact, Conclusions of Law and Order of the Pennsylvania Milk Control Commission, dated April 6, 1954, are hereby affirmed, the appeal of Lykens Dairy, Inc. is hereby dismissed, and it is ordered that the cost of this proceeding be paid by the appellant.

Milk dealer appealed.<page_number>Page 153</page_number>

</posture><attorneys>  <italic>Willis F. Daniels,</italic> with him <italic>Harold W. Swope, Donn L. Snyder</italic>
and <italic>Daniels  Swope,</italic> for appellant.

<italic>Stephen B. Narin,</italic> Deputy Attorney General, with him <italic>Herbert</italic><italic>B. Cohen,</italic> Attorney General, for appellee.

</attorneys>
<opinion_byline>  OPINION PER CURIAM, July 17, 1956:

</opinion_byline>
<opinion_text>  Order affirmed on the opinion of Judge WALTER R. SOHN, at cost of appellant.

</opinion_text>
</opinion>