<opinion>
<reporter_caption><center>COM. ex rel. THOMPSON v. HENDRICK, <citation>202 Pa. Super. 29</citation> (1963)</center></reporter_caption>
<citation_line><center><citation>195 A.2d 811</citation></center></citation_line>
<caption><center>Commonwealth ex rel. Thompson, Appellant v. Hendrick.</center></caption><court><center>Superior Court of Pennsylvania.</center></court><hearing_date><center>September 10, 1963.</center></hearing_date>
<date><center>November 13, 1963.</center>

</date>
<syllabus>  <italic>Criminal Law — Practice — Habeas corpus — Alleged illegal</italic><italic>confinement for assault and battery — Commitment on other</italic><italic>charges — Evidence</italic>.

In a habeas corpus proceeding, in which it appeared that petitioner, who had been committed to the county prison on a charge of assault and battery, alleged that he had been attacked by certain persons, but that he, himself, had been held by the magistrate on a charge of assault and battery, that petitioner also included a motion to nol. pros., and that petitioner further complained of injuries imposed upon him at the hands of the police, the magistrate, and a bondsman; that petitioner failed to state that he was being held not only on the one charge of assault and battery, but also on two other separate and distinct charges, for one of which bail had been entered and withdrawn; and that the court below, holding, in the circumstances, that even if the petition were pertinent, petitioner's confinement was not illegal, and that the main thrust of defendant's petition was to avoid trial, dismissed the petition; it was <italic>Held</italic> that the order of the court below should be affirmed.

</syllabus>
<opinion_text>  Submitted September 10, 1963.

</opinion_text><panel>  Before RHODES, P.J., ERVIN, WRIGHT, WOODSIDE, WATKINS, MONTGOMERY, and FLOOD, JJ.

</panel>
<posture>  Appeal, No. 210, Oct. T., 1963, from order of Court of Common Pleas No. 1 of Philadelphia County, March T., 1963, No. 3085, in case of Commonwealth ex rel. Alphonso Thompson v. Edward J. Hendrick, Superintendent. Order affirmed.

Same case in court below: 31 Pa. D.  C. 2d 496.

Habeas corpus.

Order entered dismissing petition, opinion by CARROLL, P.J. Petitioner appealed.

</posture><attorneys>  <italic>Alphonso Thompson,</italic> appellant, in propria persona.<page_number>Page 30</page_number>
 <italic>Arthur J. Marion</italic> and <italic>Arlen Specter,</italic> Assistant District Attorneys, <italic>F. Emmett Fitzpatrick, Jr.,</italic> First Assistant District Attorney, and <italic>James C. Crumlish, Jr.,</italic> District Attorney, for appellee.

</attorneys>
<opinion_byline>  OPINION PER CURIAM, November 13, 1963:

</opinion_byline>
<opinion_text>  The order of the court below dismissing petition for writ of habeas corpus is affirmed on the opinion of President Judge CARROLL of the Court of Common Pleas No. 2 of Philadelphia County, as reported in 31 Pa. D.  C. 2d 496.

</opinion_text>
</opinion>