<opinion>
<reporter_caption><center>FOURNIER v. ECONOMY SPRING, <citation>1141 CRD-6-90-11</citation> (10-31-91)</center></reporter_caption>
<caption><center>CAROL FOURNIER, CLAIMANT-APPELLANT v. ECONOMY SPRING, EMPLOYER and EBI</center><center>GENERAL AGENCY, INC. INSURER, RESPONDENTS-APPELLEES</center></caption>
<docket><center>CASE NO. 1141 CRD-6-90-11</center></docket><court><center>Workers' Compensation Commission</center></court>
<date><center>OCTOBER 31, 1991</center>

</date><attorneys>    The claimant was represented by Edward P. Dutkiewicz, Esq. and Theodore J. Wurz, Esq. of Morrocco and Wurz.

The respondents were represented by Richard S. Bartlett, Esq., McGann, Bartlett  Brown.

</attorneys>
<posture>    This Petition for Review from the November 14, 1990 Finding and Dismissal of the Commissioner for the Sixth District was heard August 16, 1991 before a Compensation Review Division panel consisting of the Commission Chairman, John Arcudi, and Commissioners Robin Waller and James Metro.

</posture>
<opinion_text>OPINION

</opinion_text>
<opinion_byline>    JOHN ARCUDI, CHAIRMAN.

</opinion_byline>
<opinion_text>    Claimant's appeal from the Sixth District November 14, 1990 Finding and Dismissal was filed November 29, 1990. Respondents filed a Motion to Dismiss December 6, 1990 as the appeal was filed more than ten days after the entry of the award.

An appeal must satisfy statutory requirements. Claimant failed to file her appeal within the statutorily mandated time requirements of Sec. <cross_reference>31-301</cross_reference> and Administrative Regulations Sec.<cross_reference>31-301-1</cross_reference>.

Therefore, respondents' Motion to Dismiss is granted and claimant's appeal is dismissed. Tarver v. Meriden Yellow Cab Co., <cross_reference>877 CRD-8-89-6</cross_reference> (9/27/90); Famiglietti v. Dossert Corp.,<cross_reference>8 Conn. Workers' Comp. Rev. Op. 65</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>804 CRD-5-88-12</cross_reference> (1990).

Commissioners Robin Waller and James Metro concur.

</opinion_text>
</opinion>