<opinion>
<reporter_caption><center>TYNER v. ZANT, <citation>255 Ga. 405</citation> (1986)</center></reporter_caption>
<citation_line><center><citation>339 S.E.2d 235</citation></center></citation_line>
<caption><center>TYNER v. ZANT et al.</center></caption>
<docket><center>42865.</center></docket><court><center>Supreme Court of Georgia.</center></court>
<date><center>DECIDED FEBRUARY 12, 1986.</center>

</date>
<opinion_byline>   MARSHALL, Presiding Justice.

</opinion_byline>
<opinion_text>   The appellant, an inmate of the Georgia State Prison, filed in Fulton Superior Court a petition for mandamus to obtain the removal of a disciplinary sanction imposed on him following a disciplinary hearing pursuant to Rule <cross_reference>125-3-2-.06</cross_reference> of the Official Rules of the Georgia Department of Corrections, and the expunction of this sanction from his prison record. He appeals from the denial of the writ of mandamus. We affirm.

"The right to the extraordinary writ of mandamus exists only upon meeting a two[-]prong test: (1) the applicant must demonstrate a clear legal right to the relief sought, and (2) there must be no other adequate remedy. [Cits.]" <italic>Carnes v.</italic><italic>Crawford</italic>, <cross_reference>246 Ga. 677</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>678</cross_reference> (<cross_reference>272 S.E.2d 690</cross_reference>) (1980). Under the Official Rules of the Georgia Department of Corrections, the appellant had a right of appeal from the imposition of the sanction. See Rule <cross_reference>125-3-2-.06</cross_reference> (5). The appellant having failed to exhaust his administrative remedies (see <italic>Heard v. Hopper</italic>,<cross_reference>233 Ga. 617</cross_reference> (1) (<cross_reference>212 S.E.2d 797</cross_reference>) (1975); <italic>Carnes v. Crawford</italic>, supra), the trial court properly denied the petition for mandamus.

<italic>Judgment affirmed. All the Justices concur.</italic>

</opinion_text>
<opinion_text><center>                       DECIDED FEBRUARY 12, 1986.</center></opinion_text>
<posture>   Mandamus. Fulton Superior Court. Before Judge Alverson.

</posture><attorneys>   Paul Jerome Tyner, <italic>pro se.</italic>
 <italic>Michael J. Bowers, Attorney General, Michael E. Hobbs, Senior</italic><italic>Assistant Attorney General</italic>, for appellees.

</attorneys>
</opinion>