<opinion>
<reporter_caption><center>MOTION DOCKET, <citation>88 Ohio St.3d 1425</citation> (2000)</center></reporter_caption>
<citation_line><center><citation>723 N.E.2d 1113</citation></center></citation_line><court><center>Supreme Court of Ohio.</center></court>
<date><center>2000.</center>

</date><center>                              <bold><underline>MOTION DOCKET</underline></bold><bold>98-1124. Clement v. Grange Mut. Cas. Co.</bold></center>
Medina App. No. 2698-M. <italic>Sua sponte</italic>, stay of briefing schedule dissolved in this cause and in consolidated case No. 98-1185,<italic>Simcox v. Westfield Cos.</italic>

<bold>98-1185. Simcox v. Westfield Cos.</bold>

Medina App. No. 2697-M. <italic>Sua sponte</italic>, stay of briefing schedule dissolved in this cause and in consolidated case No. 98-1124,<italic>Clement v. Grange Mut. Cas. Co.</italic>

<bold>98-1912. State ex rel. Chrysler Corp. v. Indus. Comm.</bold>

Franklin App. No. 97APD02-270. On request for oral argument. Request denied.

<bold>99-796. Black v. Allstate Ins. Co.</bold>

Scioto App. No. 98CA2597. <italic>Sua sponte</italic>, cause held for the decisions in 98-1124, <italic>Clement v. Grange Mut. Cas. Co.</italic>, Medina App. No. 2698-M; and 98-1185, <italic>Simcox v. Westfield Cos.</italic>, Medina App. No. 2697-M; briefing schedule stayed.

<bold>99-1287. Progressive Ins. Co. v. Stewart.</bold>

Lucas App. No. L-98-1250. <italic>Sua sponte</italic>, cause held for the decisions in 98-1124, <italic>Clement v. Grange Mut. Cas. Co.</italic>, Medina App. No. 2698-M; and 98-1185, <italic>Simcox v. Westfield Cos.</italic>, Medina App. No. 2697-M; briefing schedule stayed.

<bold>99-1552. State ex rel. Ohio Patrolmen's Benevolent Assn. v.</bold><bold>Mentor.</bold>

In Mandamus. This cause is  before the court for its consideration under S.Ct.Prac.R. X(5). Upon consideration,

IT IS ORDERED that relators' claims regarding payroll, overtime, and having investigative records be DISMISSED as moot.

IT IS FURTHER ORDERED that regarding relators' remaining claims concerning the Spetrino investigative records and their entitlement to attorney fees, an alternative writ is GRANTED, the parties shall file evidence regarding these claims within twenty days of this entry, relators shall file a merit brief within twenty days after the submission of evidence, respondents shall file their merit brief within twenty days after relators' merit brief is filed, and relators may file a reply brief within five days after respondents' merit brief is filed.<page_number>Page 1426</page_number>


</opinion>