<opinion unpublished=true>
<reporter_caption><center>MARTINEZ v. HARTFORD POLICE DEPT., No. HHD-CV-07-5011769 (Dec. 1, 2008)</center></reporter_caption>
<caption><center>ALBA MARTINEZ v. CITY OF HARTFORD POLICE DEPARTMENT.</center></caption>
<citation_line><center><citation>2008 Ct. Sup. 18803</citation></center></citation_line>
<docket><center>No. HHD-CV-07-5011769</center></docket><court><center>Connecticut Superior Court</center><center>Judicial District of Hartford at Hartford</center></court>
<date><center>December 1, 2008</center>

</date>
<opinion_text><unpublished><footnote_body>[EDITOR'S NOTE: This case is unpublished as indicated by the issuing court.]</footnote_body><center>                           MEMORANDUM OF DECISION</center></unpublished></opinion_text>
<opinion_byline><unpublished>  BENTIVEGNA, J.

</unpublished></opinion_byline>
<opinion_text><unpublished><center>                                     <italic>I</italic></center><center>                             <italic>STATEMENT OF CASE</italic></center>
This is a negligence action brought by the plaintiff, Alba Martinez, against the defendant, city of Hartford police department, seeking damages for injuries resulting from an automobile accident.

In the amended complaint, dated September 7, 2007, the plaintiff alleges that the defendant's employee, former Hartford Police Officer Roberto Sanchez, collided into the plaintiff's motor vehicle while operating his police cruiser. As a result of Sanchez's negligence, the plaintiff suffered injuries to her neck and back.

In the answer and special defenses to amended complaint, dated September 21, 2007, the defendant alleges the following special defenses; (1) The defendant is entitled to common-law and statutory governmental immunity pursuant to General Statutes § <cross_reference>52-557n</cross_reference>; (2) Any injuries claimed by the plaintiff were the result of her own negligence; and (3) Pursuant to General Statutes § <cross_reference>14-283</cross_reference>, the defendant's employee was operating an emergency vehicle and was not negligent.

The case was tried to the court on September 10, 2008. The last posttrial brief was filed on November 13, 2008.

<center>                                     <italic>II</italic></center><center>                              <italic>FINDINGS OF FACT</italic></center>
The court finds the following facts were proved by a fair preponderance of the evidence.

The plaintiff is thirty-eight years old. She moved from Colombia to CT Page 18804 Connecticut nine years ago and has been driving for seven years. The plaintiff lives with her five-year-old son, her sister and her niece. She works in Hartford.

The plaintiff testified that on May 9, 2006, at approximately 7:15 p.m., she was driving her 1994 Chevy Corsica northbound on Zion Street in Hartford. Her son was in a car seat in the back seat of the car. As the plaintiff approached the intersection of Flatbush Avenue and Zion Street, she planned to make a left turn onto Flatbush Avenue. She had a green light but was waiting for the oncoming traffic to pass. Her left blinker was on. No police vehicle passed through the intersection before the accident. She did not hear a police siren. She was focused on making a left turn and did not see any police lights behind her. She knew that she had to go to the right if there was an emergency vehicle that was trying to pass. When she started making the left turn, her vehicle collided with Sanchez's police cruiser.

After the accident, the plaintiff felt shocked and scared. She was worried about her son in the back seat. Her neck and back hurt after the collision. She spoke to several police officers, but none of them spoke Spanish. An ambulance was not requested. The plaintiff drove her vehicle home from the scene of the accident.

Sanchez testified that on May 9, 2006, he was employed as a Hartford police officer. He was on duty and was driving his police cruiser northbound on Zion Street. He was familiar with the right-of-way requirements of § <cross_reference>14-283</cross_reference>.

He was responding to a call when the collision occurred but could not recall the reason for the call. His lights and siren were on. There was one police cruiser a half a block in front of him and another police cruiser behind him. Sanchez did not know who was in the first police cruiser. The first police vehicle preceded Sanchez through the intersection of Zion Street and Flatbush Avenue. Sanchez could not recall if the first cruiser's lights and siren were activated. He did not see the plaintiff's car in the middle of the intersection of Zion Street and Flatbush Avenue before the collision. It was safer for him to cross the double yellow line into the oncoming traffic and pass on the left. He could not recall whether the traffic light at the intersection was red or green.

William Ortiz, the operator of the police cruiser behind Sanchez, testified at trial. At the time of the accident, he was employed as a Hartford police officer. Ortiz was operating his police vehicle northbound on Zion Street approximately two car lengths behind Sanchez's CT Page 18805 vehicle. He was also responding to the same call, but he did not remember if there was another police vehicle ahead of Sanchez. Ortiz was familiar with the requirements of § <cross_reference>14-283</cross_reference>. Police officers are trained that it is safer to pass on the left. Sanchez's siren and lights were activated. Sanchez slowed down before entering the intersection. Ortiz saw the plaintiff's vehicle stopped at the intersection. He was unable to recall whether the traffic light was red or green. Ortiz saw the two vehicles collide in the intersection.

The police report for the accident was written by Hartford Police Officer Robert Lanza. The plaintiff reportedly told Lanza that she was traveling north on Zion Street in the proper lane when she came to a stop at Flatbush Avenue. She stopped because there was southbound traffic on Zion Street. The plaintiff told Lanza that she observed, in her rearview mirror, emergency lights in the distance, but she did not hear sirens. When she made a left turn to go westbound on Flatbush Avenue, she was struck by Sanchez's vehicle.

Sanchez reportedly told Lanza that he was traveling northbound on Zion Street going to a call with his lights and sirens on. Sanchez said that he was directly behind another police cruiser that was also going to the same call with lights and sirens on. As Sanchez approached the intersection, he slowed down and observed the plaintiff's vehicle stopped at the intersection. Sanchez told Lanza that he approached the intersection with caution. Sanchez went to pass the plaintiff's vehicle on the left at the same time the plaintiff made a left-hand turn. The two vehicles collided. Lanza reported that the plaintiff and Sanchez had no physical injuries and refused medical attention.

On May 23, 2006, the plaintiff saw Dr. Anthony Infantino for injuries stemming from the accident. At a follow-up evaluation a week later, she complained about neck pain, headaches, and pain in her lower and middle back. Before the accident, she had not experienced any neck pain. The plaintiff underwent a course of physical therapy at the Infantino's recommendation. At her final examination with Infantino on October 31, 2006, the plaintiff was given a rating of five percent impairment to the cervical spine and five percent impairment to the lumbar spine. Medical bills remain unpaid in the amount of $3,340.

The plaintiff still complains of frequent pain and stiffness that interfere with her daily activities. She has difficulties with activities involving her neck and back, especially when she has to bend over. Problems also arise when she does housework, drives for extended period of time and plays with her son. The plaintiff has a life expectancy of 42.86 years. CT Page 18806

Before this accident, the plaintiff had suffered injuries relevant to this case. In August 2004, the plaintiff fell at work and injured her neck and her right shoulder, hand and hip. She received medical treatment and was found to have a five percent impairment to the lumbar spine and a six percent impairment to the right shoulder. In December 2005, the plaintiff fell at a store and injured her left hip. She received medical treatment and was found to have a five percent impairment to the left hip.

Additional facts will be provided, as needed, that are proved by a fair preponderance of the evidence.

<center>                                    <italic>III</italic></center><center>                                 <italic>DISCUSSION</italic></center>
At the end of the plaintiff's case, the defendant moved to dismiss the case under Practice Book § <cross_reference>15-8</cross_reference> on the grounds that: (1) "the plaintiff sued the [c]ity of Hartford in negligence only, but did not cite any statute that abrogates a municipality's immunity from negligence:" and (2) "the plaintiff sued the [c]ity of Hartford only and did not sue Officer Sanchez." (Defendant's Trial Brief, September 22, 2008.)

Practice Book § <cross_reference>15-8</cross_reference> provides in relevant part: "If, on the trial of any issue of fact in a civil action tried to the court, the plaintiff has produced evidence and rested his or her cause, the defendant may move for judgment of dismissal, and the judicial authority may grant such motion, if in its opinion the plaintiff has failed to make out a prima facie case."

This evidentiary nonsuit rule under Practice Book § <cross_reference>15-8</cross_reference> was overhauled when the directed verdict rule (P.B. § 16-37) was revised in 1978, and supplants the evidentiary nonsuit under General Statutes § <cross_reference>52-210</cross_reference> and the prior rule. See <italic>Reynolds v. Molitor</italic>, <cross_reference>184 Conn. 526</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>527-28</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>440 A.2d 192</cross_reference>
(1981). "When such a motion has been granted, the question is whether sufficient facts were proved to make out a prima facie case . . . To state it another way, a judgment of dismissal is proper when the evidence produced by the plaintiff, if fully believed, would not permit the trier in reason to find the essential issues on the complaint in favor of the plaintiff . . . The evidence offered by the plaintiff is to be taken as true and interpreted in the light most favorable to him, and every reasonable inference is to be drawn in his favor . . . A party has the same right to submit a weak case as he has to submit a strong one." (Citations omitted; internal quotation marks omitted. <italic>Angelo Tomasso,</italic><italic>CT Page 18807</italic><italic>Inc. v. Armor Construction  Paving, Inc.</italic>, <cross_reference>187 Conn. 544</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>547-48</cross_reference>,<cross_reference>447 A.2d 406</cross_reference> (1982).

In ruling on an evidentiary nonsuit motion, "the duty of the trial court [is] to take as true the evidence offered by the plaintiff and to interpret it in the light most favorable to him, with every reasonable inference being drawn in his favor . . . Clearly, therefore, the fact that a trial court denies a motion to dismiss does not mean that the plaintiff is `entitled' to a judgment in its favor if the defendant does not put on any evidence. Rather, the determination that a plaintiff has established a prima facie case in this instance is comparable to . . . the effect of denying a motion to dismiss is to give the plaintiff the opportunity to have the factfinder pass upon the merits of the case . . .

"Once a case is ultimately presented to the factfinder for final decision, an entirely different analysis is applied. Rather than being required to take as true the evidence offered by the plaintiff, the trier of fact can disbelieve any evidence, even if uncontradicted . . . In addition, the trier of fact is no longer bound to interpret the evidence in the light most favorable to the plaintiff, or to draw every reasonable inference therefrom, for it is axiomatic that it is within the province of the trier of facts to assess the credibility of witnesses." (Citations omitted.) <italic>Berchtold v. Maggi</italic>, <cross_reference>191 Conn. 266</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>271-72</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>464 A.2d 1</cross_reference> (1983).

Practice Book § <cross_reference>15-8</cross_reference> cannot be used to claim that the defendant should prevail on a special defense, since the plaintiff does not have to present any evidence on it in his case in chief. See <italic>Resnik v. Morganstern</italic>,<cross_reference>100 Conn. 38</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>42</cross_reference> <cross_reference>122 A. 910</cross_reference> (1923).

The city of Hartford has alleged governmental immunity as a special defense. Recently, in <italic>Vejseli v. Pasha</italic>, <cross_reference>282 Conn. 561</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>572</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>923 A.2d 688</cross_reference>
(2007), the Supreme Court reviewed the law of municipal liability. The Supreme Court stated that "unlike the state, municipalities have no sovereign immunity from suit . . . Rather, municipal governments have a limited immunity from liability." (Internal quotation marks omitted.)

"Governmental immunity, which applies to municipalities, is different in historical origin, scope and application from the sovereign immunity enjoyed by the state. A suit against a municipality is not a suit against a sovereign. Towns have no sovereign immunity, and are capable of suing and being sued . . . in any action . . . Municipalities do, in certain circumstances, have a governmental immunity from liability . . . But that is entirely different from the state's sovereign immunity from suit." (Internal quotation marks omitted.) <italic>Vejseli v. Pasha, supra</italic>, CT Page 18808<cross_reference>282 Conn. 573</cross_reference>.

"[W]hereas [t]he doctrine of sovereign immunity implicates subject matter jurisdiction and is therefore a basis for granting a motion to dismiss . . . the doctrine of governmental immunity implicates no such interest. Thus, [t]his court has previously stated that [a] municipality itself was generally immune from liability for its tortious acts at common law . . . We have also recognized, however, that governmental immunity may be abrogated by statute . . . [Section] <cross_reference>52-557n</cross_reference>(a)(1) provides in relevant part: `Except as otherwise provided by law, a political subdivision of the state shall be liable for damages to person or property caused by: (A) The negligent acts or omissions of such political subdivision or any employee, officer or agent thereof acting within the scope of his employment or official duties . . .' We previously have concluded that [t]his language clearly and expressly abrogates the traditional common-law doctrine in this state that municipalities are immune from suit for torts committed by their employees and agents." (Citation omitted; internal quotation marks omitted.) <italic>Id.</italic>, 572.

The Supreme Court noted the trial court's determination that a motion to dismiss was not the appropriate procedural vehicle to raise the defense of governmental immunity. <italic>Id.</italic>, 566 n. 6.

In this case, the plaintiff did not specifically plead General Statutes § <cross_reference>52-557n</cross_reference> in the amended complaint. "[A]lthough Practice Book § <cross_reference>10-3</cross_reference> (a) requires in relevant part that `[w]hen any claim made in a complaint . . . is grounded on a statute, the statute shall be specifically identified by its number' . . . our courts repeatedly have recognized that the rule embodied in Practice Book § <cross_reference>10-3</cross_reference> is directory and not mandatory . . . [N]otice is the critical consideration in such instances . . . [A]s long as the defendant is sufficiently apprised of the nature of the action . . . the failure to comply with the directive of Practice Book § <cross_reference>10-3</cross_reference>(a) will not bar recovery." (Citations omitted; internal quotation marks omitted.) <italic>Michalski v. Hinz</italic>, <cross_reference>100 Conn.App. 389</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>393-94</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>918 A.2d 964</cross_reference>
(2007).

It is apparent from the face of the amended complaint that the defendant, city of Hartford, through Officer Sanchez, was engaged in a governmental function while performing the acts and omissions complained of by the plaintiff. The defendant was sufficiently apprised of the nature of the action. In answering the amended complaint, the defendant alleged government immunity under § <cross_reference>52-557n</cross_reference> as a special defense. Governmental immunity "is an affirmative defense and the plaintiff is not bound to meet it in establishing [her] case. If this were not so, a CT Page 18809 plaintiff would be compelled to assume the burden of proving not only [her] own case but meeting the special defenses of the defendant."<italic>Resnik v. Morganstern</italic>, <italic>supra</italic>, <cross_reference>100 Conn. 42</cross_reference>.

Viewing the evidence in the light most favorable to the plaintiff's case, the plaintiff established a prima facie case. The evidence demonstrated that Hartford Police Officer Sanchez was on duty operating his police cruiser when he collided with the plaintiff's motor vehicle. As a result of the collision, the plaintiff suffered injuries to her neck and back. Accordingly, the motion to dismiss pursuant to Practice Book §<cross_reference>15-8</cross_reference> is denied.

In the amended complaint, the plaintiff alleges that the collision and resulting injuries and losses to the plaintiff were caused by the carelessness and negligence of the defendant, through its servants, agents and/or employees, in one or more of the following ways, in that: he was inattentive and failed to keep a reasonable and proper lookout for other vehicles using the road; he drove his motor vehicle at a greater speed than circumstances warranted; he failed to keep his vehicle under proper and reasonable control; he failed to maneuver his motor vehicle although, by a proper and reasonable exercise of his faculties, he could or should have done so; he failed to turn his motor vehicle in time to avoid colliding with plaintiff; he drove his motor vehicle with defective or inadequate brakes, or failed to apply his brakes in time to avoid the collision; he violated § <cross_reference>14-299</cross_reference>(a) in driving said motor vehicle in a reckless and dangerous manner having regard to width, traffic, and use of said roadway: he failed under the existing circumstances to take the necessary precautions to avoid the probability of harm to the plaintiff; he was driving his vehicle at an unreasonable rate of speed without having due regard to the width, traffic and use of the road and the intersection of streets in violation of § <cross_reference>14-218</cross_reference>(a). The plaintiff claims injuries to her neck and back.

"The essential elements of a cause of action in negligence are well established: duty; breach of that duty; causation; and actual injury." (Internal quotation marks omitted.) <italic>Mazurek v. Great American Ins.</italic><italic>Co.</italic>, <cross_reference>284 Conn. 16</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>29</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>930 A.2d 682</cross_reference> (2007).

In defense of the negligence claims, the defendant alleges several special defenses. The defendant alleges first that it is entitled to governmental immunity pursuant to General Statutes § <cross_reference>52-557n</cross_reference>. As previously set forth, the law of governmental immunity is clear. "The tort liability of a municipality has been codified in § <cross_reference>52-557n</cross_reference>. Section<cross_reference>52-557n</cross_reference>(a)(1) provides that `[e]xcept as otherwise provided by law, a political subdivision of the state shall be liable for damages to person CT Page 18810 or property caused by: (A) The negligent acts or omissions of such political subdivision or any employee, officer or agent thereof acting within the scope of his employment or official duties . . .' Section<cross_reference>52-557n</cross_reference>(a)(2)(B) extends, however, the same discretionary act immunity that applies to municipal officials to the municipalities themselves by providing that they will not be liable for damages caused by `negligent acts or omissions which require the exercise of judgment or discretion as an official function of the authority expressly or impliedly granted by law.'" (Internal quotation marks omitted.) <italic>Violano v. Fernandez</italic>,<cross_reference>280 Conn. 310</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>320</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>907 A.2d 1188</cross_reference> (2006).

"Generally, a municipal employee is liable for the misperformance of ministerial acts, but has a qualified immunity in the performance of governmental acts . . . Governmental acts are performed wholly for the direct benefit of the public and are supervisory or discretionary in nature . . . The hallmark of a discretionary act is that it requires the exercise of judgment . . . In contrast, [m]inisterial refers to a duty which is to be performed in a prescribed manner without the exercise of judgment or discretion." (Internal quotation marks omitted.) <italic>Id.</italic>, 318. "[O]nce the duty owed is deemed to be public, liability attaches in two situations: (1) if the act complained of is ministerial; or (2) if one of the exceptions to the doctrine of governmental immunity applies."<italic>Houlihan v. Milford</italic>, Superior Court, judicial district of Ansonia-Milford, Docket No. CV 92 038357 (January 22, 1993, Jones, J.) (8 C.S.C.R. 264) [8 Conn. L. Rptr. 738].

"[I]t is firmly established that the operation of a police department is a governmental function, and that acts or omissions in connection therewith ordinarily do not give rise to liability on the part of the municipality . . . [T]he failure to provide, or the inadequacy of, police protection usually does not give rise to a cause of action in tort against a city . . . The deployment of officers is particularly a governmental function . . . We conclude that the general deployment of police officers is a discretionary governmental action as a matter of law." (Citations omitted; internal quotation marks omitted.) <italic>Gordon v.</italic><italic>Bridgeport Housing Authority</italic>, <cross_reference>208 Conn. 161</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>180</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>544 A.2d 1185</cross_reference> (1988).

However, judges of the Superior Court have held that the duty to operate an emergency vehicle with due care in accordance with § <cross_reference>14-283</cross_reference> is a ministerial duty. The court in <italic>Allen v. Board of Fire Commissioners</italic>, Superior Court, complex litigation docket at Waterbury, Docket No. X02 CV 00 0167547 (August 2, 2002, Sheldon, J.), stated: "the operator of an emergency vehicle has no discretion under [§] <cross_reference>14-283</cross_reference> to operate his vehicle unsafely, without due regard for the rights and safety of others. To the contrary, the statute expressly provides that, `The CT Page 18811 provisions of this section shall not relieve the operator of an emergency vehicle from the duty to drive with due regard for the safety of all persons and property.' [General Statutes] § <cross_reference>14-283</cross_reference>(d). Accordingly, the duty to operate even an emergency vehicle with due care is a ministerial duty which a fireman has no discretion not to perform." Likewise, in<italic>Vilton v. Burns</italic>, Superior Court, complex litigation docket at Waterbury, Docket No. X06 CV 00 0169481 (June 22, 2004, Alander, J.) [37 Conn. L. Rptr. 425], the court held that "the duty of a police officer to operate a police cruiser with due care and so as not to endanger the safety of others is a ministerial duty outside the ambit of governmental immunity."

The defendant also alleges as a special defense that Sanchez was operating an emergency vehicle pursuant to § <cross_reference>14-283</cross_reference><footnote_reference>[fn1]</footnote_reference> and was not negligent. "General Statutes § <cross_reference>14-283</cross_reference> provides that a police officer operating a police vehicle in pursuit of fleeing law violators [or responding to an emergency call] may exceed posted speed limits and disregard other statutes, ordinances, and regulations governing the movement of vehicles. The exemptions only apply when the police vehicle is properly and lawfully making use of an audible warning signal device. General Statutes § <cross_reference>14-283</cross_reference>. The right to exceed posted speed limits or other speed limits imposed by §§ <cross_reference>14-218a</cross_reference> or <cross_reference>14-219</cross_reference> is limited by the duty to not endanger life or property by doing so. General Statutes §<cross_reference>14-283</cross_reference>(b)(3). Moreover, the statute does not relieve the police officer from the duty to drive with due regard for the safety of all persons and property. General Statutes § <cross_reference>14-283</cross_reference>(d)." <italic>Id.</italic>

Subsection (b) of § <cross_reference>14-283</cross_reference> grants immunity to operators of emergency vehicles under some circumstances. <italic>State v. Nesteriak</italic>, <cross_reference>60 Conn.App. 647</cross_reference>,<cross_reference>654</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>760 A.2d 984</cross_reference> (2000) (criminal case). Our Supreme Court has construed § <cross_reference>14-283</cross_reference>(d) in a civil context. <italic>Tetro v. Stratford</italic>,<cross_reference>189 Conn. 601</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>458 A.2d 5</cross_reference> (1983). In <italic>Tetro</italic>, the court held that police officers conducting an otherwise valid police chase were not relieved "from their general duty to exercise due care for the safety of others . . . [Section] <cross_reference>14-283</cross_reference> provides no special zone of limited liability once the defendants' negligence has been established." (Citations omitted.)<italic>Tetro v. Stratford</italic>, <italic>supra</italic>, <cross_reference>189 Conn. 609-10</cross_reference>.

The meaning of the words "safety of all persons and property" has been addressed. "Other courts, construing similar statutory language, have explained that emergency vehicle legislation provides only limited shelter from liability for negligence. The effect of the statute is merely to displace the conclusive presumption of negligence that ordinarily arises from the violation of traffic rules. The statute does not relieve operators of emergency vehicles from their general duty to exercise due care for the safety of others . . . We agree with this CT Page 18812 interpretation and conclude that § <cross_reference>14-283</cross_reference> provides no special zone of limited liability once the defendants' negligence has been established." (Citations omitted.) <italic>Id.</italic>, 609-10.

The plaintiff alleges that the collision and resulting injuries and losses to the plaintiff were caused by the carelessness and negligence of Sanchez. Sanchez clearly owed the public a duty to operate his police cruiser in accordance with § <cross_reference>14-283</cross_reference>(d).

The evidence demonstrated that Sanchez was traveling northbound on Zion Street responding to an emergency call with his lights and sirens on. He was answering an emergency call and therefore had the right of way under § <cross_reference>14-283</cross_reference>. He slowed down as he approached the intersection. The plaintiff observed emergency lights in her rearview mirror before the collision. Although the plaintiff's vehicle was in the immediate vicinity of the police cruisers, she did not immediately drive to the right as required by § <cross_reference>14-238</cross_reference>. She instead decided to continue making a left turn at the intersection. The evidence did not show that it was more practical to grant the right-of-way by turning left. Sanchez went to pass the plaintiff's vehicle on the left at the same time the plaintiff made a left-hand turn. The two vehicles collided.

"Generally speaking, facts must be pleaded as a special defense when they are consistent with the allegations of the complaint but demonstrate nonetheless, that the plaintiff has no cause of action. Practice Book §<cross_reference>10-50</cross_reference>." <italic>Almada v. Wausau Business Ins. Co.</italic>, <cross_reference>274 Conn. 449</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>456</cross_reference>,<cross_reference>876 A.2d 535</cross_reference> (2005). The preponderance of the evidence showed that Sanchez was operating his police cruiser in accordance with the right-of-way provisions of § <cross_reference>14-283</cross_reference>. While responding to the emergency call, he had his lights and siren on. He slowed down as he approached the intersection. He drove with due regard to the safety of the plaintiff. The defendant's negligence has not been established. Accordingly, defendant, city of Hartford, is not liable for the plaintiff's injuries.

<center>                                     <italic>IV</italic></center><center>                            <italic>CONCLUSION AND ORDER</italic></center>
For the above-stated reasons, the court renders judgment for the defendant and awards no damages to the plaintiff.

SO ORDERED.

<footnote_body><footnote_number>[fn1]</footnote_number> General Statutes § <cross_reference>14-283</cross_reference> provides in relevant part:

CT Page 18813<block_quote>  (a) `Emergency vehicle' . . . means any . . . local police vehicle operated by a police officer . . . answering an emergency call . . . while in the course of such officer's employment and while responding to an emergency call.</block_quote>

<block_quote>  (b) The operator of any emergency vehicle may . . . (2) proceed past any red light or stop signal or stop sign, but only after slowing down or stopping to the extent necessary for the safe operation of such vehicle, (3) exceed the posted speed limits or other speed limits imposed by or pursuant to section <cross_reference>14-218a</cross_reference>
or <cross_reference>14-219</cross_reference> as long as such operator does not endanger life or property by so doing, and (4) disregard statutes, ordinances or regulations governing direction of movement or turning in specific directions.</block_quote>

<block_quote>  (c) The exemptions herein granted shall apply . . . to any . . . local police vehicle properly and lawfully making use of an audible warning signal device only.</block_quote>

<block_quote>  (d) The provisions of this section shall not relieve the operator of an emergency vehicle from the duty to drive with due regard for the safety of all persons and property.</block_quote>

<block_quote>  (e) Upon the immediate approach of . . . any . . . local police vehicle properly and lawfully making use of an audible warning signal device only, the operator of every other vehicle in the immediate vicinity shall immediately drive to a position parallel to, and as close as possible to, the right-hand edge or curb of the roadway clear of any intersection and shall stop and remain in such position until the emergency vehicle has passed, except when otherwise directed by a state or local police officer . . ."</block_quote></footnote_body>

CT Page 18814

</unpublished></opinion_text>
</opinion>