<opinion unpublished=true>
<reporter_caption><center>WILLIAMS v. WILLIAMS, No. FA07-4006855 (Feb. 6, 2009)</center></reporter_caption>
<caption><center>MARK A. WILLIAMS v. CYNTHIA J. WILLIAMS.</center></caption>
<citation_line><center><citation>2009 Ct. Sup. 2859</citation></center></citation_line>
<docket><center>No. FA07-4006855</center></docket><court><center>Connecticut Superior Court</center><center>Judicial District of Danbury at Danbury</center></court>
<date><center>February 6, 2009</center>

</date>
<opinion_text><unpublished><footnote_body>[EDITOR'S NOTE: This case is unpublished as indicated by the issuing court.]</footnote_body><center>                           MEMORANDUM OF DECISION</center></unpublished></opinion_text>
<opinion_byline><unpublished>  WINSLOW, J.

</unpublished></opinion_byline>
<opinion_text><unpublished>  The plaintiff seeks dissolution of his marriage and other relief on the ground of irretrievable breakdown. Attorneys represented both parties on the trial dates. The more credible evidence leads to the following findings of fact. The plaintiff and the defendant, whose maiden name was Cynthia Jane Rosa, married December 22, 1982, at Bethel, Connecticut. This is the first marriage for both parties. The plaintiff has resided in the State of Connecticut continuously for more than one year next before the filing of this action. There are two children issue of the marriage. The parties' son is twenty-five years old and self-supporting. The parties' daughter, Christina J. Williams, was born December 8, 1986. She is twenty-two years old and attending college at Western Connecticut State University in her fourth year. The parties anticipate that Christina will require a fifth year at college in order to attain her bachelor's degree. No other children have been born to the defendant since the date of the marriage. During the marriage, no one in the family has received assistance in the nature of welfare from the State of Connecticut or any municipality.

The plaintiff husband is forty-five years old. Despite a family history of diabetes and heart disease, his physical and mental health is excellent. He has a high school education. Shortly after his graduation, the plaintiff met the defendant where they both worked at a supermarket. When the parties married in Connecticut, the plaintiff was nineteen years old and the defendant was eighteen. The plaintiff enlisted in the Air Force. He served as a military policeman in Texas. After two-and-a-half years of active service in Texas, the plaintiff and his wife moved back to Connecticut in late-1984. The plaintiff finished his military obligation thereafter by serving four years with the National Guard. Beginning in 1984, the plaintiff took jobs as a janitor, and then worked briefly for the postal service. On January 5, 1987, the plaintiff realized his lifelong goal by becoming a police officer. He served seven-and-a-half years in the patrol division of the Danbury police department. The patrol officers worked rotating shifts on a schedule of CT Page 2860 five days on, two days off, five days on, three days off. In 1994, the plaintiff became a vice control officer and was no longer subject to rotating shifts. In 1997, he was promoted to sergeant. As a sergeant, the plaintiff returned to community service work, first as a patrol officer, then as a bicycle patrol officer. In 2000, the plaintiff was promoted to detective sergeant supervising three officers in the youth bureau. The youth bureau investigates crimes against children. The present assignment of the plaintiff allows a consistent Monday through Friday work schedule. The plaintiff expects to stay in his current position within the department for the foreseeable future. He is not looking for a promotion to lieutenant. Such a promotion would require a return to the patrol division and its shifting hours. The plaintiff works forty hours per week plus limited overtime in the detective office. The police department now has a freeze in effect as to overtime work. Private duty work and road duty work are also possible, but the availability of that work is decreasing as the economy worsens. The plaintiff has a base salary of $74,724 per year. He has traditionally earned approximately $28,000 in overtime and private duty work. The plaintiff's gross earned income in 2007, was $101,901.83. In 2008, it was $106,555.11.

The plaintiff has contributed to his 457 tax-deferred plan for many years. The investment is now worth $39,925. The plaintiff vested in a pension plan after fifteen years of service with the Danbury police force. He has served twenty-two years and one month. If the plaintiff were to retire before twenty-five years of service, he could opt to receive an immediate lump sum payout of his retirement contribution (approximately $43,000 at this time) or he could opt to begin receiving a pension at age fifty-five calculated at two percent (2%) per year of service multiplied times his base pay for the averaged pay of his top three years of compensation. For example, if the plaintiff retires immediately with twenty-two years of service, he would receive, beginning at age fifty-five, forty-four percent per year of his base pay averaged over the past three years. If the plaintiff were to retire at twenty-five years of service, he would be entitled, immediately, to begin receiving two percent (2%) per year of service multiplied times his base pay for the averaged three years. At twenty-five years, the plaintiff would also receive an immediate increment of five percent (5%). Therefore, if the plaintiff were to retire at twenty-five years of service, he would receive immediately fifty-five percent (55%) of his base pay averaged over the past three years. For every year the plaintiff delays his retirement after twenty-five years, his retirement benefit increases an additional two percent (2%), up to a cap of 31.5 years (sixty-eight percent [68%]). Five years after retirement, the plaintiff would also receive a one-time boost in the pension benefit in the amount of two percent (2%). For example, if the plaintiff were to retire in nine years after thirty-one years of CT Page 2861 service, he would receive immediately sixty-seven percent (67%) of his base pay; five years thereafter, he would begin to receive sixty-nine (69%) of his base pay. If the plaintiff became permanently disabled at work prior to twenty-five years of service, he would receive disability retirement benefits at fifty percent (50%) of base pay (approximately $37,362 per year). No income tax would be payable on the plaintiff's disability pension. Unless the plaintiff is disabled from work, he may be able to acquire additional social security benefits from future employment after he leaves the police department.

The defendant wife is forty-four years old. Her physical and mental health is excellent. As a teenager, the defendant was working at Stop 
Shop supermarket when she married the plaintiff in December 1982. They moved together to San Antonio, Texas for the plaintiff's military service. After the birth of the parties' son in 1983, the defendant worked as a cashier for several months, first at Montgomery Ward, then at a troop store on the base. After the parties returned to Connecticut in late-1984, the defendant worked two or three months as a cashier at a Pathmark food store, and then in the warehouse at Pitney Bowes. After maternity leave for the birth of the parties' daughter in December 1986, the defendant returned for a short time to the Pitney Bowes job. Next, the defendant worked part-time at Deep's Market as a cashier. She left Deep's after a couple of months to work for her sister, who had opened a deli. The defendant graduated from high school by attending night school in 1987. When her sister's deli closed after one-and-a-half years, the defendant worked at Sears in a concession stand for a couple of months. Then she worked seven or eight years at Anesthesia Associates doing medical billing. In October 2001, the defendant took a position at Housatonic Valley Radiology Associates doing medical billing and coding, scheduling, receptionist work, interpreting and miscellaneous additional tasks. In 2005, and 2006, the defendant undertook new and expanded duties with a team of employees marketing enhanced magnetic resonance imagery (MRI) services to area doctors. In recognition of her added responsibilities, the defendant received a promotion and increase in pay to $22 per hour in February 2006. The defendant left Housatonic Radiology in January 2007, for her current position at Community Radiology Network. Her duties are similar to her work at Housatonic Radiology. She earns $50,000 per year. The defendant has contributed to the social security system throughout her working career. She has accumulated tax-deferred assets invested at Oppenheimer funds in the amount of $38,738. The defendant's pension eligibility will not vest until five years at her current job, i.e. January 2012. She is not part of the pension plan as yet at her current place of employment. She may be able to acquire pension assets in the future. The defendant is covered by the plaintiff's health insurance plan at this time. Upon the dissolution of CT Page 2862 her marriage, the defendant anticipates a cost of $37 per week for health insurance through her own place of work.

In April 1992, the parties purchased a five-room house in Brookfield, Connecticut at 14 Alexander Drive (the house). They financed the purchase by mortgaging the entire purchase price. The plaintiff undertook extensive renovations, including replacing the roof and siding, sheetrocking, redoing the driveway, and renovating the kitchen and bathrooms. The defendant helped with miscellaneous clean-up tasks during renovations. The house is worth $310,000 today. The parties' original mortgage has been paid down to $79,300. When this action for dissolution of the marriage began in November 2006, the defendant moved out of the house. When the defendant moved back into the house seven or eight months later, the plaintiff moved out of the house. The defendant now lives alone at the house. She has a boyfriend who stays at the house three or four nights a week. Pendente lite, the plaintiff pays the mortgage, taxes and home owner's insurance at the house, plus the heat and the telephone land line cost. The plaintiff also pays the auto loan for the defendant's car and the car insurance for that car. These expenses now total $2,416 per month. The defendant pays for electricity, garbage removal, cable television, her cell phone and the life insurance on the parties' two life insurance policies through Met Life. Each party's life is insured by a term policy in the face amount of $300,000.

When the parties resided together, the plaintiff rarely used credit cards. The defendant would use her credit cards when the parties ate at restaurants. When the parties separated in November 2006, the defendant's credit card debt totaled approximately $6,000 for family expenses. The defendant's credit card debt now exceeds $24,000. Most of the new credit card debt incurred by the defendant is attributable to the $13,000 she spent on elective plastic surgery in February 2007, and attorneys fees associated with this action. The defendant seems unaware that she is paying exorbitant interest rates on her credit cards. For example, the defendant used the Care Credit card exclusively for part of her plastic surgery cost. The balance owed on that card is $4,704.25. The defendant is now paying 29.99 percent interest on that card.

The parties are united in supporting the higher education of their daughter. The plaintiff has been paying the daughter's tuition and book costs for four years. He has carried Christina on his medical insurance policy and pays her unreimbursed medical costs. He also provides a cash allowance of about $200 per month. The defendant pays the daughter's rent and miscellaneous expenses.

It will serve no useful purpose to repeat the charges each party CT Page 2863 leveled against the other concerning fault in the breakdown of the marriage. As the court stated on the record after the completion of evidence and final arguments, the plaintiff's testimony concerning the breakdown of the marriage was credible and amply supported by additional witnesses. The defendant's testimony concerning the breakdown was not consistent with statements made at her deposition and was not credible. The court finds the defendant primarily at fault in the breakdown of the marriage.

The court has considered all the criteria of General Statutes §§ <cross_reference>46b-56c</cross_reference>,<cross_reference>46b-62</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>46b-81</cross_reference>, and <cross_reference>46b-82</cross_reference> in light of the evidence presented. The parties are in equipoise as to age, station, health, and needs of the parties. The plaintiff enjoys advantages over the defendant in such matters as occupation, amount and sources of income, vocational skills, estate, liabilities, and the opportunity for future acquisition of capital assets and income. Fault for the breakdown of the marriage is assessed against the defendant. Such assets as the parties have acquired have come primarily from the parties' earnings. The court has not attempted or intended that the parties have an equal division of income or assets. The following are the orders of the court:

1. The marriage of the parties is dissolved on the ground of irretrievable breakdown.

The parties are each declared to be single and unmarried.

2. The plaintiff shall pay spousal support to the defendant in the amount of $2,500 per month commencing March 1, 2009, for a total of seventeen (17) months or until the death of either party. Alimony shall not cease upon the remarriage or cohabitation of the defendant. Alimony shall cease July 31, 2010. Alimony shall be non-modifiable as to amount and term. Alimony shall be taxable to the defendant and tax-deductible for the plaintiff.

3. No alimony is awarded to the plaintiff.

4. The plaintiff shall be the sole owner of the Met Life insurance policy and the life insurance through his employment insuring his life. He is responsible for payment of any and all premiums commencing immediately. He is not obligated to keep the policies in place. He may designate any beneficiary or beneficiaries of his choice.

5. The defendant shall be the sole owner of the Met Life insurance policy insuring her life. She is responsible for payment of any and all premiums commencing immediately. She is not obligated to keep the policy CT Page 2864 in place. She may designate any beneficiary of her choice.

6. Each party shall be responsible for his or her own health insurance and costs.

7. The plaintiff shall pay all mortgage, tax and insurance payments for the house through February 2009. The plaintiff shall pay all heating bills and landline telephone bills at the house with a billing date prior to March 1, 2009. The defendant shall pay all utilities and services incurred at the house for all heating bills and landline telephone bills with a billing date on and after March 1, 2009. It is the billing date, and not the date the services were used, that will determine which bills are to be paid by each party. Each such bill will not be split by the parties. The plaintiff's payments for the month of February shall not be alimony.

8. The plaintiff shall pay the auto loan payment and auto insurance for the defendant's Acura automobile through the month of February 2009. The plaintiff's payments for the month of February shall not be alimony.

9. The defendant is awarded sole ownership of the real property (the house) at 14 Alexander Drive, Brookfield, Connecticut. She shall immediately have sole and exclusive possession of the house. The plaintiff shall forthwith give to the defendant every key to the house now in his possession or control. Commencing March 1, 2009, the defendant shall be solely responsible for payment of the mortgage, taxes, home owner's insurance, heat, utilities, services, maintenance, repairs and costs of all kinds associated with the house. The defendant shall indemnify and save the plaintiff harmless from all such expenses and liabilities. On or before July 31, 2010, the defendant shall sell or refinance the mortgage on the house so as to remove the plaintiff's name from any liability associated with the house.

10. On or before July 31, 2010, the defendant shall pay to the plaintiff as lump sum property settlement the sum of $47,000. The debt is to be secured by a promissory note and second mortgage placed upon the house. If the defendant defaults in the payment of the note on or before July 31, 2010, interest shall begin on the obligation as of August 1, 2010, at the rate of eight percent (8%) per annum. The plaintiff shall prepare the note and mortgage deed to be executed by the defendant promptly upon presentation. The mortgage shall be recorded at the expense of the plaintiff. The release upon the full payment of the obligation shall be prepared and filed on the land records by the plaintiff. If the defendant refinances the mortgage or secures a home equity line at any time prior to July 31, 2010, she shall pay to the CT Page 2865 plaintiff the full amount owed to him simultaneously with the securing of the refinance or the home equity line.

11. The plaintiff shall retain sole ownership of the Toyota Tacoma automobile and the Toyota Camry automobile. He shall pay all costs and expenses associated with those vehicles and shall indemnify and save harmless the defendant as to all such costs and expenses.

12. The defendant shall have sole rights to the ownership of the Acura TL automobile. Commencing March 1, 2009, she shall pay all costs and expenses associated with that vehicle and shall indemnify and save harmless the plaintiff as to all such costs and expenses. Upon the pay off of the remaining loan on the Acura TL, the plaintiff shall sign all documents necessary to transfer his interest in the vehicle to the defendant.

13. The plaintiff shall retain sole ownership of his 457 tax-deferred plan with The Hartford. Until July 31, 2010, the plaintiff shall designate the defendant as sole death beneficiary of the 457 plan. On or before March 31, 2009, the plaintiff shall provide to the defendant written proof that the defendant is named as sole beneficiary on the 457 plan. Commencing August 1, 2010, the plaintiff may remove the defendant as the beneficiary, if he so chooses.

14. The defendant shall retain sole ownership of her tax-deferred plan now or formerly invested with the Oppenheimer Funds. Any rights by the plaintiff to claim an interest in the defendant's tax-deferred asset are hereby terminated.

15. The defendant is awarded part of the plaintiff's Danbury police pension by the present division method. See <italic>Bender v. Bender</italic>, <cross_reference>258 Conn. 733</cross_reference>,<cross_reference>758-60</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>785 A.2d 197</cross_reference> (2001).

<block_quote>  a. The defendant shall receive a fraction of the accrued benefit when the plaintiff retires. The remaining benefit shall belong solely to the plaintiff. The fraction representing the defendant's interest shall have a numerator of eleven (11) and a denominator that is the number of years of credited service as of the date of the plaintiff's retirement. The denominator shall, however, never exceed thirty-one and one-half (31.5).</block_quote>

<block_quote>  Defendant's benefit 11 = x Accrued benefit credited years of service as of date of retirement</block_quote>
CT Page 2866

<block_quote>  Example: If the number of years of work is 27.5 (credited service) at retirement and the accrued benefit is $5,000 per month at that time, the defendant's initial benefit would be $2,000 per month and the plaintiff's initial benefit would be $3,000 per month.</block_quote>

<block_quote>  b. If the pension benefit increases after retirement, the parties will benefit from the increase in the same proportion as the initial benefit. Example: If the pension amount goes up two percent (2%) five years after retirement, the defendant and the plaintiff will share the increase using the same fraction that defined the portion of the pension received by each party at retirement.</block_quote>

<block_quote>  c. If the plaintiff becomes disabled before twenty-five years of credited service and receives only a disability pension, the plaintiff shall receive the entire disability pension; in that circumstance, the defendant shall receive no part of the disability payments.</block_quote>

<block_quote>  d. To the extent permitted by the plan, the defendant shall be entitled to a separate interest so that the defendant will not lose her entitlement to benefits if the plaintiff dies before retiring.</block_quote>

<block_quote>  e. If the defendant dies before the plaintiff retires, then the defendant's portion of the pension will revert to the plaintiff's benefit.</block_quote>

f. The parties shall mutually select a qualified person to prepare the Domestic Relations Order (DRO) to effectuate the division of the pension in accordance with these orders. If the parties are not able to agree upon the person to prepare the DRO within sixty days of this judgment, the parties shall return to the court and the court shall make the selection. All costs for the preparation and submission of the DRO shall be shared equally by the parties.

<block_quote>  g. The court shall retain jurisdiction for review and approval of the DRO, if necessary.</block_quote>

16. The plaintiff shall be solely responsible for the debts showing on CT Page 2867 his financial affidavit dated January 23, 2009. He shall indemnify and save harmless the defendant as to all such debts.

17. The defendant shall be solely responsible for the debts showing on her financial affidavit dated January 20, 2009. She shall indemnify and save harmless the defendant as to all such debts.

18. It is more likely than not that the parties would have continued to provide support to their daughter for college if the family were intact. Until December 8, 2009, when the parties' daughter attains the age of twenty-three, the plaintiff shall pay the tuition, books, and student fees for the parties' daughter Christina at Western Connecticut State University. Until December 8, 2009, the plaintiff shall provide medical insurance for Christina and shall pay all unreimbursed medical and dental costs for Christina. Until December 8, 2009, the defendant shall pay the rent or shelter costs for Christina to allow her to attend Western Connecticut State University. The defendant may invite Christina to live in the same residence with the defendant in lieu of paying rent separately for the daughter.

19. The plaintiff and the defendant shall each be entitled to claim for income tax purposes one-half of mortgage and real property taxes paid by the parties or either of them for the house for the tax years 2007 and 2008.

20. The defendant shall be entitled to claim for income tax purposes all mortgage interest and real estate taxes paid by the parties or either of them for the house for the tax year 2009, and all subsequent years.

21. The plaintiff shall be entitled to claim Christina as a dependency exemption for the tax year 2008, and all subsequent years, if the exemption is available to be claimed by either party.

22. The plaintiff may make copies for himself at his own expense of any photographs he removed from the house while this action has been pending. The plaintiff shall return to the defendant in good condition all the photographs, framed photographs and photo albums removed from the house by the plaintiff. The plaintiff shall deliver these materials to the office of his attorney on or before March 31, 2009. The plaintiff's attorney shall convey the materials to the office of the defendant's attorney immediately thereafter.

23. Each party shall retain all other items of tangible personal property now in his or her possession. CT Page 2868

24. Each party shall retain bank accounts now in his or her name.

25. The plaintiff shall retain the joint Sikorsky Federal Credit Union account.

26. The defendant shall retain the Pitney Bowes stock.

27. The parties shall divide equally the joint Primerica and Pruamerican account or accounts.

CT Page 2869

</unpublished></opinion_text>
</opinion>