<opinion unpublished=true>
<reporter_caption><center>SAGA SOLUTIONS v. KENNY, No. CV01 0072857S (Oct. 30, 2003)</center></reporter_caption>
<caption><center>SAGA SOLUTIONS v. BRIAN KENNY.</center></caption>
<citation_line><center><citation>2003 Ct. Sup. 11667</citation></center></citation_line>
<docket><center>No. CV01 0072857S</center></docket><court><center>Connecticut Superior Court, Judicial District of Ansonia-Milford</center><center>at Milford</center></court>
<date><center>October 30, 2003</center>

</date>
<opinion_text><unpublished><footnote_body>[EDITOR'S NOTE: This case is unpublished as indicated by the issuing court.]</footnote_body><center>                         MEMORANDUM OF DECISION</center></unpublished></opinion_text>
<opinion_byline><unpublished>  CURRAN, JUDGE TRIAL REFEREE.

</unpublished></opinion_byline>
<opinion_text><unpublished>  Saga Solutions, LLC, the plaintiff, is in the business of installing computer software systems and providing support and training to its various customers.

Toward the latter part of 1999 and the early part of the year 2000, the defendant, Brian Kenny, was employed by a firm known as Uniscribe, a customer of Saga Solutions. In supplying the training and support services, Mr. Jacobowitz, the President and CEO of Saga Solutions, came into contact with Mr. Kenny. Both parties worked together in implementing the software program at Uniscribe. This led to the solicitation of Mr. Kenny by Mr. Jacobowitz to come to work for Saga Solutions, LLC.

At that time, Saga Solutions was a small start-up company with three employees. Uniscribe, Mr. Kenny's employer, was a large company with several hundred employees and whose work covered a large territory.

Having the opportunity to work with and observe Mr. Kenny, Mr. Jacobowitz actively pursued him to work for Saga Solutions. At that time, Kenny was comfortable in his employment with Uniscribe, being paid a salary of $112,000.00 per year, with fringe benefits. He was married with small children and was in the process of purchasing a new home. Although comfortable at Uniscribe, Kenny could see opportunities that might exist were he to change his employment, including bonus plans

Jacobowitz offered Kenny a salary of $100,000.00. Kenny, whose move to Saga would be a lateral move, found this to be unacceptable and indicated he would need a bonus of $15,000.00 to make the move. This was accepted and Kenny transferred his employment to Saga.

The issue here is whether the $15,000.00 was a sign-on bonus and not reimbursable as claimed by Kenny or whether it was an advancement on an incentive bonus based on Kenny's billable hours as claimed by Jacobowitz. CT Page 11668

The offer of employment was in the form of a letter to Kenny by Jacobowitz on behalf of Saga dated March 21, 2000. The compensation offered was $100,000.00 per annum. In addition, the offer contained the following statement:

<block_quote>  Initial advance. Upon acceptance of this agreement and commencement of employment, you will receive $15,000.00 that is an advance against your 2000 bonus under Sage Senior Technical Management Incentive Compensation Plan.</block_quote>

(See Ex. 1.)

Reference is made in the offer of the need for him to sign the "enclosed confidentiality agreement." The plan was not enclosed nor was the incentive plan, which was still being drafted at the time.

The terms of the offer were not acceptable to Kenny and he indicated his concern to Jacobowitz. The offer of employment was never signed or accepted by Kenny.

Nevertheless, Kenny began his employment with Saga. Upon doing so, he was proffered a check in the amount of $15,000.00. There was a notation on the check indicated it was an "advance on bonuses," "bonuses" being in the plural as opposed to the term being in the singular as in the offer of employment. Kenny, being of the opinion that bonuses were to be multiple, i.e., sign-on bonus and incentive bonus, negotiated the check. The sole issue as it relates to the first count of plaintiff's complaint is whether the $15,000.00 check was a sign-on bonus or whether it represented an advance payment on any incentive bonus the defendant might earn.

<block_quote>  To form a valid and binding contract in Connecticut, there must be a mutual understanding of the terms that are definite and certain between the parties . . . To constitute an offer and acceptance sufficient to create an enforceable contract, each must be found to have been based on an identical understanding by the parties.</block_quote>

(Internal quotation marks omitted.) <italic>Cheverie v. Ashcraft  Gerel</italic>,<cross_reference>65 Conn. App. 425</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>439</cross_reference> (2001).

It is obvious that there was no meeting of the minds as to the offer of CT Page 11669 employment. The defendant Kenny never signed the offer of employment. He did commence working for Saga Solutions and did accept a check in the amount of $15,000.00. While the offer of employment referred to a check which was to be an advance on an incentive bonus, the check that was delivered contains a memorandum entitled "bonuses." Mr. Kenny accepted the check as written in the belief that "bonuses" plural meant that the check was a sign-on bonus.

In examining the facts surrounding Kenny's employment by Saga, the court is of the opinion that the check was a sign-on bonus.

In arriving at that conclusion, the court takes note of the fact that the defendant, Kenny, was at the time working for an established company; that he was in the process of purchasing a home and received a salary of $112,000.00; that he received sign — on bonuses previously; that Saga was a start-up company with all of the risks involved; and it is highly improbable that Kenny would make a lateral move of this nature at a reduction in salary.

"In a civil action, the general burden of proof rests on the plaintiff, and when an answer denies several paragraphs of the complaint, the burden of proving each separate, material issue of fact that was raised is thrown on the plaintiff." <italic>Hally v. Hospital of St. Raphael</italic>,<cross_reference>162 Conn. 352</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>358</cross_reference> (1972)

The court finds that the plaintiff has not, by any preponderance of the evidence, sustained its burden of proof.

The second count of plaintiff's complaint seeks the recovery of wages paid to the defendant, Kenny, during the last three weeks of employment. While the complaint makes reference to three weeks, the evidence elicited at the trial was for two weeks. It is the claim of Saga Solutions that Mr. Kenny performed no services entitling him to the compensation paid.

Again, the evidence fails to show by any preponderance of the evidence that Mr. Kenny performed no services during that period of time. The strength of the claim seems to be the lack of any time sheets. Kenny counters the plaintiff's testimony with the claim that he in fact performed during that time; that his time sheets can be found on his computer; that he worked with customers during that time; and that much of his work was done at the company offices. Based on the evidence presented, the court is of the opinion that the defendant did in fact render services relating to his employment during his last two weeks at Saga Solutions. On the second count, the court finds for the defendant. CT Page 11670

Judgment may enter in accordance with the above.

The Court

By Curran, JTR CT Page 11671

</unpublished></opinion_text>
</opinion>