<opinion unpublished=true>
<reporter_caption><center>STATE v. BECKERMAN, No. CR09-0629576-S (Dec. 14, 2010)</center></reporter_caption>
<caption><center>STATE OF CONNECTICUT v. WILLIAM BECKERMAN.</center></caption>
<citation_line><center><citation>2011 Ct. Sup. 1198</citation></center></citation_line>
<docket><center>No. CR09-0629576-S</center></docket><court><center>Connecticut Superior Court</center><center>Judicial District of Hartford at Hartford</center></court>
<date><center>December 14, 2010</center>

</date>
<opinion_text><unpublished><footnote_body>[EDITOR'S NOTE: This case is unpublished as indicated by the issuing court.]</footnote_body><center>                         MEMORANDUM OF DECISION MOTION TO SET BAIL PENDING APPEAL</center></unpublished></opinion_text>
<opinion_byline><unpublished>  O'KEEFE, J.

</unpublished></opinion_byline>
<opinion_text><unpublished>  This is a motion to set bail pending an appeal. It should be noted that the court previously considered the same motion and it was denied.

The court recognizes that it has discretion to grant post-conviction bail. The court also agrees that a number of factors should be considered in that decision.

The court, however, views these factors in a different light than the former defendant. To begin with Mr. Beckerman has been convicted and sentenced. The presumption of innocence no longer applies and there is no question about the severity of his sentence. The temptation to flee can only be described as great.

Next. The former defendant's history of appearance at trial is of questionable relevance. The same can be said for all formerly accused individuals who flee when they finally face the reality of their situation. His intentional conduct put the lives of numerous people at risk.

Mr. Beckerman's record also includes an apparent unwillingness to pay his fair share of his taxes. A record of fraud, even in the past, certainly does not inspire confidence in Beckerman's reliability.

Family ties were considered by the court in this motion. At trial, Mr. Beckerman was portrayed as married with a wife and children. Apparently that is not the truth. He is married and has a fond, but distant, relationship with his wife and children but also lives with another woman with whom he has a child at an address that is different than the address he lists as his residence in the PSI.

CT Page 1199

As far as employment. The State of Connecticut Department of Labor has no current wages listed for Mr. Beckerman. How Mr. Beckerman supports himself was never fully explained at trial or at his sentencing. It is therefore difficult to assess his financial resources. Obviously his character is extremely suspect and the court sees his mental condition as defiant, unrepentant and unremorseful.

Mr. Beckerman is elderly. His age is a factor of little relevance. His health problems, for the most part, are self-reported and appear to be under control.

The motion is denied. The court finds incarceration appropriate and necessary in light of all the factors considered.

CT Page 1200

</unpublished></opinion_text>
</opinion>