<opinion unpublished=true>
<reporter_caption><center>IN RE NATALIA T., No. T11-CP06-012452-A (May 11, 2007)</center></reporter_caption>
<caption><center>IN RE NATALIA T.<footnote_reference>[fn1]</footnote_reference>.</center></caption>
<citation_line><center><citation>2007 Ct. Sup. 6720</citation></center></citation_line>
<docket><center>No. T11-CP06-012452-A</center></docket><court><center>Connecticut Superior Court</center><center>Judicial District of Tolland at Rockville,</center><center>Juvenile Matters</center></court>
<date><center>May 11, 2007</center>

</date>
<opinion_text><unpublished><footnote_body>[EDITOR'S NOTE: This case is unpublished as indicated by the issuing court.]</footnote_body><footnote_body><footnote_number>[fn1]</footnote_number> In accordance with the Connecticut General Statutes Section<cross_reference>46b-124</cross_reference> and the Connecticut Practice Book Section <cross_reference>32a-7</cross_reference>, the names of the parties involved in this case are not to be disclosed and the records and papers of this case shall be open for inspection only to persons having a proper interest therein and only upon order of the Superior Court.</footnote_body>

</unpublished></opinion_text>
<opinion_text><unpublished><center>                         <italic>MEMORANDUM OF DECISION</italic></center></unpublished></opinion_text>
<opinion_byline><unpublished>  E. GRAZIANI, JUDGE.

</unpublished></opinion_byline>
<opinion_text><unpublished>  This case regarding the child Natalia T. presents a petition of alleged neglect filed by the Department of Children and Families on March 29, 2006 as amended on August 3, 2006.

The history of the file reveals that on March 29, 2006, a Petition of alleged Neglect was filed by the Department of Children and Families in the Superior Court for Juvenile Matters at Rockville. On July 26, 2006, DCF invoked a 96-hour Administrative Hold on behalf of said child. On July 28, 2006, filed a Motion for an Order of Temporary Custody on behalf of the above-named child. On August 3, 2006, the Motion for an Order of Temporary Custody was sustained. On August 3, 2006, the Neglect Petition was amended. The mother entered a written plea of nolo contendere on November 30, 2006 to the allegations in the petition that the child was neglected in that the child was permitted to live under conditions, circumstances or associations injurious to her well-being. Accordingly, on November 30, 2006, the Court found that the mother's plea was knowingly and voluntarily made with the adequate advice and assistance of competent counsel and that there was a factual basis for the plea. The court accepted the plea of the mother and adjudicated the matter as to the mother by finding that the child has been neglected in that the child has been permitted to live under conditions, circumstances or associations injurious to the child's well-being.

On May 2, 2007, this matter was tried to the court. The Department of Children and Families was represented by Attorney Jason Lobo. The minor child was represented by Attorney Steven Melocowsky. The mother was CT Page 6721 represented by Attorney Trudy Condio and the father was represented by Attorney Sara Robinson.

The court has reviewed the evidence produced at the trial and heard the testimony of the witnesses. The credible and relevant evidence submitted during the trial reveals the following facts.

The court heard testimony from Mr. Colin Coburn of the Department of Corrections, Crystal Smith and Jessica Thomas, both Social Workers with the Department of Children and Families who were familiar with the DCF case regarding the subject child. In addition, the court has reviewed the multiple exhibits filed in this case which include the Social Studies done by DCF in regard to the subject family.

The child is now approximately one and one-half years old. The child is currently residing in a non-relative foster home. The father has also presented the Department with relatives as a possible resource for the child and the Department is currently investigating the relatives.

The father has history of criminal convictions starting in 1998 and continuing through the June 28, 2006 when he was incarcerated after being found guilty of the crime of Burglary in the first degree for which he received a sentence of eight years in jail, with three years to serve and four years probation. He also was found guilty on June 28, 2006 to a charge of violation of a protective order in which he received a three-year sentence to run concurrently with the sentence for the burglary. Those convictions resulted from an incident that occurred on January 14, 2006 as detailed in a police report entered as Petitioner's Exhibit #2, in which the father broke into the mother's residence in violation of a protective order in which the mother sustained injuries. The child while not hurt during the incident but was present. As of this date he remains in prison with his earliest release date being January 16, 2009. His criminal history also includes but is not limited to convictions for threatening in the second degree, breach of peace in the second degree, breach of peace in the second degree, criminal mischief, criminal trover in the second degree, evading/inj./prop, larceny 2, larceny 4, and interfering and resisting arrest.

The father has long-standing mental health, substance abuse and domestic violence issues as detailed in the multiple exhibits entered by the Petitioner. Given the long history of the father's criminal involvement, his substance abuse and mental health issues that have placed the child at risk, as well as the father's current incarceration, it is not in the best interest of the child that the child be placed with the father. CT Page 6722

The father acknowledges that he is unable to care for the child at the present time due to his incarceration. Testimony was presented by a DCF social worker that the Department does not know of any program to allow a child to be placed to live with a parent who is incarcerated.

The father currently visits with his daughter one hour a month and the visits are going well with both the child and the father responding appropriately.

The mother has previously voluntarily entered a nolo contendere plea to the neglect petition and is not contesting the disposition of commitment.

The Attorney for the minor child supports the Department's request for an adjudication of neglect as well as commitment of the child.

By a fair preponderance of the evidence as of the date of the petition, as amended, the court finds that the child, Natalia T. has been neglected in that the child has been permitted to live under conditions, circumstances or associations injurious to her well-being and that the child has been denied proper care and attention, physically, educationally, emotionally or morally.

In reference to the disposition, the court hereby finds by fair preponderance of the evidence that the following disposition is in the best interest of the child. The child, Natalia T. is committed until further order of the court to the Commissioner of the Department of Children and Families who shall be guardian of the child. The court hereby orders and approves as final steps the specific steps attached hereto as part disposition of this case. In addition, the court finds that continuation in the home is contrary to the welfare of the child and that reasonable efforts to prevent or eliminate the removal of the child were made by the state.

CT Page 6723

</unpublished></opinion_text>
</opinion>