<opinion unpublished=true>
<reporter_caption><center>CRAIG S.S. v. DCF, COMMISSIONER, No. HHB-CV08-4018108-S (Oct. 30, 2008)</center></reporter_caption>
<caption><center>CRAIG S.S. v. COMMISSIONER, DEPARTMENT OF CHILDREN AND FAMILIES.</center></caption>
<citation_line><center><citation>2008 Ct. Sup. 17382</citation></center></citation_line>
<docket><center>No. HHB-CV08-4018108-S</center></docket><court><center>Connecticut Superior Court</center><center>Judicial District of New Britain at New Britain</center></court>
<date><center>October 30, 2008</center>

</date>
<opinion_text><unpublished><footnote_body>[EDITOR'S NOTE: This case is unpublished as indicated by the issuing court.]</footnote_body><center>                         <italic>MEMORANDUM OF DECISION</italic></center></unpublished></opinion_text>
<opinion_byline><unpublished>  BEAR, J.

</unpublished></opinion_byline>
<opinion_text><unpublished>  On February 25, 2007, the defendant commissioner of the department of children and families ("DCF") filed a petition for the termination of the parental rights of the mother and the father ("TPR proceeding") who is the plaintiff in this declaratory judgment proceeding.<footnote_reference>[fn1]</footnote_reference>

The mother died in April 2007.

The Child Protection Session of the Superior Court for Juvenile Matters ("CPS") scheduled the TPR petition for trial beginning on May 13, 2008.

On March 9, 2008, while the plaintiff was incarcerated in Missouri, he filed with DCF a petition for declaratory ruling concerning "open adoption" issues. In such petition, the plaintiff asserted, <italic>inter</italic><italic>alia</italic>, that

<block_quote>  DCF must refuse to license and/or refrain from allowing adoption by any prospective foster/adoptive parents who are unwilling to consult with an attorney supplied by Connecticut Association of Foster and Adoptive Parents, Inc. (CAFAP), and explore, in good faith, whether a cooperative post-adoption agreement is in the best interests of the prospective adoptee through one or more conferences with the child's attorney, the biological parent(s), the prospective adoptive parents, the CAFAP attorney, and other appropriate individuals.<footnote_reference>[fn2]</footnote_reference></block_quote>

On or about April 18, 2008, the plaintiff filed a motion for continuance of the upcoming TPR trial and on May 1, 2008, the court (Wilson, J.) denied such motion with prejudice.

CT Page 17383

On May 9, 2008, DCF mailed to the plaintiff's counsel and on May 13, 2008, in her post office box the counsel for the plaintiff received from DCF a notice of pre-hearing conference/declaratory ruling. Counsel picked up such notice on May 15, 2008.

On May 13, 2008, the TPR trial commenced and continued on the next day, May 14, 2008.

On May 14, 2008, the plaintiff consented to a termination of his parental rights, and the parties (including DCF and the father but excluding the pre-adoptive foster mother) entered into a stipulated agreement for so long as DCF was the statutory parent providing for means of contact between the father and his biological child, including sending cards, letters and gifts, the involvement of the child's therapist for the best interest of Samantha, the ability of the child to reply to the father under appropriate circumstances, supervised visitation with the paternal grandmother under appropriate circumstances, her contact information to be provided to the adoptive parents, a monthly written progress report to the father from DCF and/or the therapist, and a provision for possible involvement by the father with the child if the child is not adopted. The father knowingly, voluntarily and intelligently consented to the termination of his parental rights, see General Statutes § <cross_reference>45a-707</cross_reference>(8) and form JD-JM-60, affidavit/consent to termination of parental rights, and he entered into the stipulated agreement, although because he was incarcerated in Missouri he did not sign it.

Judge Wilson, who allowed the trial to stop and based on the father's and his counsel's representations accepted the father's consent, set forth the following about the canvass of the father and his consent in her decision denying the father's subsequent motion to open the TPR judgment:

<block_quote>  The father submitted a written consent to terminate his parental rights, after which this court fully canvassed him. Based on the full canvass, the court found by clear and convincing evidence, the consent to be knowingly, intelligently and voluntarily made. The court subsequently found that it was in the minor child's best interest to terminate the respondent father's parental rights and entered judgment accordingly. It is this judgment that the respondent father seeks to open.</block_quote>

CT Page 17384

<italic>In re Samantha S.</italic>, <cross_reference>2008 Ct.Sup. 12153</cross_reference>, No. D03-CP06-002317-A, Superior Court, Judicial District of Middlesex, Child Protection Session at Middletown (Wilson, J., July 23, 2008).

On May 29, 2008, DCF dismissed the plaintiff's petition for declaratory ruling. The written decision included the following:

<block_quote>  As to his biological daughter, Mr. S. had a legal interest up until 5/14/08, on which date he voluntarily consented to terminate his parental rights in exchange for an agreement with DCF that he will be allowed limited post-judgment contact with the child only while the agency remains her statutory parent. He entered this agreement voluntarily, despite the fact that his motion for a continuance based on the pendency of the declaratory ruling petition had been denied on 5/1/08 and knowing that the preadoptive parents were unwilling to enter into a postadoption cooperative agreement.</block_quote>

<block_quote>  As his petition for a declaratory ruling requests that the agency's decision be tied to the specific facts of his TPR case, and since the petitioner voluntarily terminated his parental rights in exchange for limited post-TPR contact that does not involve the preadoptive parents, the question presented in his petition is not only moot, but any standing that he may have had has been voluntarily relinquished. Any facts stated in the original petition that would tend to support his standing to request a declaratory ruling have been superseded by his voluntary action in court. He no longer has a legal interest in the question of whether the Department is required to place his biological child with preadoptive parents who are interested in pursuing a postadoption agreement.</block_quote>

(Footnote omitted.)

On July 14, 2008, pursuant to General Statutes § <cross_reference>4-175</cross_reference>(a)(2), <footnote_reference>[fn3]</footnote_reference> the plaintiff Craig S. ("the plaintiff" or "the father") filed a complaint for declaratory judgment based on the decision of the defendant commissioner of the department of children and families dismissing the CT Page 17385 plaintiff's petition for a declaratory ruling pursuant to General Statutes § <cross_reference>4-176</cross_reference>(e)(5).<footnote_reference>[fn4]</footnote_reference>

The plaintiff sought the following declaratory relief in this court:

<block_quote>  1. Whether, pursuant to General Statutes Section <cross_reference>17a-112</cross_reference>, the defendant has a necessary and supportive role in facilitating a discussion of a voluntary termination and an open adoption agreement between the potential adoptive parent and the plaintiff who was subject to a termination petition when the plaintiff wants to remain in contact and believes it is in the child's best interests to do so.</block_quote>

<block_quote>  2. Whether, pursuant to General Statues 46b-129(k)(4) and specifically to the standard of "child specific recruitment," the defendant has an obligation to make a preliminary determination concerning cooperative post-adoption relationships, which would include not recruiting families who are opposed to cooperative agreements with the biological parents when children would prefer such contact or for whom such contact might be in their best interests.</block_quote>

<block_quote>  3. Whether the defendant has an obligation during administrative case reviews to provide any information about the prospective adoptive family to the biological parent who still maintains legal rights and responsibilities.</block_quote>

<block_quote>  4. Whether, pursuant to General Statutes Section <cross_reference>17a-112</cross_reference> and <cross_reference>46b-129</cross_reference>(k)(4) and Regs. Conn. State Agencies §§ <cross_reference>48-3</cross_reference>, 48-5-5, 48-12-3, and 48-13-3, the defendant must refuse to license and/or refrain from allowing adoption by a prospective foster/adoptive parent who are unwilling to consult with an attorney supplied by Connecticut Association of Foster and Adoptive Parents, Inc. (CAFAP), and explore in good faith, whether a cooperative post-adoption agreement is in the best interests of the prospective adoptee through one or more conferences with the child's attorney, the biological parent(s), the CT Page 17386 prospective adoptive parents, the CAFAP attorney, and other appropriate individuals.</block_quote>

Pursuant to General Statutes § <cross_reference>52-212a</cross_reference>, the plaintiff sought to open the TPR judgment, but he was unsuccessful. On July 23, 2008, the court (Wilson, J.) denied the plaintiff's motion to open such judgment. <italic>In re</italic><italic>Samantha S., supra</italic>. Judge Wilson explained:

<block_quote>  In order to open a judgment pursuant to § <cross_reference>52-212</cross_reference>, "a moving party must show reasonable cause, or that a good cause of action or defense in whole or in part existed at the time of the rendition of the judgment or the passage of the decree, and that the plaintiff or defendant was prevented by mistake, accident or other reasonable cause from prosecuting the action or making the defense." This statutory language has been interpreted by the courts to represent two distinct prongs. "There must be a showing that (1) a good defense, the nature of which must be set forth, existed at the time judgment was rendered, and (2) the party seeking to set aside the judgment was prevented from making that defense because of mistake, accident or other reasonable cause." <italic>In Re</italic> <italic>Ilyssa</italic>, <cross_reference>105 Conn.App. 41</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>45</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>936 A.2d 674</cross_reference>
(2007).</block_quote>

<block_quote>  A review of the motion and related briefs, as well as oral argument, establishes that the respondent father has not satisfied the first prong necessary to open the termination judgment. His motion seeks to open a termination judgment, however, the grounds for this motion is his alleged imperfect knowledge of a declaratory ruling that involves the placement of the child after termination. The post-termination placement of the child is not at issue during the termination proceeding. Accordingly, his knowledge of the status of the declaratory judgment, and the effect that this knowledge may have had on his consent, does not constitute a defense to this court's ultimate decision to terminate his parental rights. Even if DCF issued a timely ruling in favor of the respondent father's position, the outcome would not concern CT Page 17387 the issues before the court in the termination proceeding, namely whether the statutory grounds for termination existed and whether termination was in the best interest of the child. Therefore, even though the respondent father alleges that his consent to termination was based on his belief that a declaratory ruling would not be issued by DCF, this does not constitute a defense to the termination judgment he seeks to open.</block_quote>

<block_quote>  Having concluded that the respondent father has failed to demonstrate the existence of a good defense, this court need not address the second prong of the analysis. Furthermore, it should be noted that this court has not received any evidence to indicate that opening the judgment would be in the best interest of the child, which is a necessary consideration in order to open the judgment in accordance with General Statutes § <cross_reference>45a-719</cross_reference>. The respondent father's motion to open the judgment is, therefore, denied.</block_quote>

<italic>In re Samantha S., supra</italic>, 12155-56.

The plaintiff appealed from the denial of the motion to open judgment, and on or about August 26, 2008, filed a preliminary statement of issues with the Appellate Court. The issues were set forth as follows:

<block_quote>  1. Whether or not the trial court erred in its canvass and acceptance of the respondent father's consent;</block_quote>

<block_quote>  2. Whether or not the trial court erred in its findings that it would be in the best interests of the minor child to terminate parental rights;</block_quote>

<block_quote>  3. Whether or not the trial court erred in its denial of the respondent father's motion for continuance;</block_quote>

<block_quote>  4. Whether or not the trial court erred in its denial of the respondent father's motion to reopen the judgment; and</block_quote>

<block_quote>  5. Such other issues as become evident upon CT Page 17388 review of the transcripts and record.</block_quote>

On September 9, 2008, the defendant filed a motion to dismiss and alleged (1) the plaintiff lacks standing to bring this declaratory judgment action since he is not aggrieved; and (2) the relief that plaintiff seeks is not available to him pursuant to General Statutes § <cross_reference>4-175</cross_reference>.

On October 17, 2008, the plaintiff objected to the motion to dismiss. The plaintiff asserted that the court had subject matter jurisdiction over the matters raised by the plaintiff because (1) the plaintiff had appealed the decision of the trial court terminating his parental rights and its denial of his motion for a continuance of the trial and his motion to open the TPR judgment, and Appellate Court reversal of the trial court's judgment would restore the timeliness of the plaintiff's declaratory judgment request; (2) the plaintiff should have the benefit of the "capable of repetition yet evading review" exception to the mootness doctrine; and (3) the plaintiff should have the benefit of the collateral legal consequences exception to the mootness doctrine.

On October 29, 2008, the court heard argument on the motion to dismiss and the objection thereto.

From the issues raised and statements made in his objection it is clear that the plaintiff understands that he currently lacks standing<footnote_reference>[fn5]</footnote_reference> to proceed with the declaratory judgment case in this court, but he hopes that despite such lack of standing he can find a basis on which to continue to prosecute such matter.

The plaintiff lacks standing because at this time he has no legal right to force any contact between him and Samantha.<footnote_reference>[fn6]</footnote_reference> The Appellate Court has recently explained the concepts of standing and aggrievement:

<block_quote>  "[A] party must have standing to assert a claim in order for the court to have subject matter jurisdiction over the claim . . . Standing is the legal right to set judicial machinery in motion. One cannot rightfully invoke the jurisdiction of the court unless he has, in an individual or representative capacity, some real interest in the cause of action, or a legal or equitable right, title or interest in the subject matter of the controversy . . . [Our Supreme Court] has often stated that the question of subject matter jurisdiction, because it addresses the basic CT Page 17389 competency of the court, can be raised by any of the parties, or by the court sua sponte, at any time . . . [T]he court has a duty to dismiss, even on its own initiative, any appeal that it lacks jurisdiction to hear . . . Moreover, [t]he parties cannot confer subject matter jurisdiction on the court, either by waiver or by consent . . . Standing . . . is not a technical rule intended to keep aggrieved parties out of court; nor is it a test of substantive rights. Rather it is a practical concept designed to ensure that courts and parties are not vexed by suits brought to vindicate non-justiciable interests and that judicial decisions which may affect the rights of others are forged in hot controversy, with each view fairly and vigorously represented." (Citations omitted; internal quotation marks omitted.) <italic>Webster Bank v. Zak</italic>, <cross_reference>259 Conn. 766</cross_reference>,  <cross_reference>774</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>792 A.2d 66</cross_reference> (2002). "Where a party is found to lack standing, the court is consequently without subject matter jurisdiction to determine the cause." (Internal quotation marks omitted.)  <italic>Blakeney v. Commissioner of Correction</italic>,  <cross_reference>47 Conn.App. 568</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>574</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>706 A.2d 989</cross_reference>, cert. denied,  <cross_reference>244 Conn. 913</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>713 A.2d 830</cross_reference> (1998). Our review of the question of the plaintiff's standing is plenary. See <italic>West Farms Mall, LLC v. West</italic> <italic>Hartford</italic>, <cross_reference>279 Conn. 1</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>12</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>901 A.2d 649</cross_reference> (2006).</block_quote>

<block_quote>  "To be entitled to invoke the judicial process, a party must have suffered an aggrievement."  <italic>Kelly v. Dearington</italic>, <cross_reference>23 Conn.App. 657</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>660</cross_reference>,  <cross_reference>583 A.2d 937</cross_reference> (1990). "Two broad yet distinct categories of aggrievement exist, classical and statutory . . . Classical aggrievement requires a two part showing. First, a party must demonstrate a specific, personal and legal interest in the subject matter of the [controversy], as opposed to a general interest that all members of the community share . . . Second, the party must also show that the [alleged conduct] has specially and injuriously affected that specific personal or legal interest . . . Statutory aggrievement . . . exists by legislative fiat, not by judicial analysis of the particular facts of the case. In CT Page 17390 other words, in cases of statutory aggrievement, particular legislation grants standing to those who claim injury to an interest protected by that legislation." (Internal quotation marks omitted.)  <italic>McWeeny v. Hartford</italic>, <cross_reference>287 Conn. 56</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>64-65</cross_reference>,  <cross_reference>946 A.2d 862</cross_reference> (2008) . . .</block_quote>

<italic>Lewis v. Slack</italic>, <cross_reference>110 Conn.App. 641</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>643-44</cross_reference> (2008). The plaintiff currently has no right to the relief he seeks to have declared, and he is not classically or statutorily aggrieved. <italic>Lewis v. Slack</italic>,<italic>supra</italic>, <cross_reference>110 Conn.App. at 644-47</cross_reference>.

The plaintiff has referred to two statutes in support of his claim for declaratory relief. General Statutes § <cross_reference>17a-112</cross_reference>(b) provides as follows:

<block_quote>  Either or both birth parents and an intended adoptive parent may enter into a cooperative postadoption agreement regarding communication or contact between either or both birth parents and the adopted child. Such an agreement may be entered into if (1) The child is in the custody of the Department of Children and Families; (2) an order terminating parental rights has not yet been entered; and (3) either or both birth parents agree to a voluntary termination of parental rights, including an agreement in a case which began as an involuntary termination of parental rights. The postadoption agreement shall be applicable only to a birth parent who is a party to the agreement. Such agreement shall be in addition to those under common law. Counsel for the child and any guardian ad litem for the child may be heard on the proposed cooperative postadoption agreement. There shall be no presumption of communication or contact between the birth parents and an intended adoptive parent in the absence of a cooperative postadoption agreement.</block_quote>

The first line contains the word "may" instead of "shall," and the common interpretation of "may" is that an act is permitted but not required:

<block_quote>  We consistently have observed that, "as opposed to definitive words, such as must or shall, which CT Page 17391 ordinarily express legislative mandates of a nondirectory nature . . . the word may [generally] imports permissive conduct and the conferral of discretion." (Citation omitted; internal quotation marks omitted.) <italic>State v.</italic> <italic>Bletsch</italic>, <italic>supra</italic>, <cross_reference>281 Conn. 17</cross_reference>; see also  <italic>id.</italic>, 18 ("may" is construed as directory "[o]nly when the context of legislation permits such an interpretation and if the interpretation is necessary to make a legislative enactment effective").</block_quote>

<italic>State v. Arthur H.</italic>, <cross_reference>288 Conn. 582</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>591</cross_reference> (2008).

In the circumstances of this case, an order terminating the father's parental rights was entered by the court upon the father's voluntary agreement on May 14, 2008. In the absence of a cooperative post-adoption agreement between the father and the foster parents, the General Assembly has determined that there "shall be no presumption of communication or contact between the birth parents and an intended adoptive parent." General Statutes § <cross_reference>17a-112</cross_reference>(b). Such statute does not provide to the father any current basis for classical or statutory aggrievement.

The second statute referred to by the father, General Statutes § <cross_reference>46b-129</cross_reference>(k)(4), provides as follows:

<block_quote>  If the court approves the permanency plan of adoption: (A) The Commissioner of Children and Families shall file a petition for termination of parental rights not later than sixty days after such approval if such petition has not previously been filed; (B) the commissioner may conduct a thorough adoption assessment and  <italic>child-specific recruitment</italic>; and (C) the court may order that the child be photo-listed within thirty days if the court determines that such photo-listing is in the best interest of the child. As used in this subdivision, "thorough adoption assessment" means conducting and documenting face-to-face interviews with the child, foster care providers and other significant parties and "<italic>child specific</italic> <italic>recruitment</italic>" <italic>means recruiting an adoptive</italic> <italic>placement targeted to meet the individual needs</italic><italic>CT Page 17392</italic> <italic>of the specific child</italic>, including, but not limited to, use of the media, use of photo-listing services and any other in-state or out-of-state resources that may be used to meet the specific needs of the child, unless there are extenuating circumstances that indicate that such efforts are not in the best interest of the child.</block_quote>

(Emphasis added.) Since Samantha is already with a pre-adoptive family, this subsection does not seem to be relevant to her current circumstances. In any event, the statutory language is clear: the child specific recruitment for purposes of adoption is based on the individual needs of the specific child, and not on the needs, wishes or hopes of a biological parent. Such statute does not provide to the father any current basis for classical or statutory aggrievement.

<block_quote>  As set forth above, General Statutes § <cross_reference>4-175</cross_reference>(a)(2) provides in part as follows: (a) If a provision of the general statutes, a regulation or a final decision, or its threatened application, <italic>interferes with or impairs, or</italic> <italic>threatens to interfere with or impair, the legal</italic> <italic>rights or privileges of the plaintiff</italic> . . . the petitioner may seek in the Superior Court a declaratory judgment as to the validity of the regulation in question or the applicability of the provision of the general statutes, the regulation or the final decision in question to specified circumstances. The agency shall be made a party to the action.</block_quote>

(Emphasis added.) As set forth above, the plaintiff no longer has legal rights or privileges that are being interfered with, since those rights were terminated based on the father's knowing, voluntary and intelligent consent during the second day of trial on May 14, 2008. Such statute does not provide to the father any current basis for classical or statutory aggrievement.

The plaintiff argues that although he has no standing he can proceed as a surrogate because the issue of an administrative declaratory judgment proceeding not being resolved before a TPR trial is "capable of repetition, yet evading review." In <italic>Dutkiewicz v. Dutkiewicz</italic>, 289 Conn. (October 28, 2008), the Supreme Court discussed this exception to the mootness doctrine:

CT Page 17393

<block_quote>  The mootness doctrine does not preclude a court from addressing an issue that is "capable of repetition, yet evading review." <italic>Loisel v.</italic> <italic>Rowe</italic>, <cross_reference>233 Conn. 370</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>378</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>660 A.2d 323</cross_reference> (1995). "[F]or an otherwise moot question to qualify for review under the capable of repetition, yet evading review exception, it must meet three requirements. First, the challenged action, or the effect of the challenged action, by its very nature must be of a limited duration so that there is a strong likelihood that the substantial majority of cases raising a question about its validity will become moot before appellate litigation can be concluded. Second, there must be a reasonable likelihood that the question presented in the pending case will arise again in the future, and that it will affect either the same complaining party or a reasonably identifiable group for whom that party can be said to act as surrogate. Third, the question must have some public importance. Unless all three requirements are met, the appeal must be dismissed as moot." (Internal quotation marks omitted.) <italic>Id.</italic>, 382-83. We discuss these three requirements in turn.</block_quote>

<block_quote>  The first requirement is that the challenged action "must be of a limited duration so that there is a strong likelihood that the substantial majority of cases raising a question about its validity will become moot before appellate litigation can be concluded." <italic>Id.</italic>, 382. As we stated in <italic>Loisel</italic>, a party typically satisfies this prong if there exists a "functionally insurmountable time [constraint]." <italic>Id.</italic>, 383 . . .</block_quote>

<block_quote>  "Second, there must be a reasonable likelihood that the question presented in the pending case will arise again in the future, and that it will affect either the same complaining party or a reasonably identifiable group for whom that party can be said to act as surrogate." <italic>Loisel v. Rowe,</italic> <italic>supra</italic>, <cross_reference>233 Conn. 382</cross_reference>. "This analysis entails two separate inquiries: (1) whether the question presented will recur at all; and (2) whether the CT Page 17394 interests of the people likely to be affected by the question presented are adequately represented in the current litigation." <italic>Id.</italic>, 384 . . .</block_quote>

<block_quote>  ****</block_quote>

<block_quote>  Third, the claim must have some public importance. "The requirement of public importance is largely self explanatory." <italic>Id.</italic> "Consideration of the importance of the issue represents a sound means for distinguishing those cases that should be reviewed and those that should not."  <italic>Id.</italic> In <italic>Roth v. Weston</italic>, <cross_reference>259 Conn. 202</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>216</cross_reference>,  <cross_reference>789 A.2d 431</cross_reference> (2002), we recognized that "parents' interest in the care, custody and control of their children, [i]s `perhaps the oldest of the fundamental liberty interests recognized by [the Supreme] Court.' <italic>Troxel v. Granville</italic>, [<cross_reference>530 U.S. 57</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>65</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>120 S.Ct. 2054</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>147 L.Ed.2d 49</cross_reference> (2000)].</block_quote>

As to the first requirement, unlike in the <italic>Dutkiewicz</italic> case, where there was a sixty-day window for the parenting classes at issue, and because of the applicable statute, General Statutes § <cross_reference>46b-69</cross_reference>, there would always be such a sixty-day window (at least until the statute was repealed or the time period was modified), in this matter the plaintiff's decision to seek administrative declaratory relief and the timing of it were in the sole control of the plaintiff without any statutory time constraint. The plaintiff's delay in the filing of such administrative petition for declaratory relief until approximately sixty days before the previously scheduled first trial date in this matter was the decision of the plaintiff and was not determined by any statutory requirement or prescription. In most TPR cases (assuming arguendo that a parent has to wait for the filing of a TPR case against her or him in order to file a petition seeking declaratory relief similar to those filed by the plaintiff in this matter) several months if not more than a year will pass between the filing of a TPR petition and the trial thereof. Thus, there is no functionally insurmountable time constraint between the filing of a TPR petition and the court's decision after the trial thereof that would prevent the filing of such a petition for an administrative ruling and a DCF decision thereon. Thus, this matter is not "capable of repetition, yet evading review."

The plaintiff also claims that the "collateral consequences" exception to the mootness doctrine is also applicable. Such exception to mootness has been recently explained by the Appellate Court in <italic>Iacurci v.</italic><italic>CT Page 17395</italic><italic>Wells</italic>, <cross_reference>108 Conn.App. 274</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>276-77</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>947 A.2d 1034</cross_reference> (2008) (footnotes omitted):

<block_quote>  Before we can reach the merits of the defendants' appeal, we first must determine whether the case has been rendered moot because the defendants are no longer in possession of the leased property. "Mootness is a threshold issue that implicates subject matter jurisdiction, which imposes a duty on the court to dismiss a case if the court can no longer grant practical relief to the parties . . . Mootness presents a circumstance wherein the issue before the court has been resolved or had lost its significance because of a change in the condition of affairs between the parties . . . [T]he existence of an actual controversy is an essential requisite to appellate jurisdiction; it is not the province of appellate courts to decide moot questions, disconnected from the granting of actual relief or from the determination of which no practical relief can follow." (Internal quotation marks omitted.)  <italic>Wilcox v. Ferraina</italic>, <cross_reference>100 Conn.App. 541</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>547-48</cross_reference>,  <cross_reference>920 A.2d 316</cross_reference> (2007). "We have consistently held that an appeal from a summary process judgment becomes moot where, at the time of the appeal, the defendant is no longer in possession of the premises." (Internal quotation marks omitted.)  <italic>Cheshire v. Lewis</italic>, <cross_reference>75 Conn.App. 892</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>893</cross_reference>,  <cross_reference>817 A.2d 1277</cross_reference>, cert. denied, <cross_reference>264 Conn. 905</cross_reference>,  <cross_reference>826 A.2d 177</cross_reference> (2003). "Our Supreme Court, however, has allowed us to retain jurisdiction where the matter being appealed creates collateral consequences prejudicial to the interests of the appellant, even though developments during the pendency of the appeal would otherwise render it moot." (Internal quotation marks omitted.)  <italic>Wilcox v. Ferraina, supra</italic>, 548.</block_quote>

<block_quote>  "[T]o invoke successfully the collateral consequences doctrine, the litigant must show that there is a reasonable possibility that prejudicial collateral consequences will occur. Accordingly, the litigant must establish these consequences by more than mere conjecture, but CT Page 17396 need not demonstrate that these consequences are more probable than not. This standard provides the necessary limitations on justiciability underlying the mootness doctrine itself. Whe[n] there is no direct practical relief available from the reversal of the judgment . . . the collateral consequences doctrine acts as a surrogate, calling for a determination whether a decision in the case can afford the litigant some practical relief in the future." (Internal quotation marks omitted.) <italic>Smith Lawler v.</italic> <italic>Lawler</italic>, <cross_reference>97 Conn.App. 376</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>380</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>904 A.2d 1235</cross_reference>
(2006).</block_quote>

In <italic>In re Claudia F.</italic>, <cross_reference>93 Conn.App. 343</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>888 A.2d 1138</cross_reference> (2006), cert. denied, <cross_reference>277 Conn. 924</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>895 A.2d 796</cross_reference> (2006), the respondent's voluntary termination of her parental rights rendered her appeal moot. The mother conceded that resolution of her appeal could provide her with no practical relief but she argued that the Appellate Court should still decide her appeal because of the collateral consequences exception to mootness doctrine. <italic>Id.</italic>, 346-47. The Appellate Court distinguished a Supreme Court decision cited by the plaintiff in support of his position in this matter:

<block_quote>  The respondent relies heavily on <italic>Williams v.</italic> <italic>Ragalia</italic>, <cross_reference>261 Conn. 219</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>802 A.2d 778</cross_reference> (2002), to support her claim of collateral consequences. That case is distinguishable from the present case. <italic>Williams</italic> involved an appeal from a decision by the commissioner revoking the plaintiff's special study foster care license. Although the plaintiff adopted the children for whom the license had been granted, our Supreme Court held that the appeal from the revocation of the license was not moot due to the totality of the possible consequences, namely, that the plaintiff would want to become a foster parent at some time in the future and the revocation would be held against her in subsequent proceedings. The court reasoned that the revocation of a foster care license for cause stigmatizes the plaintiff as having been found to be an unfit caregiver. Such a finding directly implicates the holder of the license, whereas in this case, a finding of neglect is not directed against the parents. See CT Page 17397  <italic>In re Elisabeth H.</italic>, <italic>supra</italic>, <cross_reference>45 Conn.App. 512</cross_reference>.</block_quote>

<italic>Id.</italic>, 347-48.

In this case, the plaintiff is asking the court not to dismiss the complaint for declaratory relief based on the plaintiff's hope that despite his knowing, voluntary and intelligent consent to the termination of his parental rights during the course of a trial, thus stopping the court, DCF and the child from proceeding with such trial, the Appellate Court is going to reverse the trial court's denial of his motion to open the judgment after it has rejected the arguments being made by the plaintiff concerning the meaning of the statutes cited by the plaintiff in support of his open adoption arguments. See <italic>In re</italic><italic>Devaun J.</italic>, <cross_reference>109 Conn.App. 832</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>838-40</cross_reference> (August 26, 2008).<footnote_reference>[fn7]</footnote_reference> The plaintiff is thus asking the court to speculate that the pending appeal will be resolved in his favor:

<block_quote>  By not dismissing this complaint, and hearing it on its merits, the Court will afford the plaintiff some practical relief in the future based on the collateral consequences doctrine. The plaintiff has filed an appeal based on underlying issues pertaining to open adoptions. If the plaintiff achieves an appellate result of reversal, this court's favorable ruling on his complaint for a declaratory judgment will afford the plaintiff some practical relief in the future.</block_quote>

Plaintiff's memorandum of law in support of objection to motion to dismiss, 16.

By asking the court to speculate about the result of the pending appeal, the plaintiff is asking the court to ignore the ruling of the Appellate Court in <italic>In re Selena O.</italic>, <cross_reference>104 Conn.App. 635</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>647</cross_reference> (2007):

<block_quote>  In its oral decision, the court found on September 27, 2006, that the respondent had completed nine months of the Coventry House program, from January to September 2006. On the basis of our review of the evidence, we conclude that there is no evidence to support a finding that the respondent entered the program in January 2006. She therefore could not have completed nine months of the program in September CT Page 17398 2006.</block_quote>

<block_quote>  Furthermore, without evidence that the respondent continued to comply with the Coventry House program beyond March 2006, the court's conclusion that the respondent was still participating in the program in September 2006, and would complete the program in three months was based on pure speculation. This clearly erroneous finding was central to the court's conclusion that the respondent could achieve rehabilitation.</block_quote>

Unlike the situation in the <italic>Williams</italic> case, involving a pending appeal to the Appellate Court from a decision by the commissioner revoking the plaintiff's special study foster care license, if the plaintiff in this matter is successful in his appeal, and if the open adoption statutory interpretation and alleged mandates he seeks to raise have not been foreclosed by the <italic>Devaun J.</italic> decision or any future court decision, which higher court decision(s) are binding on this court and on DCF in the exercise of its administrative functions, then the plaintiff can seek another administrative ruling when he has standing to obtain such a ruling and his alleged right to seek such a ruling have properly ripened:

<block_quote>  "The basic rationale [of the ripeness doctrine] is to prevent the courts, through avoidance of premature adjudication, from entangling themselves in abstract disagreements." (Internal quotation marks omitted.) <italic>Forcier v. Sunnydale</italic> <italic>Developers, LLC</italic>, <cross_reference>84 Conn.App. 858</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>865</cross_reference>,  <cross_reference>856 A.2d 416</cross_reference> (2004).</block_quote>

<italic>Rosenfield v. David Marder  Associates</italic>, <cross_reference>110 Conn.App. 679</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>687</cross_reference> (2008).

Because the plaintiff currently has no standing to pursue the pending declaratory judgment proceeding that he has filed, and because none of the exceptions to mootness advanced by the plaintiff are applicable, the plaintiff's complaint is dismissed.

</unpublished></opinion_text><unpublished><footnote_body><footnote_number>[fn1]</footnote_number> This and many other facts set forth herein and accepted for the purpose of the pending motion to dismiss and the objection thereto are alleged by plaintiff in his complaint for declaratory judgment and/or the documents annexed thereto, and they are primarily chronological in nature. The court has taken judicial notice of Judge Wilson's decision denying the father's motion to open judgment and other non-contested CT Page 17399 facts.</footnote_body>

<footnote_body><footnote_number>[fn2]</footnote_number> Forcing a foster or pre-adoptive parent to consult with a specific lawyer provided by a specific agency as a condition of adoption and directing such person to explore specific topics with such lawyer is contrary to the traditional lawyer/client relationship and a violation of such person's right to decide whether he or she wishes to consult a lawyer, and, if so, which lawyer to consult. See, e. g., Rule of Professional Conduct 1.2:

<block_quote>  (a) Subject to subsections (c) and (d), a lawyer shall abide by a client's decisions concerning the objectives of representation and, as required by Rule 1.4, shall consult with the client as to the means by which they are to be pursued. A lawyer may take such action on behalf of the client as is impliedly authorized to carry out the representation. A lawyer shall abide by a client's decision whether to settle a matter . . .</block_quote>

<block_quote>  The comment to such Rule contains the following:</block_quote>

<block_quote>  Allocation of Authority between Client and Lawyer. Subsection (a) confers upon the client the ultimate authority to determine the purposes to be served by legal representation, within the limits imposed by law and the lawyer's professional obligations. The decisions specified in subsection (a), such as whether to settle a civil matter, must also be made by the client. See Rule 1.4(a)(1) for the lawyer's duty to communicate with the client about such decisions. With respect to the means by which the client's objectives are to be pursued, the lawyer shall consult with the client as required by Rule 1.4(a)(2) and may take such action as is impliedly authorized to carry out the representation.</block_quote>

<block_quote>  ***</block_quote>

<block_quote>  All agreements concerning a lawyer's representation of a client must accord with the Rules of Professional Conduct and other law. See, CT Page 17400 e.g., Rules 1.1, 1.8 and 5.6.</block_quote>

The commentary to Rule 1.16 contains the following concerning the client's right to end the attorney/client relationship, a right seemingly contradicted by the plaintiff's above-stated alleged mandate to exclude those persons who refuse to work with and be guided by an attorney from a specific foster parent organization:

Discharge. A client has a right to discharge a lawyer at any time, with or without cause . . .</footnote_body>

<footnote_body><footnote_number>[fn3]</footnote_number> General Statutes § <cross_reference>4-175</cross_reference>(a) provides:

<block_quote>  (a) If a provision of the general statutes, a regulation or a final decision, or its threatened application, interferes with or impairs, or threatens to interfere with or impair, the legal rights or privileges of the plaintiff and if an agency (1) does not take an action required by subdivision (1), (2) or (3) of subsection (e) of section <cross_reference>4-176</cross_reference>, within sixty days of the filing of a petition for a declaratory ruling, (2) decides not to issue a declaratory ruling under subdivision (4) or (5) of subsection (e) of said section <cross_reference>4-176</cross_reference>, or (3) is deemed to have decided not to issue a declaratory ruling under subsection (i) of said section <cross_reference>4-176</cross_reference>, the petitioner may seek in the Superior Court a declaratory judgment as to the validity of the regulation in question or the applicability of the provision of the general statutes, the regulation or the final decision in question to specified circumstances. The agency shall be made a party to the action.</block_quote></footnote_body>

<footnote_body><footnote_number>[fn4]</footnote_number> General Statutes § <cross_reference>4-176</cross_reference>(e) provides in part:

(e) Within sixty days after receipt of a petition for a declaratory ruling, an agency in writing shall: . . . (5) decide not to issue a declaratory ruling, stating the reasons for its action.</footnote_body>

<footnote_body><footnote_number>[fn5]</footnote_number> The father's parental rights have been terminated. A TPR judgment is a final judgment and there is no automatic stay of it currently in effect. See Practice Book § <cross_reference>61-11</cross_reference>:

CT Page 17401

<block_quote>  (b) Matters in which no automatic stay is available under this rule</block_quote>

<block_quote>  Under this section, there shall be no automatic stay in actions concerning attorneys pursuant to chapter 2 of these rules, in juvenile matters brought pursuant to chapters 26 through 35a . . .</block_quote>

Even if this court were to grant the declaratory relief the father is seeking, such relief would not undo the effect of the termination of his parental rights, or restore any such rights, which issues are the subject of the appeal to the Appellate Court and thus cannot be addressed by this court while such appeal is pending.</footnote_body>

<footnote_body><footnote_number>[fn6]</footnote_number> As long as DCF is statutory parent of Samantha, it can decide to permit the father's direct or indirect contact with Samantha. If Samantha is adopted, DCF will cease to be her statutory parent. As set forth in General Statutes <cross_reference>17a-93</cross_reference>(f):

<block_quote>  "Statutory parent" means the Commissioner of Children and Families or that child-placing agency appointed by the court for the purpose of giving a minor child or minor children in adoption . . .</block_quote>

<block_quote>  General Statutes <cross_reference>17a-112</cross_reference>(m) provides:</block_quote>

<block_quote>  . . . The Superior Court may appoint a statutory parent at any time after it has terminated parental rights if the petitioner so requests.</block_quote></footnote_body>

<footnote_body><footnote_number>[fn7]</footnote_number> The counsel for the plaintiff in this matter was the counsel for the respondent biological mother in <italic>Devaun J.</italic> Such attorney did not refer to such decision either in her October 17, 2008, memorandum of law in support of objection to motion to dismiss or in the October 29, 2008, oral argument until the decision was mentioned by the court.</footnote_body>

CT Page 17402

</unpublished>
</opinion>