<opinion unpublished=true>
<reporter_caption><center>TOROS v. KAPRAL, No. CV98 0062621S (Aug. 21, 2003)</center></reporter_caption>
<caption><center>MELISSA TOROS v. JOAN KAPRAL.</center></caption>
<citation_line><center><citation>2003 Ct. Sup. 10101</citation></center></citation_line>
<docket><center>No. CV98 0062621S</center></docket><court><center>Connecticut Superior Court, Judicial District of Ansonia-Milford</center><center>Geographic Area #5 at Derby.</center></court>
<date><center>August 21, 2003</center>

</date>
<opinion_text><unpublished><footnote_body>[EDITOR'S NOTE: This case is unpublished as indicated by the issuing court.]</footnote_body><center>       MEMORANDUM OF DECISION ON DEFENDANT'S MOTION FOR COLLATERAL SOURCE HEARING</center></unpublished></opinion_text>
<opinion_byline><unpublished>  NADEAU, JUDGE.

</unpublished></opinion_byline>
<opinion_text><unpublished>  The defendant's motion, dated August 14, 2003 and filed August 18, 2003, is denied without prejudice.

First, the motion is replete with errors which are probably merely typographical but which affect clarity.

The parties should note that this court has taken a position on one of the issues to which defendant alludes. Where a plaintiff puts before a jury a bill in the amount of 100% of what the treater sought, and apparently receives said amount from the verdict, the court subtracts the 100% as a collateral source despite that the doctor actually received a lesser amount and had no further recourse against the patient. This prospective "ruling" is proffered to the extent that it might illuminate the situation the parties face.

The parties are also ordered to provide each other <italic>forthwith</italic> with the discovery sought. No hearing will be held until discovery is completed and a party is able to articulate the issue (s) needed to be resolved. Of course, if a discovery request is refused, a hearing may be necessary or a ruling, with possible sanctions, may be possible.

In any event, the court can do no more at this point given the state of the information needed and the condition of defendant's memorandum.

The Court

By Nadeau, J. CT Page 10102

</unpublished></opinion_text>
</opinion>