<opinion unpublished=true>
<reporter_caption><center>STANNARD v. D'ANDREA, No. CV-05-4007111S (Jun. 4, 2008)</center></reporter_caption>
<caption><center>LUCIAN STANNARD ET AL. v. DANIEL N. D'ANDREA ET AL.</center></caption>
<citation_line><center><citation>2008 Ct. Sup. 9139</citation>, <citation>45 CLR 585</citation></center></citation_line>
<docket><center>No. CV-05-4007111S</center></docket><court><center>Connecticut Superior Court</center><center>Judicial District of Waterbury at Waterbury</center></court>
<date><center>June 4, 2008</center>

</date>
<opinion_text><unpublished><footnote_body>[EDITOR'S NOTE: This case is unpublished as indicated by the issuing court.]</footnote_body><center>                         <italic>MEMORANDUM OF DECISION</italic></center></unpublished></opinion_text>
<opinion_byline><unpublished>  ROCHE, J.

</unpublished></opinion_byline>
<opinion_text><unpublished>  This is a claim involving the death of a 22-year-old young man on a motorcycle at an intersection of South Main Street and Flatts Mill Road on the Waterbury-Naugatuck town line. The City of Waterbury as well as the defendant driver are named defendants. The City of Waterbury was named because the defendant driver Daniel D'Andrea had left work early as a City employee and admitted to consuming alcohol and using drugs (marijuana) between the hours of 3:00 p.m. and 6:30 p.m. leading up to the accident. There was a criminal prosecution of the defendant driver and he was sentenced to prison for a period of three years plus. The plaintiff attempted to hold the City in the case under the <italic>Shore v.</italic><italic>Stonington</italic>, <cross_reference>187 Conn. 147</cross_reference> (1982), case and its progeny. The City was released towards the end of evidence from the case leaving the defendant driver as the sole defendant in this matter.

This was an intersection type accident in which the plaintiff decedent was on a motorcycle traveling at an unascertained speed and collided with the right side of the defendant's personal pickup truck. The defendant was not driving a City vehicle, nor did he have permission to leave work early or obviously consume any alcohol or drugs during that period leading up to the accident which occurred on August 15, 2003 at approximately 6:30 p.m. Weather and lighting conditions were not factors, and the three-way intersection is controlled by a red/green traffic signal, which was functioning properly. The defendant driver attempted to make a left hand turn at the traffic signal after going around on the right side of a stopped vehicle. The defendant's vehicle was impacted by the plaintiffs' decedent who survived the impact for 10 to 15 minutes before being removed by ambulance to the nearby hospital where he expired.

Although the defendant driver does not admit liability and pled nolo contendere to the criminal charges, the defense counsel implicitly conceded liability and in effect left it up to the court to determine the amount of damages that should be awarded to the estate of the CT Page 9140 decedent.

As difficult as it is to evaluate the value of a young life that has unknown and immeasurable potential, nonetheless a certain level of objectivity must be brought to the analysis. The decedent had a life expectancy of 54 years, was trained in motorcycle mechanics and repair which he was doing on a full-time/part-time basis. He was a high school graduate who had had some training and schooling in motorcycle repair and was attempting to set up a separate business of his own involving such mechanics. There was no evidence of actual earnings or any projected future earnings. His mother and father were the named administrators of the estate and testified concerning the loss of their son.

There is no magic formula for evaluating the life of a young person regardless of his potential earning power or lack thereof. The plaintiff's counsel argued for a certain amount and defense counsel conceded a certain amount in final argument upon which the court places some reliance. The fact that the decedent survived for a period of time, approximately 10 to 15 minutes after the impact with the defendant's vehicle, allows the court to award some amount for the pain and suffering that was endured by the plaintiffs' decedent leading up to his death. This evaluation of an intangible cannot be quantified or measured with any absolute objectivity and yet the court will award an amount that recognizes, but never compensates for such a loss. The court finds that a fair, just and reasonable amount for that period of pain and suffering leading up to the decedent's death to be $150,000.

The further analysis that the court must render involves the determination of what monetary value can be assigned to a life not lived and to those unrealized joys, pleasures and accomplishments that may have accrued to a 22-year-old who had a life expectancy of 54 years. Any such measurement of a future life is beyond the usual powers of any court. However, the duty has devolved on this court after trial to establish a future value for the plaintiffs' decedent based on that life expectancy and good faith appraisal of such life at $15,000 per year resulting in an award of $810,000 for those unrealized years that were foreclosed and shortened by this tragic incident. The court further awards the actual out-of-pocket economic loss to the administrators in the amount of $10,286 as submitted in evidence. Based on the best available and more credible evidence, this court, therefore, finds a total judgment as fair, just and reasonable in favor of the plaintiffs/administrators of the decedent's estate in the amount of $970,286 as final judgment.

CT Page 9141

</unpublished></opinion_text>
</opinion>