<opinion unpublished=true>
<reporter_caption><center>PERROTTI v. ST. JOHN, No. CV 05-5000443 S (Sep. 9, 2008)</center></reporter_caption>
<caption><center>NEIL PERROTTI v. EDWARD ST. JOHN.</center></caption>
<citation_line><center><citation>2008 Ct. Sup. 14582</citation></center></citation_line>
<docket><center>No. CV 05-5000443 S</center></docket><court><center>Connecticut Superior Court</center><center>Judicial District of Waterbury at Waterbury</center></court>
<date><center>September 9, 2008</center>

</date>
<opinion_text><unpublished><footnote_body>[EDITOR'S NOTE: This case is unpublished as indicated by the issuing court.]</footnote_body><center>                           <italic>MEMORANDUM OF DECISION</italic></center></unpublished></opinion_text>
<opinion_byline><unpublished>  JANE S. SCHOLL, J.

</unpublished></opinion_byline>
<opinion_text><unpublished><center>                                <italic>Introduction</italic></center>
The Plaintiff Neil Perrotti, makes the following allegations in his complaint dated October 21, 2005: In the summer of 1987, <footnote_reference>[fn1]</footnote_reference> when he was 17 years old, he was a member of the Middlebury Junior Fire Department and in late July the Defendant, Edward B. St. John, who was the First Selectman of the Town of Middlebury, invited him and several other Middlebury Junior Firefighters also minors, to accompany him to a cottage in Rhode Island. <italic>Complaint, Paragraphs 3, 4</italic>. While at the cottage St. John provided him and the other minors with quantities of alcohol and beer, <italic>Complaint, Paragraph 4</italic>. As the drinking continued, St. John urged the boys to disrobe and engage in "streaking" inside the cottage.<italic>Complaint, Paragraph 4</italic>. As the night progressed, St. John provided the boys with increasing quantities of beer and alcohol and continued to press them to disrobe and by then he had persuaded Perrotti to strip to his underwear. <italic>Complaint, Paragraph 5</italic>. St. John told Perrotti he wanted him to "streak" with an erection and instructed him to masturbate until he was fully erect. <italic>Complaint Paragraph 5</italic>. Although Perrotti protested he was too intoxicated to do so, St. John insisted and persuaded him to remove his underwear and St. John also removed all his own clothing.<italic>Complaint, Paragraph 5</italic>. St. John then began masturbating both himself and Perrotti and, although Perrotti objected, St. John continued. <italic>Complaint,</italic><italic>Paragraph 6</italic>. Eventually Perrotti ejaculated and then fled from the area and hid elsewhere in the cottage. <italic>Complaint, Paragraph 6</italic>. The following week St. John telephoned Perrotti and told him he thought his parents would be very upset "if they knew how bad we were in Rhode Island."<italic>Complaint, Paragraph.</italic> Perrotti claims that as a result he has suffered severe emotional distress. <italic>Complaint, Paragraph</italic>.

Trial on this matter was held on April 8th, 9th, 10th, 15th and 22nd, 2008. At that time the court heard testimony from the Defendant, Edward St. John, the former First Selectman of the Town of Middlebury; Ralph Carpinella, a Middlebury resident who ran against the Defendant in 2005; CT Page 14583 the Plaintiff, Neil Perrotti; Francis Brennan, the Defendant's 2005 campaign manager; Tara Perrotti the Plaintiff's wife; Paul Perrotti, the Plaintiff's brother and the Fire Chief of Middlebury; Anthony Perrotti, Jr., the Plaintiff's brother; William Nicholas Perrotti, the Plaintiff's brother and the owner of a restaurant in Middlebury; William Calabrese, whose sister is married to Paul Perrotti; Brett Kales, a good friend of the Plaintiff; David Anthony Lenkowski, a Middlebury businessman who has members of the Perrotti family as customers; Joseph Arnson, a friend and former roommate of the Plaintiff; Rebecca Estrella, the Plaintiff's girlfriend; Patrick J. Bona, the former Chief of Police of Middlebury and a recent political opponent of the Defendant; Monika Foss, a friend of the Defendant; David Desmarais, a public works employee of Middlebury and a friend of the Plaintiff; Pat Deangelis, a Middlebury resident who at times has been critical of both Paul Perrotti and the Defendant; and Thomas Christopher King, Monica Foss' brother and a friend of the Defendant.

Both parties submitted post-trial briefs on August 11th.

<center>                              <italic>Burden of Proof</italic></center>
The Plaintiff has the burden of proving his claims by a preponderance of the evidence. This means that "in an ordinary civil action the party upon whom rests the burden of proof as to a fact of issue has sustained that burden if the evidence, considered fairly, induces in the trier's mind reasonable belief that it is more probable than otherwise that the fact or issue is true." (Quotation marks and citations omitted.)<italic>Holmes v. Holmes</italic>, <cross_reference>32 Conn.App. 317</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>318</cross_reference>, cert. denied, <cross_reference>228 Conn. 902</cross_reference>
(1983).

<center>                                 <italic>Discussion</italic></center>
Certain facts alleged by the Plaintiff in his complaint have been admitted by the Defendant. They are: The Plaintiff is an adult citizen of the United States who resides in Middlebury, Connecticut. He was born on October 24, 1969. The Defendant is an adult citizen of the United States who resides in Middlebury, Connecticut. At all times mentioned in the complaint he was the First Selectman of the Town of Middlebury.

As to the remaining allegations of the Plaintiff's complaint, the court is called upon to determine the truth of very serious and disturbing allegations which concern activities that are alleged to have taken place over twenty years ago. The only evidence in support and in opposition to these claims is testimonial. Even here the court has no testimony from an unbiased or disinterested third party. Except for Pat Deangelis, who CT Page 14584 appears to have been critical of persons related to both sides, all the other witnesses in this case were aligned, either by politics or family relationships or friendships, with one side or the other. The court, as the trier of fact and the one charged with the determination of the credibility of the witnesses in determining whether the allegations of the complaint have been proven, must consider the respective allegiances of each witness. As the Plaintiff admits, "[t]his case hinges on the credibility of the witnesses." <italic>Plaintiff's Post-Trial Brief p. 10.</italic>

"It is well established that in cases tried before courts, trial judges are the sole arbiters of the credibility of witnesses and it is they who determine the weight to be given specific testimony." <italic>Re</italic><italic>Antonio M.</italic>, <cross_reference>56 Conn.App. 534</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>540</cross_reference> (2000).

Much evidence was offered regarding the Defendant's reputation for truthfulness. Although the Defendant himself may have been, at times in the past, less then truthful, and his memory for some of the basic details of his life, such as where he graduated from college, less than clear, the Defendant had no burden to disprove the Plaintiff's allegations. The issue is not the strength and credibility of the Defendant's denials but of the evidence supporting the Plaintiff's claims. "While a plaintiff is entitled to every favorable inference that may be legitimately drawn from the evidence and has the same right to submit a weak case as a strong one, the plaintiff must still sustain the burden of proof on the contested issues in the complaint and the defendant need not present any evidence to contradict it . . . The general burden of proof in civil actions is on the plaintiff, who must prove all the essential allegations of the complaint. (Citations omitted.)<italic>Gulycz v. Stop  Shop Cos.</italic>, <cross_reference>29 Conn.App. 519</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>523</cross_reference>, cert denied,<cross_reference>224 Conn. 923</cross_reference> (1992).

The court finds that, based upon the preponderance of the evidence, the Plaintiff has failed in his burden of proof for the following reasons. Prior to 1987 the Defendant was a close personal friend of the Plaintiff and his family. Until 2004 the Defendant was described as an extended part of the Perrotti family. The Plaintiff has three brothers, Paul, William, and Anthony. Paul is the Fire Chief of Middlebury. The Defendant was First Selectman of the Town of Middlebury from 1983-2007. In 1987 the Defendant and others rented a cottage in Rhode Island during the summer. The Defendant extended an open invitation to the Plaintiff, and others, to visit the cottage. The Plaintiff was 17 and a Junior Firefighter for the Town. The Defendant was in his mid-forties. The Plaintiff traveled to the cottage for a weekend. At the cottage that weekend were the Defendant Carl Bayer, who was in his late twenties; Desmarais, who was 18; Kales, who was 19 or 20; and the Foss family of CT Page 14585 four. There was much drinking at the cottage even by the Plaintiff and the other minors. The Plaintiff admitted at trial, however, that there was only one instance when the Defendant gave him a drink and that was when the Defendant showed him how to make a gin and tonic. In fact, in his statement to the police in 2005 the Plaintiff stated that another adult took him and his friends to a local package store where they gave the adult money to buy them beer. Although the Plaintiff claims that Kales and Desmarais were present prior to the incident and were also asked by the Defendant to streak, they deny it. Desmarais stated that he did not observe any inappropriate conduct by the Defendant or recall any talk about masturbation, streaking or naked parades. Kale claims that the Defendant danced on his bed in his boxers but he didn't witness any other inappropriate behavior by the Defendant and did not hear any conversation about streaking or masturbating. The morning after the alleged incident the Plaintiff suggested to the others that they play a prank on the Defendant and they did so.

After the alleged incident the Defendant continued to be a close friend of the Perrotti family. The Plaintiff continued to go to the Defendant's cottages in Rhode Island during the summers, continued to visit the firehouse where the Defendant often frequented, invited the Defendant to his wedding, and the Defendant attended the Plaintiff's brother's graduation as a Marine. The Plaintiff did not tell any one about the alleged incident until late 2004 during a conversation with his brother William at his restaurant. Although the impetus for the revelation at this time is less than clear to the court, it apparently was made after a political meeting at William's restaurant as some of the Defendant's political opponents, including William, were engaged in a conversation criticizing the Defendant and voicing their desire that they get rid of him as First Selectman. It was also not until that time that the Plaintiff informed his wife of eleven years of the incident. Although the Plaintiff also claimed that the revelation was made at that time because his brother Paul was asked by the Defendant to refer other Junior Firefighters to him to work in the summer, this practice had been going on for many years prior to that time with no reaction by the Plaintiff. He did not report the alleged incident to the police until July 2005 after consulting with an attorney in January 2005. This lawsuit itself was brought only days before the election in 2005 in which the Defendant was running for re-election as First Selectman. Although the Plaintiff claims that he has given consistent accounts of the event, there was no evidence that he told anyone of the incident until 17 years after it happened.

The Plaintiff introduced evidence of other alleged misconduct by the Defendant, and the court allowed it, pursuant to the rule that CT Page 14586 "[e]vidence of prior sex offenses committed with persons other than the prosecuting witness is admissible to show a common design or plan [when] the prior offenses (1) are not too remote in time; (2) are similar to the offense charged; and (3) are committed upon persons similar to the prosecuting witness." (Internal quotation marks omitted.) <italic>State v.</italic><italic>Jacobson</italic>, <cross_reference>283 Conn. 618</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>631</cross_reference> (2007). However, that evidence was the testimony of the Plaintiff's brothers and his brother-in-law. Paul Perrotti claimed that when he was 15 in 1983 in Rhode Island, the Defendant, on a bet, disrobed and walked down the road naked. As Fire Chief Paul has had many disagreements with the Defendant, one of which involved Paul reimbursing the town several thousand dollars because of improper cell phone use. He told the Plaintiff that the Defendant wanted to oust him as Fire Chief. William Perrotti claims that the Defendant asked him to streak in 1984 while on a trip with the Defendant to Rhode Island when he was 19 but he refused and it was not brought up again during the trip. William is the owner of a restaurant in Middlebury. He sued the Defendant in federal court regarding a building permit and admits to having been openly disdainful and distrustful of the Defendant for twenty years and blames the Defendant for many of his personal problems including problems in his marriage. William Calabrese claimed that in 2000, when he was 27, the Defendant and three other adults paraded naked on the deck of a house at night in Rhode Island. He is married to Paul Perrotti's sister. None of these incidents was revealed until after the Plaintiff instituted this suit. Even if one is to credit all of this testimony, it does not lend support to the Plaintiff's claims because none of these incidents involved any inappropriate touching by the Defendant as alleged here.

There was also no evidence linking the alleged incident to the Plaintiff's claims of emotion distress. The Plaintiff never saw a therapist or any other professional as a result of the alleged incident. Even after the alleged incident but prior to its disclosure, the Plaintiff was described as very social, a lot of fun, the life of the party, and a loving husband. It appeared to the court that his distress was the result of a failed marriage and the stresses of this lawsuit itself.

<center>                                 <italic>Conclusion</italic></center>
Therefore, based upon a preponderance of all the evidence, the court finds that the Plaintiff has failed to prove the allegations of his complaint and judgment shall enter for the Defendant.

</unpublished></opinion_text><unpublished><footnote_body><footnote_number>[fn1]</footnote_number> The Plaintiff brings this action under the authority of General Statutes ยง <cross_reference>52-577d</cross_reference> which provides "Notwithstanding the provisions of CT Page 14587 section <cross_reference>52-577</cross_reference>, no action to recover damages for personal injury to a minor, including emotional distress, caused by sexual abuse, sexual exploitation or sexual assault may be brought by such person later than thirty years from the date such person attains the age of majority."</footnote_body>

CT Page 14588

</unpublished>
</opinion>