<opinion unpublished=true>
<reporter_caption><center>SKAKEL v. STATE, No. FST CV 05 4006524 S (Apr. 3, 2007)</center></reporter_caption>
<caption><center>MICHAEL C. SKAKEL v. STATE OF CONNECTICUT.</center></caption>
<citation_line><center><citation>2007 Ct. Sup. 5287</citation></center></citation_line>
<docket><center>No. FST CV 05 4006524 S</center></docket><court><center>Connecticut Superior Court</center><center>Judicial District of Stamford-Norwalk at Stamford</center></court>
<date><center>April 3, 2007</center>

</date>
<opinion_text><unpublished><footnote_body>[EDITOR'S NOTE: This case is unpublished as indicated by the issuing court.]</footnote_body><center>                      <italic>MEMORANDUM OF DECISION RE MOTION</italic></center><center>                       <italic>FOR SUMMARY JUDGMENT (160.00)</italic></center></unpublished></opinion_text>
<opinion_byline><unpublished>  EDWARD R. KARAZIN, JUDGE.

</unpublished></opinion_byline>
<opinion_text><unpublished>  This matter comes to this court as a Motion For Summary Judgment. The petitioner filed a Reply Brief (162.00). Issue is joined by the parties. The defendant, State of Connecticut, has moved for a summary judgment on counts 5 and 6 of the Revised Substitute Petition For New Trial. The petitioners have withdrawn counts 5 and 8. Therefore, the Motion For Summary Judgment is moot as to count 5 and the court only addresses count 6. Count 6 addresses the profile reports prepared during the course of the homicide investigation.

The standard for a motion for summary judgment is that the court must view the evidence in the light most favorable to the non-moving party. The party seeking summary judgment has the burden of showing the absence of any genuine issue of material facts which under applicable principles of substantive law entitle the party to judgment as a matter of law.

Based on all the facts and circumstances involved in this issue, the court denies the Motion For Summary Judgment.

The court finds there is a genuine issue of material fact as to whether the profile reports are newly discovered in accordance with Conn. Gen. Statutes ยง <cross_reference>52-270</cross_reference>. In addition, the ruling of the Supreme Court on this issue as claimed by the defendant is not clear enough for this court to rule that it was adjudicated as a matter of law.

Accordingly, the Motion For Summary Judgment is denied.

CT Page 5288

</unpublished></opinion_text>
</opinion>