<opinion>
<reporter_caption><center>IN RE JOHN DOE, A MINOR, <citation>7 Haw. App. 575</citation> (1990)</center></reporter_caption>
<citation_line><center><citation>786 P.2d 519</citation></center></citation_line>
<caption><center>In the Matter of the Guardianship of the Person of JOHN DOE, a Minor</center></caption>
<docket><center>NO. 13759</center></docket><court><center>Hawaii Court of Appeals.</center></court>
<date><center>February 2, 1990</center>

</date>
<posture>  APPEAL FROM THE FAMILY COURT OF THE FIFTH CIRCUIT HONORABLE GERALD S. MATSUNAGA, JUDGE.

</posture><panel>  BURNS, C.J., HEEN AND TANAKA, JJ.

</panel>
<opinion_byline>  OPINION OF THE COURT BY BURNS, C.J.

</opinion_byline>
<opinion_text>  Petitioners, the paternal grandmother (PGM) and the paternal stepgrandfather (PSGF) of John Doe (Child), appeal the family court's March 17, 1989 Order Granting Temporary Guardianship (March 17, 1989 Order). Notwithstanding its title, the March 17, 1989 Order completed the adjudication of the guardianship proceeding and, therefore, is an appealable final order. We vacate the March 17, 1989 Order and remand for further proceedings consistent with this opinion.<page_number>Page 576</page_number>

The chronology of relevant events is as follows:

<table>
<bold>Date</bold>                    <bold>Event</bold>

May 26, 1986            Child's father (Father) and mother
                        (Mother) (collectively, "Parents") were
                        married in California.

December 16, 1986       Child was born in California.

December 31, 1987       According to Father, because they were
                        having financial and marital problems,
                        Parents gave temporary physical custody
                        of Child to PGM and PSGF, who
                        live in the County of Kauai, but who
                        were then visiting in California.

January 3, 1988         PGM and PSGF returned to Kauai with
                        Child.

Post-January 3, 1988 —  Father moved to Kauai.
Pre-November 16, 1988

November 16, 1988       PGM and PSGF filed, in Kauai, a Petition
                        for Appointment of Guardians of
                        the Person of Minor (November 16,
                        1988 Petition), FC-G 88-0009, seeking
                        their appointment as guardians of
                        Child's person, alleging that "[s]uch
                        appointment is necessary because
                        [Child's] parents are unable to care for
                        or support the child, and they have given
                        physical custody of [Child] to [PGM and
                        PSGF]." Record at 2.

December 8, 1988        Father and Child's paternal grandfather
                        filed consents to the November 16, 1988
                        Petition and waivers of further notice.

December 12, 1988       PGM, PSGF, and Parents stipulated to
                        order (December 12, 1988 Stipulated
                        Order). It states in relevant part:

                          1. An investigation and report shall
                          be made by the staff of the Family
                          Court of the Fifth Circuit, and the
<page_number>Page 577</page_number>

<bold>Date</bold>                    <bold>Event</bold>

                          corresponding agency in the State of
                          California where [Mother] resides.

                          2. [PGM and PSGF] shall have temporary
                          physical custody of [Child]
                          pending completion of the aforesaid
                          study and until further order of this
                          Court.

                                      *   *   *

                          4. None of the parties shall remove
                          the [Child] from the County of
                          Kauai, until further order of this
                          Court.

                        Record at 18.

December 13, 1988       In California, Mother filed a petition
                        for divorce from Father.

January 30, 1989        January 18, 1989 California social study
                        of Mother was filed.

January 31, 1989        Father filed UCCJ (Uniform Child Custody
                        Jurisdiction) 89-0001 in Kauai.

February 7, 1989        Daryl Y. Dobashi was appointed as
                        Child's Guardian Ad Litem.

March 16, 1989          Supplemental California social study of
                        Mother was filed.

March 17, 1989          The family court entered an "Order
                        Granting Temporary Guardianship". It
                        states in relevant part:

                            The primary concern of this
                          Court is the best interest of [Child].
                          The Court also believes that the
                          main objective herein should be to
                          build and maintain a safe environment
                          for the [C]hild, and to return
<page_number>Page 578</page_number>

<bold>Date</bold>                    <bold>Event</bold>

                          the [Child] to his natural parents or
                          parent as soon as feasible.

                                      *   *   *

                            The Court finds that [PGM and
                          PSGF], who are the paternal grandmother
                          and her husband, respectively,
                          are fit and proper persons to
                          be guardians, and that [Child], has
                          resided with [PGM and PSGF] since
                          January 1, 1988 in a stable and
                          wholesome home. The Court, however,
                          makes no finding as to the circumstances
                          of [PGM and PSGF's] obtaining
                          physical custody of [Child]
                          from the [Parents], those factual circumstances
                          being disputed by the
                          parties.

                            This Court therefore defers to
                          the jurisdiction of the Superior
                          Court, Ventura County, State of
                          California, where [Mother] has filed
                          a divorce action, to determine:

                            1. The circumstances of [PGM
                          and PSGF's] obtaining physical custody
                          of the [Child];

                            2. The fitness of [Mother] as a
                          proposed custodial parent;

                            3. The determination of permanent
                          or temporary custody of the
                          [Child].

                                    *   *   *

                            IT IS THEREFORE HEREBY
                          ORDERED that the Petition for Appointment
                          of Guardians is granted
                          insofar as the [PGM and PSGF] are
<page_number>Page 579</page_number>

<bold>Date</bold>                    <bold>Event</bold>

                          hereby appointed temporary guardians
                          of [Child], until such time as the
                          California Superior Court resolves
                          the issue of temporary or permanent
                          custody of the [Child] in the divorce
                          action pending in that State.

                                    *   *   *

                          If necessary, Child Psychologist Dianne
                          Girard shall examine the
                          [Child] to make recommendations as
                          to how this Court may order the return
                          or transfer of the minor child to
                          the natural parent(s) with the least
                          negative effects on the [Child.]

                        Record at 89-92.

April 5, 1989           PGM and PSGF filed a notice of appeal.

April 17, 1989          Father withdrew his December 8, 1988
                        waiver and consent.

October 30, 1989        According to Mother, the California divorce
                        decree was entered.

February 26, 1990       According to Father, the custody issue
                        in the California divorce case is set for
                        hearing on this date.
</table>
In this appeal, PGM and PSGF contend that the family court erred when it failed to grant their November 16, 1988 Petition. We conclude that the family court erred when it (1) appointed PGM and PSGF as temporary guardians for more than ninety days; (2) failed to decide whether the November 16, 1988 Petition was a petition for guardianship of the person or a petition for an award of Child's legal and physical custody or both; and (3) declined to decide the merits of the November 16, 1988 Petition.

<center>                               I.</center>
When the family court refused to assume jurisdiction over the major issues raised in the November 16, 1988 Petition and deferred<page_number>Page 580</page_number>
to the California court's jurisdiction in the California divorce case involving only Parents as parties, it effectively denied PGM and PSGF's November 16, 1988 Petition. Therefore, notwithstanding its misleading title, the March 17, 1989 Order is an appealable final order. <italic>See Gomes v. Heirs of Kauwe,</italic> <cross_reference>52 Haw. 126</cross_reference>,<cross_reference>472 P.2d 119</cross_reference> (1970).

<center>                               II.</center>
Hawaii Revised Statutes (HRS) § <cross_reference>560:5-207</cross_reference>(c) (1985) states: "If necessary, the family court may appoint a temporary guardian of the person, with the status of an ordinary guardian of the person of a minor, but the authority of such temporary guardian shall not last longer than ninety days."

Consequently, we <italic>sua sponte</italic> conclude that the March 17, 1989 appointment of PGM and PSGF as temporary guardians terminated on the ninety-first day thereafter.

<center>                              III.</center>
Upon a review of HRS chapters 571 (Family Courts), 577 (Children), 580 (Annulment, Divorce, Separation), 583 (Uniform Child Custody Jurisdiction Act), and 587 (Child Protective Act), we conclude that HRS chapter 560:5 (Protection of Persons Under Disability and Their Property) does not govern child custody disputes. However, nothing in the law precludes a petition for the award of legal and physical custody of a child or the award of physical custody and guardianship of the child's person.

The record reveals that PGM and PSGF desired to be awarded Child's legal and physical custody. That being so, the November 16, 1988 Petition should have been expressly based on HRS §§<cross_reference>571-11</cross_reference>(3), -46 (Supp. 1989). The material facts alleged in support of the November 16, 1988 Petition are PGM's and PSGF's physical custody of Child with the consent of Parents and Parents' inability to care for or support Child. In other words, PGM and PSGF implicitly concede that if they are not entitled to Child's physical custody they are not entitled to guardianship of Child's person.

HRS § <cross_reference>577-3</cross_reference> (1985) states, in relevant part, that "[t]he father and mother of an unmarried minor child are jointly the natural<page_number>Page 581</page_number>
guardians of the child's person and property." HRS § <cross_reference>577-7</cross_reference>(a) (1985) states, in relevant part, that "[p]arents or, in case they are both deceased, guardians, legally appointed, . . . shall have the right, at all times, to recover the physical custody of their children by habeas corpus".

On the subject of child custody, we recently stated that "HRS §<cross_reference>571-46</cross_reference>(1) accords priority to the child's parents. HRS Chapter 587 accords priority to the child's family as defined in HRS §<cross_reference>587-2</cross_reference>[.]" <italic>In the Interest of Jane Doe, born on June 4, 1987,</italic>
___ Haw. App. ___, slip op. at 10 (No. 13507, December 18, 1989). In other words, in a contest between the mother and the paternal grandmother for a child's custody, the mother must prevail absent a valid finding that she is not a fit and proper person or has a home that is not stable and wholesome.

In the absence of a valid court order to the contrary, Father and Mother are equally entitled to Child's custody. <italic>See Fujikane</italic><italic>v. Fujikane.</italic> <cross_reference>61 Haw. 352</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>604 P.2d 43</cross_reference> (1979). Consequently, if Father and/or Mother requests the physical custody of Child from PGM and PSGF, the request must be granted unless PGM and PSGF, desiring to continue physical custody, allege in good faith that both Father and Mother are not fit and proper persons and/or have homes that are not stable and wholesome.

<center>                           CONCLUSION</center>
Accordingly, we vacate the March 17, 1989 Order Granting Temporary Guardianship and remand for further proceedings consistent with this opinion.

</opinion_text><attorneys>  <italic>Lawrence D. McCreery</italic> on the briefs for paternal grandmother and paternal stepgrandfather of child, petitioners-appellants.

Mother of child, <italic>pro se</italic> appellee, on the brief.<page_number>Page 582</page_number>

</attorneys>
</opinion>