<opinion>
<reporter_caption><center>CARLISLE v. 1984 CHEVROLET CORVETTE, 24821 (Haw. 1-18-2002)</center></reporter_caption>
<caption><center>PETER B. CARLISLE, In his official capacity as the Prosecuting Attorney</center><center>of the City and County of Honolulu on behalf of the State of Hawai`i,</center><center>Petitioner, v. 1984 CHEVROLET CORVETTE, 2-DOOR, RED IN COLOR, HAWAII</center><center>LICENSE NUMBER JRB-464, VEHICLE IDENTIFICATION NO. 1G1AY0780E5150265</center><center>(ESTIMATED VALUE: $10,000.00), Defendant, INTERESTED PARTIES: NATHAN</center><center>D. PARK and SCOTT R. SPEAR.</center></caption>
<docket><center>24821</center></docket><court><center>Supreme Court of Hawaii.</center></court>
<date><center>January 18, 2002.</center>

</date>
<posture>  A.G. NO. 01-1540, [HPD Report No. 01-152533]

</posture><panel>  MOON, C.J., LEVINSON, NAKAYAM, RAMIL, and ACOBA, JJ.

</panel>
<opinion_text><center>                                   ORDER</center></opinion_text>
<opinion_text>  Upon consideration of the notice of appeal filed by Nathan D. Park, it appears that: (1) Park is appealing from the Attorney General's order granting a petition for administrative forfeiture and denying a petition for remission or mitigation filed by Scott Spear; (2) Park did not serve the notice of appeal as required by HRAP Rule 3, pay the filing fee, or move for waiver of the filing fee; (3) HRS ยง <cross_reference>712A-10</cross_reference> governs administrative forfeitures; (4) HRS ยง <cross_reference>712A-10</cross_reference>(11) provides that there shall be no appeal from the attorney general's decision or order of forfeiture or remission or mitigation; (5) It is well-settled that the right to appeal is purely statutory and exists only when given by some constitutional or statutory provision. <italic>Burke v. County of Maui</italic>,<cross_reference>95 Haw. 288</cross_reference>, 289, <cross_reference>22 P.3d 84</cross_reference>, 85 (2001); <italic>Oppenheimer v. AIG Hawai`i Ins.</italic><italic>Co</italic>., <cross_reference>77 Haw. 88</cross_reference>, 91, <cross_reference>881 P.2d 1234</cross_reference>, 1237 (1994); <italic>Chambers v. Leavey</italic>,<cross_reference>60 Haw. 52</cross_reference>, 57, <cross_reference>587 P.2d 807</cross_reference>, 810 (1978); and (6) Inasmuch as HRS ยง<cross_reference>712A-10</cross_reference>(11) provides that there shall be no appeal from the attorney general's decision or order of forfeiture, this court lacks jurisdiction to consider this appeal. Therefore,

IT IS HEREBY ORDERED that the notice of appeal is dismissed.

</opinion_text>
</opinion>