<opinion>
<reporter_caption><center>IN RE A MEMBER OF STATE BAR, FRANKLIN, SB-07-0181-D (Ariz. 1-8-2008)</center></reporter_caption>
<caption><center>IN THE MATTER OF A MEMBER OF THE STATE BAR OF ARIZONA, JOHN T. FRANKLIN,</center><center>Attorney No. 22163 Respondent.</center></caption>
<docket><center>Supreme Court No. SB-07-0181-D</center></docket><court><center>Supreme Court of Arizona.</center></court>
<date><center>January 8, 2008</center>

</date>
<posture>  State Bar of Arizona No. 07-1848.

</posture>
<opinion_text><center>                       <bold>ORDER OF INTERIM SUSPENSION</bold></center></opinion_text>
<opinion_byline>  RUTH V. McGREGOR, Chief Justice.

</opinion_byline>
<opinion_text>  A Motion for Interim Suspension was filed by the State Bar. Respondent<bold>John T Franklin</bold> filed a response. After considering the motion and response, the Court finds that the motion for interim suspension should be granted. Accordingly,

IT IS ORDERED, pursuant to Rule 61(c), Rules of the Supreme Court, that <bold>John T Franklin</bold> is hereby suspended from the practice of law, effective this date.

IT IS FURTHER ORDERED that the suspension shall continue in effect until final disposition of all pending proceedings against <bold>John T</bold><bold>Franklin</bold>, unless earlier vacated or modified.

IT IS FURTHER ORDERED that <bold>John T Franklin</bold>, from this date, shall not accept for representation any new cases, nor shall he agree to represent any existing client after the effective date of this Order.

IT IS FURTHER ORDERED that <bold>John T Franklin</bold> is precluded from distributing funds from any trust account to anyone except with the written approval of bar counsel or of this court.<page_number>Page 2</page_number>

IT IS FURTHER ORDERED that pursuant to Rule 72(a), Rules of the Supreme Court of Arizona, <bold>John T Franklin</bold> shall notify all his clients within ten (10) days from the date hereof of his inability to continue to represent them and that they should promptly retain new counsel, and shall promptly inform this Court of his compliance with this Order as provided by Rule 72(e), Rules of the Supreme Court of Arizona.

DATED this ___ day of January, 2008.

TO:

John T Franklin (Certified Mail, Return Receipt and Regular Mail)

Shauna R Miller, Bar Counsel, State Bar of Arizona

Nancy Swetnam, Acting Disciplinary Clerk (Cert. Copy)

Sandra Montoya, Records Manager, State Bar of Arizona (Cert. Copy)

Perry Thompson, Director, United States Supreme Court (Cert. Copy)

Cathy A. Catterson, Clerk, United States Court of Appeals for the Ninth Circuit (Cert. Copy)

Richard H. Weare, Clerk, United States District Court for the

District of Arizona (Cert. Copy)

Jode Ottman, West Publishing Company

<block_quote>  Lexis Nexis</block_quote><page_number>Page 1</page_number>

</opinion_text>
</opinion>