<opinion>
<reporter_caption><center>NEWKIRK v. NOTHWEHR, <citation>210 Ariz. 601</citation> (App. 2005)</center></reporter_caption>
<citation_line><center><citation>115 P.3d 1264</citation></center></citation_line>
<caption><center>Anthony Paul NEWKIRK, Petitioner, v. The Honorable Richard NOTHWEHR,</center><center>Commissioner of the Superior Court of the State of Arizona, in and for the</center><center>County of Maricopa, Respondent Judge, The State of Arizona, Real Party in</center><center>Interest.</center></caption>
<docket><center>No. 1 CA-SA 05-0061.</center></docket><court><center>Court of Appeals of Arizona.</center></court>
<date><center>June 23, 2005.</center>

</date>
<posture>  Appeal from the Superior Court, Maricopa County, No. CR 2003-030712, Richard Nothwehr, Commissioner.<page_number>Page 602</page_number>

</posture><attorneys>  Andrew Thomas, Maricopa County Attorney by Diane Gunnels Rowley, Deputy County Attorney, Phoenix, Attorneys for Real Party in Interest.

Neal W. Bassett, Laurie Herman, Phoenix, Attorneys for Petitioner.

</attorneys>
<opinion_text><center>                                 <bold>OPINION</bold></center></opinion_text>
<opinion_byline>  THOMPSON, Judge.

</opinion_byline>
<opinion_text>  ¶ 1 Anthony Paul Newkirk (petitioner) challenges the denial of his request to allow a jury to find a prior conviction. Petitioner contends that <italic>Derendal v. Griffith</italic>, <cross_reference>209 Ariz. 416</cross_reference>,<cross_reference>104 P.3d 147</cross_reference> (2005), resurrected the right to a jury trial on allegations of prior convictions. For the following reasons, we accept jurisdiction and deny relief.

<center>                     <bold>FACTUAL AND PROCEDURAL HISTORY</bold></center>  ¶ 2 Petitioner was charged with driving under the influence. The state filed an allegation of a prior conviction. Petitioner requested a jury trial on the allegation of prior conviction. The trial court denied the request. Petitioner then filed this special action.

<center>                              <bold>JURISDICTION</bold></center>  ¶ 3 The acceptance of jurisdiction in a special action is discretionary. <italic>King v. Superior Court</italic>, <cross_reference>138 Ariz. 147</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>149</cross_reference>,<cross_reference>673 P.2d 787</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>789</cross_reference> (1983) (citations omitted). We may accept special action jurisdiction when there is no other means of obtaining justice, id. (citing <italic>Nataros v. Superior Court of Maricopa</italic><italic>County</italic>, <cross_reference>113 Ariz. 498</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>557 P.2d 1055</cross_reference> (1976)), or where the issue is one of statewide importance, <italic>Citizens Clean Elections Comm'n</italic><italic>v. Myers</italic>, <cross_reference>196 Ariz. 516</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>517</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>1 P.3d 706</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>707</cross_reference> (2000).

  ¶ 4 Petitioner relies on <italic>Derendal</italic> to support his request for special action relief. The Arizona Supreme Court decided<italic>Derendal</italic> in January 2005. The issue is one of first impression that may have an impact on other cases. In addition, special action jurisdiction is appropriate to determine if there is a right to a jury trial. <italic>Campbell v. Superior Court</italic>,<cross_reference>186 Ariz. 526</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>527</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>924 P.2d 1045</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>1046</cross_reference> (App. 1996) (citing <italic>Mungarro v.</italic><italic>Riley</italic>, <cross_reference>170 Ariz. 589</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>590</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>826 P.2d 1215</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>1216</cross_reference> (App. 1991)). We therefore accept jurisdiction.<page_number>Page 603</page_number>

<center>                               <bold>DISCUSSION</bold></center>  ¶ 5 According to petitioner, defendants are entitled to jury trials on allegations of prior convictions. Arizona Revised Statutes (A.R.S.) § <cross_reference>13-604</cross_reference>(P) (2004) provides that a prior conviction is to be found by the court. <italic>See also</italic>
Ariz. R.Crim. P. 19.1(b)(2) (stating that trial court shall determine allegation or prior conviction). In <italic>State v. Quinonez</italic>,<cross_reference>194 Ariz. 18</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>20</cross_reference>, ¶ <cross_reference>12</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>976 P.2d 267</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>269</cross_reference> (App. 1999), we upheld the constitutionality of A.R.S. § <cross_reference>13-604</cross_reference>(P) and clarified that prior conviction trials were no longer jury eligible.

  ¶ 6 In <italic>Quinonez</italic>, the defendant requested a jury trial on an allegation of a historical prior felony conviction, and the trial court denied the request under A.R.S. § <cross_reference>13-604</cross_reference>(P). <italic>Id.</italic> at 19, ¶ 3, <cross_reference>976 P.2d at 268</cross_reference>. The defendant argued that A.R.S. § <cross_reference>13-604</cross_reference>(P) violated his constitutional right to a jury trial under the<cross_reference>Sixth Amendment to the United States Constitution</cross_reference> as well as Article <cross_reference>2</cross_reference>, Section <cross_reference>24</cross_reference> of the Arizona Constitution. <italic>Id.</italic> at ¶ 4 (citation omitted). The court noted that the defendant had tradition on his side because, from at least 1887 to the 1996 amendment to A.R.S. § <cross_reference>13-604</cross_reference>(P), Arizona granted a jury trial on an allegation of prior convictions to criminal defendants. <italic>Id.</italic> at ¶ 5 (citing<italic>State v. Armstrong</italic>, <cross_reference>103 Ariz. 174</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>179-81</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>438 P.2d 411</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>416-18</cross_reference>
(1968) (Bernstein, J., dissenting), <italic>vacated on other grounds</italic>,<cross_reference>103 Ariz. 280</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>440 P.2d 307</cross_reference> (1968), and Arizona Penal Code of 1887, § 1714). The court noted that the majority in <italic>Armstrong</italic>
agreed that the state constitutional provision guaranteeing the right to a jury trial was violated where a trial judge refused a defendant's request for a jury trial on an allegation of a prior conviction. <italic>Id.</italic> at ¶ 6 (citing <italic>Armstrong</italic>, <cross_reference>103 Ariz. at 177</cross_reference>,<cross_reference>438 P.2d at 414</cross_reference>). Although <italic>Armstrong's</italic> reference to the constitution seemed to support the defendant's argument,<italic>Quinonez</italic> noted that the reference is dictum because in<italic>Armstrong</italic> the defendant admitted the prior conviction. <italic>Id.</italic>

  ¶ 7 The <italic>Quinonez</italic> court noted that more recent cases dispelled any notion that a constitutional right to a jury trial exists on an allegation of a prior conviction. <italic>Id.</italic> at 19-20, ¶ 6,<cross_reference>976 P.2d at 268-69</cross_reference>. For example, in <italic>State ex rel. Neely v.</italic><italic>Sherrill</italic>, <cross_reference>168 Ariz. 469</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>472</cross_reference> n. 2, <cross_reference>815 P.2d 396</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>399</cross_reference> n. 2 (1991), the court stated that the use of a jury to determine a prior conviction is not constitutionally mandated but only required by statute in Arizona. <italic>Quinonez</italic>, <cross_reference>194 Ariz. at 20</cross_reference>, ¶ <cross_reference>7</cross_reference>,<cross_reference>976 P.2d at 269</cross_reference>. In <italic>State v. Hurley</italic>, <cross_reference>154 Ariz. 124</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>127</cross_reference>,<cross_reference>741 P.2d 257</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>260</cross_reference> (1987), the Arizona Supreme Court stated that its research did not reveal any constitutional basis for the requirement of a jury trial on prior convictions in Arizona.<italic>Quinonez</italic>, <cross_reference>194 Ariz, at 20</cross_reference>, ¶ <cross_reference>7</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>976 P.2d at 269</cross_reference>. In addition,<italic>Quinonez</italic> noted that the Ninth Circuit "squarely holds that a defendant has no right to a jury trial on a sentence-enhancing allegation of prior conviction." <italic>Id.</italic> at ¶ 8 (citing <italic>United</italic><italic>States v. Kinsey</italic>, <cross_reference>843 F.2d 383</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>391-92</cross_reference> (9th Cir. 1988) (distinguishing between enhancement statutes and substantive crimes and concluding that enhancements do not create criminal charges that necessarily guarantee a right to a jury)).

  ¶ 8 After reviewing these cases, <italic>Quinonez</italic> determined that, because a sentencing allegation is not a "constituent element" of a crime, the constitutional right of a jury trial does not apply to it. <italic>Id.</italic> at ¶ 9. The court held that, "[a]lthough, prior to 1996, the Arizona legislature traditionally granted criminal defendants the right to a jury trial on an allegation of historical prior felony conviction, that right is not guaranteed by the constitution, and its revocation does not offend the constitution." <italic>Id.</italic> at ¶ 12 (citation omitted).

  ¶ 9 Petitioner argues that <italic>Derendal</italic> resurrects the right to have a jury find prior convictions. In <italic>Derendal</italic>, the defendant was charged with misdemeanor drag racing, and the trial court denied his request for a jury trial. <cross_reference>209 Ariz. at 417</cross_reference>, ¶ <cross_reference>2</cross_reference>,<cross_reference>104 P.3d at 148</cross_reference>. The Arizona Supreme Court accepted review to determine when the Arizona Constitution mandates that a criminal offense be eligible for a jury trial. <italic>Id.</italic> at ¶ 4. The court formulated a two-part test to determine whether misdemeanor offenses were jury eligible. <italic>Id.</italic> at 425, ¶ 36, <cross_reference>104 P.3d at 156</cross_reference>. The first inquiry is whether a statutory offense has a common-law antecedent that guaranteed a jury trial at the time of Arizona statehood. <italic>Id.</italic> If so, the inquiry ends, and the defendant has established a right to a jury trial. <italic>Id.</italic> If<page_number>Page 604</page_number>
not, the court must analyze the seriousness of the offense under Article <cross_reference>2</cross_reference>, Section <cross_reference>24</cross_reference> of the Arizona Constitution. <italic>Id.</italic> at ¶ 37. Under <italic>Derendal</italic>, a finding that an act is of moral turpitude, as previously set forth in <italic>Rothweiler v. Superior Court</italic>,<cross_reference>100 Ariz. 37</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>42</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>410 P.2d 479</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>483</cross_reference> (1966), and <italic>State v. Harrison</italic>,<cross_reference>164 Ariz. 316</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>317</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>792 P.2d 779</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>780</cross_reference> (App. 1990), is no longer enough to afford a jury trial for an offense. <italic>Id.</italic> at ¶¶ 36-37. Therefore, <italic>Derendal</italic> does not expand the right to trial by jury but rather restricts it by no longer requiring jury trials for offenses of moral turpitude.

  ¶ 10 Petitioner contends that the Arizona Constitution's provision that "the right to trial by jury shall remain inviolate" mandates that anything entitled to a jury trial at the time of statehood, such as an allegation of a prior conviction, still retains that right today. Petitioner argues that "[n]o matter what we call the issue that is on trial, if it was tried to a jury during territorial days, it is tried to a jury today." A prior conviction, however, is not a common-law offense but rather a sentencing enhancement. <italic>See Apprendi v. New Jersey</italic>,<cross_reference>530 U.S. 466</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>485-87</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>120 S.Ct. 2348</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>147 L.Ed.2d 435</cross_reference> (2000) (quoting <italic>McMillan v. Pennsylvania</italic>, <cross_reference>477 U.S. 79</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>87-88</cross_reference>,<cross_reference>106 S.Ct. 2411</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>91 L.Ed.2d 67</cross_reference> (1986)) (sentencing enhancement does not create a separate offense calling for a separate penalty). Petitioner's attempt to liken an allegation of a prior conviction to a common-law <italic>offense</italic> that retains the right to a jury trial under <italic>Derendal</italic> — because it enjoyed the right to jury trial before Arizona's statehood — fails.

  ¶ 11 According to petitioner, because <italic>Quinonez</italic> acknowledges that prior convictions were tried to juries from 1887 to 1996,<cross_reference>194 Ariz. at 19</cross_reference>, ¶ <cross_reference>5</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>976 P.2d at 268</cross_reference>, and <italic>Derendal</italic> holds that a defendant is entitled to a jury if the crime was jury eligible at the time of statehood, <cross_reference>209 Ariz. at 425</cross_reference>, ¶ <cross_reference>36</cross_reference>,<cross_reference>104 P.3d at 156</cross_reference>, defendants retain the right to a jury determination of prior convictions. <italic>Derendal</italic>, however, did not address sentencing enhancements or whether an allegation of prior conviction is jury eligible. Rather, it only directed trial courts in determining whether a misdemeanor <italic>offense</italic> is jury eligible. <italic>Id.</italic>
at 425-26, ¶ 40, <cross_reference>104 P.3d at 156-57</cross_reference>.

  ¶ 12 As <italic>Quinonez</italic> and the cases that court cites make clear, the right to a jury trial on an allegation of prior conviction was statutory under both the territorial penal code and Arizona Revised Statutes until 1996. Thus, an allegation of prior conviction has no <italic>common-law</italic> antecedent that would require a jury under <italic>Derendal.</italic>

  ¶ 13 In <italic>Blakely v. Washington</italic>, <cross_reference>542 U.S. 296</cross_reference>, ___,<cross_reference>124 S.Ct. 2531</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>2536</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>159 L.Ed.2d 403</cross_reference> (2004) (citing <italic>Apprendi</italic>,<cross_reference>530 U.S. 466</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>120 S.Ct. 2348</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>147 L.Ed.2d 435</cross_reference>), the United States Supreme Court reaffirmed that "the fact of a prior conviction" need not be found by a jury to satisfy the United States Constitution.<italic>Apprendi</italic> notes that, when the sentencing enhancement is the fact of prior conviction, "the certainty that procedural safeguards attached to any `fact' of prior conviction . . . mitigated the due process and <cross_reference>Sixth Amendment</cross_reference> concerns otherwise implicated in allowing a judge to determine a `fact' increasing punishment beyond the maximum of the statutory range."<cross_reference>530 U.S. at 488</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>120 S.Ct. 2348</cross_reference> (citing <italic>Almendarez-Torres v.</italic><italic>United States</italic>, <cross_reference>523 U.S. 224</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>118 S.Ct. 1219</cross_reference>, <cross_reference>140 L.Ed.2d 350</cross_reference> (1998)).

  ¶ 14 Petitioner has not established the right to a jury trial on an allegation of a prior conviction, and the trial court did not err in denying his request for a jury trial on that basis.

<center>                               <bold>CONCLUSION</bold></center>  ¶ 15 For the foregoing reasons, we accept special action jurisdiction and deny relief.

DONN KESSLER, Presiding Judge, and PATRICK IRVINE, Judge, concur.

<page_number>Page 1</page_number>

</opinion_text>
</opinion>