<opinion>
<reporter_caption><center>RE AMENDING ARIZ. CODE OF JUD. § 6-204.01, 2009-79 (Ariz. 7-23-2009)</center></reporter_caption>
<caption><center>In the Matter of: AMENDING ARIZONA CODE OF JUDICIAL ADMINISTRATION</center><center>§ 6-204.01: INTERSTATE COMPACT PROBATION EVIDENCE BASED PRACTICE.</center></caption>
<docket><center>Administrative Order No. 2009-79</center></docket><court><center>Supreme Court of Arizona.</center></court>
<date><center>July 23, 2009.</center>

</date>
<posture>  Affecting Administrative Order No. 2009-39.

</posture>
<opinion_byline>  REBECCA WHITE BERCH, Chief Justice.

</opinion_byline>
<opinion_text>  Pursuant to the Arizona Code of Judicial Administration § <cross_reference>1-201</cross_reference> (E), the Chief Justice may adopt emergency administrative code proposals and technical changes in existing code sections by administrative order without prior distribution for comment and action by the Arizona Judicial Council.

Now, therefore, pursuant to Article <cross_reference>VI</cross_reference>, Section <cross_reference>3</cross_reference>, of the Arizona Constitution,

IT IS ORDERED that Arizona Code of Judicial Administration § 6-204.01 is amended as indicated on the attached document. All other provisions of § 6-204.01 as adopted, remain unchanged and in effect.

Dated this <underline>23rd</underline> day of <underline>July</underline>, 2009.<page_number>Page 2</page_number>

<center>                  <bold>ARIZONA CODE OF JUDICIAL ADMINISTRATION</bold></center><center>                             <bold>Part 6: Probation</bold></center><center>                         <bold>Chapter 2: Adult Services</bold></center><center>               <bold>Section 6-204.01: Interstate Compact Probation</bold> <bold>Evidence-Based Practices</bold></center> <bold>Courts shall be governed by section <cross_reference>6-204</cross_reference>, except and until approved by</bold><bold>the Administrative Director to be governed by section 6-204.01.</bold>
 <bold>Sections A through H — No changes</bold>
 <bold>I. Direct Case.</bold>

1. The interstate compact probation officer's direct caseload shall include:

<block_quote>  a. Probationers accepted for supervision who are residing in the officer's county and receiving supervision services, regardless of supervision level;</block_quote>

<block_quote>  b. Probationers in residential treatment in the officer's county; and</block_quote>

<block_quote>  c. Probationers in short term residential treatment in another county.</block_quote>

2. The interstate compact probation<strikethrough>er's</strikethrough> <underline>officer's</underline> direct caseload shall not include:

<block_quote>  a. Probationers pending acceptance of supervision in the officer's county, regardless of where they may be residing;</block_quote>

<block_quote>  b. Probationers in long term residential treatment in another county;</block_quote>

<block_quote>  c. Probationers considered absconders; and</block_quote>

<block_quote>  d. Probationers who have been retaken by the sending state.</block_quote>
 <bold>Sections J through Q — No changes</bold><page_number>Page 1</page_number>

</opinion_text>
</opinion>