<opinion>
<reporter_caption><center>IN MATTER OF THE RESIGNATION OF ETHAN R. HASENSTEIN, 51796 (Nev. 7-11-2008)</center></reporter_caption>
<caption><center>IN THE MATTER OF THE RESIGNATION OF ATTORNEY ETHAN R. HASENSTEIN.</center></caption>
<docket><center>No. 51796</center></docket><court><center>Supreme Court of Nevada.</center></court>
<date><center>July 11, 2008.</center>

</date>
<opinion_text><center>                 <bold>ORDER GRANTING PETITION FOR RESIGNATION</bold></center>
This is a joint petition by the State Bar of Nevada and attorney Ethan R. Hasenstein for his resignation from the Nevada bar. Hasenstein states that he is aware that his resignation is irrevocable.<footnote_reference>[fn1]</footnote_reference>

Bar counsel has recommended that the resignation be approved, and the Board of Governors has approved the petition for resignation. The petition includes statements from State Bar staff confirmation that no disciplinary matters, fee disputes, or Client Security Fund matters are pending against Hasenstein, and that he is current on all membership fee payments and other financial commitments relating to his practice of law in this state.

SCR 98(5)(a) provides that Nevada attorneys who are not actively practicing law in this state may resign from the State Bar if certain conditions are met:

<block_quote>Any member of the state bar who is not actively engaged in the practice of law in this state, upon written application on a form approved by the state bar, may resign from membership in the state bar if the member: (1) has no discipline, fee dispute arbitration, or clients' security fund matters pending and (2) is current on all membership fee payments and other financial commitments relating to the member's practice of law in Nevada. Such resignation shall become effective when filed with the state bar, accepted by the board of governors, and approved by the supreme court.</block_quote>

The petition satisfies the requirements of SCR 98(5). Accordingly, we grant the petition and approve Hasenstein's resignation.

It is so ORDERED.

Gibbons, C.J.

Maupin, J.

Hardesty, J.

Parraguiree, J.

Douglas, J.

Cherry, J.

Saitta, J.

<footnote_body><footnote_number>[fn1]</footnote_number> <italic>See</italic> SCR 98(5)(c).</footnote_body>

</opinion_text>
</opinion>