<opinion unpublished=true>
<reporter_caption><center>PETITIONS FOR REVIEW, <citation>328 Or. 418</citation> (1999)</center></reporter_caption>                           <bold>PETITIONS FOR REVIEW</bold><court><center>Oregon Supreme Court.</center></court>
<date><center>1999.</center>

</date><unpublished><footnote_body>[EDITOR'S NOTE: This case is unpublished as indicated by the issuing court.]</footnote_body><center>                                 <bold>ALLOWED</bold></center><center>                              <bold>April 6, 1999</bold></center>
Parrott and Forshey v. Carr Chevrolet, Inc. (A88512) (S45916) (<cross_reference>156 Or. App. 257</cross_reference>) (petition of Parrott)

Parrott and Forshey v. Carr Chevrolet, Inc. (A88512) (S45917) (<cross_reference>156 Or. App. 257</cross_reference>) (petition of Carr Chevrolet)

<center>                             <bold>April 13, 1999</bold></center>
Crocker and Crocker (A99888) (S46166) (<cross_reference>157 Or. App. 651</cross_reference>)

State v. Selness, Ronald Wayne (A89706) (S46149) (<cross_reference>154 Or. App. 579</cross_reference>)

Webber v. Olsen (A98055) (S46063) (<cross_reference>157 Or. App. 585</cross_reference>)

<center>                                 <bold>DENIED</bold></center><center>                              <bold>April 6, 1999</bold></center>
Deason, Ronald L. v. Thompson (A102246) (S46159) (<cross_reference>158 Or. App. 246</cross_reference>)

First Commerce of America, Inc. v. Nimbus Center Associates (A93182) (S45921) (<cross_reference>153 Or. App. 561</cross_reference>)

Hanzo v. deParrie (A94099) (S45702) (<cross_reference>152 Or. App. 525</cross_reference>)

Holterman, Daniel v. Armenakis (A99821) (S46095) (<cross_reference>157 Or. App. 396</cross_reference>)

Lange, Chris v. Thompson (A97844) (S46153) (<cross_reference>157 Or. App. 600</cross_reference>)

Oregon Occupational Safety  Health Division v. Eslinger Logging, Inc. (A92225) (S46087) (<cross_reference>156 Or. App. 519</cross_reference>). Van Hoomissen, J., would allow.

Russell v. Waldron and State of Oregon (A94478) (S45355) (<cross_reference>153 Or. App. 123</cross_reference>)

State v. Beaston, Everett Wendell (A102016) (S46066) (<cross_reference>157 Or. App. 724</cross_reference>) (supplemental petition for review)

State v. Capell, Matthew Monroe (A94532) (S46143) (<cross_reference>156 Or. App. 582</cross_reference>). Durham, J., would allow.

State v. Garvey, Mark Edward (A99483) (S46161) (<cross_reference>157 Or. App. 397</cross_reference>)

State v. Goldsborough, Roy Lee (A98362) (S46154) (<cross_reference>158 Or. App. 144</cross_reference>)

State v. Maher, Patrick Brian (A98532) (S46074) (<cross_reference>157 Or. App. 723</cross_reference>)

State v. Mitchell, Joseph Luther (A95543) (S46197) (<cross_reference>158 Or. App. 248</cross_reference>)

State v. Peacock, Howard Albert (A96754) (S46025) (<cross_reference>157 Or. App. 398</cross_reference>)

State v. Schlappie, Timothy Charles (A100310) (S46211) (<cross_reference>158 Or. App. 248</cross_reference>)

Stokes, Laurie Anne v. State of Oregon (A96608) (S46091) (<cross_reference>157 Or. App. 114</cross_reference>)

Wilkins v. Frink and State of Oregon (A98198) (S46162) (<cross_reference>158 Or. App. 76</cross_reference>)

Williams, Carlos v. Thompson (A96930) (S46068) (<cross_reference>155 Or. App. 644</cross_reference>)

<center>                             <bold>April 13, 1999</bold></center>
Domingo v. Anderson (A101189) (S46073) (<cross_reference>157 Or. App. 396</cross_reference>)

Eugene Police Employees' Association v. City of Eugene (A99251) (S46160) (<cross_reference>157 Or. App. 341</cross_reference>). Carson C.J., and Van Hoomissen, J., would allow.

Potts, David P. v. Baldwin (A99225) (S46200) (<cross_reference>158 Or. App. 683</cross_reference>)

State ex rel Juvenile Department of Coos County v. Flores (A99446-49) (S46155) (<cross_reference>158 Or. App. 144</cross_reference>)<page_number>Page 419</page_number>

</unpublished>
</opinion>