<opinion>
<reporter_caption><center>COMM OFFICERS v. ALLEN PARK (ON REM), <citation>219 Mich. App. 251</citation> (1996)</center></reporter_caption>
<citation_line><center><citation>556 N.W.2d 185</citation></center></citation_line>
<caption><center>COMMAND OFFICERS ASSOCIATION OF MICHIGAN v CITY OF ALLEN PARK (ON REMAND)</center></caption>
<docket><center>Docket No. 196011.</center></docket><court><center>Michigan Court of Appeals.</center></court><hearing_date><center>Submitted July 5, 1996, at Lansing.</center></hearing_date>
<date><center>Decided October 4, 1996, at 9:05 A.M.</center><page_number>Page 252</page_number>

</date><attorneys>  <italic>Stephen P Whitaker</italic>, for the Command Officers Association of Michigan and Kenneth Dobson.

<italic>Pagnucco</italic>, <italic>Kruse</italic>, <italic>Tamsen  Labadie</italic>, <italic>P.C.</italic> (by <italic>Kenneth D. Kruse</italic>
and <italic>Deborah L.E. Green</italic>), for the City of Allen Park.

<italic>Judith Sawicki</italic>, for the City of Allen Park Fire  Police Civil Service Commission.

</attorneys>
<opinion_text><center>                                ON REMAND</center></opinion_text><panel>  Before: FITZGERALD, P.J., and MICHAEL J. KELLY and MARKEY, JJ.

</panel>
<opinion_byline>  FITZGERALD, P.J.

</opinion_byline>
<opinion_text>  This case is before us on remand from the Supreme Court.<footnote_reference>[fn1]</footnote_reference> A panel of this Court previously reversed the trial court's decision to uphold a decision by the City of Allen Park Fire 
Police Civil Service Commission to discipline petitioner Kenneth Dobson, a policeman with the Allen Park Police Department, on the ground that the charges against Dobson were not filed within the ninety-day limitation period of MCL<cross_reference>38.514</cross_reference>; MSA 5.3364.<footnote_reference>[fn2]</footnote_reference> In reversing, the panel noted that it was bound by another panel's decision in <italic>Goodridge v Ypsilanti Twp</italic><italic>Bd</italic>, <cross_reference>209 Mich. App. 344</cross_reference>,<page_number>Page 253</page_number>
347; <cross_reference>529 N.W.2d 665</cross_reference> (1995), that "all charges filed after ninety days from the date of the violation are void." The panel disagreed with the holding in <italic>Goodridge</italic> and noted that, but for<italic>Goodridge</italic>, it would hold that the ninety-day limitation period of MCL <cross_reference>38.514</cross_reference>; MSA 5.3364 did not begin to run until the discharging authority had actual knowledge of an employment violation.<footnote_reference>[fn3]</footnote_reference> Consequently, the panel would have affirmed the decision of the trial court.

The Supreme Court, in lieu of granting leave to appeal, reversed <italic>Goodridge</italic> and our prior opinion in this case and remanded this case "for further consideration in light of this opinion." The Supreme Court held that MCL <cross_reference>38.514</cross_reference>; MSA 5.3364 should be interpreted to provide that charges against a member of any fire or police department are timely if filed within ninety days of the time the employer learned, or reasonably should have learned, of the alleged misconduct. Consistent with the Supreme Court's holding in <italic>Goodridge</italic> and with the analysis in our prior opinion, we now hold that, because the police department did not have knowledge of Dobson's violations until June 9, 1992, and the charges were brought against Dobson on September 1, 1992, no violation of MCL <cross_reference>38.514</cross_reference>; MSA 5.3364 occurred.

Affirmed.

<footnote_body><footnote_number>[fn1]</footnote_number> <italic>Goodridge v Ypsilanti Twp Bd</italic>, <cross_reference>451 Mich. 446</cross_reference>; <cross_reference>547 N.W.2d 668</cross_reference>
(1996).</footnote_body>

<footnote_body><footnote_number>[fn2]</footnote_number> <italic>Command Officers Ass'n of Michigan v Allen Park</italic>, <cross_reference>210 Mich. App. 485</cross_reference>;  <cross_reference>534 N.W.2d 258</cross_reference> (1995).</footnote_body>

<footnote_body><footnote_number>[fn3]</footnote_number> Judge MICHAEL J. KELLY concurred in the result only, stating his belief that <italic>Goodridge</italic> was not wrongly decided by the Court of Appeals.</footnote_body><page_number>Page 254</page_number>

</opinion_text>
</opinion>