<opinion>
<reporter_caption>                           <underline>Opinion No. <citation>2010-065</citation></underline></reporter_caption>
<caption>                               Randy Laverty</caption><court>                  Attorney General of Arkansas — Opinion</court>
<date>                     Opinion Delivered August 16, 2010<page_number>Page 1</page_number>

</date>
<opinion_byline>  DUSTIN McDANIEL, Attorney General

</opinion_byline>
<opinion_text>  The Honorable Randy Laverty State Senator Post Office Box 303 Jasper, Arkansas 72641-0303

Dear Senator Laverty:

This is my response to your questions about state regulation of electric cooperatives, as follows:

<block_quote>  1. Does the Arkansas Public Service Commission and/or Attorney General's office have jurisdiction and/or oversight on matters relating to Arkansas electric cooperatives democratic governance issues, specifically board accountability to its members/owners?</block_quote>

<block_quote>  2. If so, which statute and/or regulation allows for jurisdiction and oversight, and what process within the appropriate agency is in place to ensure compliance?</block_quote>

<heading><bold>RESPONSE</bold></heading>
Although your questions are general and do not refer to any particular facts or parties, they appear to relate directly to a case now before the Arkansas Court of Appeals. <italic>See Capps v.</italic><italic>Carroll Electric Coop. Corp.</italic>, Case No. CA 10-667. I have a statutory duty to render my opinion to legislators and other state officials on certain matters of state law (<italic>see</italic> A.C.A. § <cross_reference>25-16-706</cross_reference> (Repl. 2002)), but my office follows a long-standing policy against issuing opinions on matters that are in litigation. <italic>See, e.g.</italic>, Op. Att'y Gen. <cross_reference>2009-089</cross_reference> and 2007-039 (and opinions cited therein). I must therefore respectfully decline to issue an opinion on these<page_number>Page 2</page_number>
questions. Any opinion from my office would be executive comment on questions properly before a court.

Assistant Attorney General J. M. Barker prepared this opinion, which I approve.

Sincerely,

DUSTIN McDANIEL Attorney General<page_number>Page 1</page_number>

</opinion_text>
</opinion>